<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of Philoxypes and Polycrite, as it was told by Leontides to the great Cyrus. / Englished out of French, by an honourable anti-Socordist.</title>
            <author>Scudéry, Madeleine de, 1607-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 228 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 101 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92766</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2159A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R183636</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077609</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077609</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151701</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92766)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151701)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2272:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of Philoxypes and Polycrite, as it was told by Leontides to the great Cyrus. / Englished out of French, by an honourable anti-Socordist.</title>
                  <author>Scudéry, Madeleine de, 1607-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 187 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Humphrey Moseley, and are to be sold at his shop in St. Pauls Church-yard at the sign of the Prince's Arms,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Madeleine de Scudéry by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Errors in paging: 142-143 numbered 141-142.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:151701:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
THE HISTORY OF PHILOXYPES AND POLYCRITE, As it was told by <hi>LEONTIDES</hi> to the great CYRUS.</p>
            <p>Engliſhed out of <hi>French,</hi> by an Honourable ANTI-SOCORDIST.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Ex pede Hercules.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Humphrey Moſeley,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in S<hi rend="sub">t</hi> 
               <hi>Pauls Church-yard</hi> at the ſign of the Prince's Arms. 1652.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151701:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151701:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151701:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151701:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:151701:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151701:4"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY OF PHILOXYPES AND POLICRITE: As it was told by <hi>Leontidas,</hi> to <hi>Arta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mene,</hi> or the great <hi>Cyrus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT you may the better underſtand this Story, it is requiſite that you know part of the Cuſtomes of this Iſland, the which I will in a few words acquaint you with, that my enſuing Diſcourſe may appear leſſe tedious to you. You muſt then know, Sir, that this goodly Iſland,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151701:5"/>
which for its precinct, ſituation, fertility, for the beauty and greatnes of its Towns, and its Magnificent Temples, paſſeth for the moſt famous and moſt conſiderable of as many as lie on the <hi>Aegean Sea,</hi> hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been conſecrated to <hi>Venus;</hi> and that love, which every where elſe is a paſſion, which hath no particular priviledges, is in this place accounted a religious act. All that are born here, ſeem as if they were bound to love from their very birth; all the Temples are dedicated to <hi>Venus,</hi> under ſeveral name<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; all the pictures and ſtatues here, repreſent only this Goddeſs, and depend only upon her. You ſhall finde here <hi>Cupid</hi> ſet out every where, and thoſe who inſtruct us elſewhere virtuouſly in our youth, by teaching us how to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ambition, anger, hatred, envy, and all other paſſions; deal otherwiſe with us here, perſwading us only how to love in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocently. But as there is nothing ſo pure or refined, which meets not with alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and corruption at the laſt; a ſtrange diſorder crope in long ſince amongſt us: for you muſt know the firſt Temple which was conſecrated to <hi>Venus,</hi> was that of <hi>Venus Urania,</hi> who we ſay, is the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151701:5"/>
of Heaven. This <hi>Venus</hi> as we believe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpires only rational reſentments, and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous paſſions: whereas on the contrary, there are ſome Temples on the utmoſt borders of the Iſle towards the South, built long ſince the former, which are dedicated to <hi>Venus Anodema,</hi> as much as to ſay, to <hi>Venus</hi> comming forth from the foam of the ſea. Now Sir, theſe Temples doe differ very much, as doe their reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, who offer ſacrifices at them; yet as thoſe Religions wherein Libertiniſm paſſeth for a vertue, are grounded with moſt eaſe, the Religion of <hi>Venus Anadio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena,</hi> hath for a long time prevailed over that of <hi>Venus Urania;</hi> and our Iſland hath ſeen things which makes thoſe even bluſh with confuſion, who remember they have heard them ſpoken of by their forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: but thanks to Heaven, a vertuous Queen, who lived ſome ſixty years ſince, did re-eſtabliſh all the Temples of <hi>Venus Urania;</hi> made almoſt all thoſe of <hi>Venus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadiomena,</hi> be beaten down; aboliſht all the ſhameful cuſtomes which were intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and left only pure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments amongſt us of that paſſion, which is the ſoul of the Univerſe, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151701:6"/>
which is the ſole entertainer of civil ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. We are now taught to love our God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe, our Princes, our Laws, our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, our fellow-Citizens, our Parents, Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, Wives and Children; and laſtly, to love our ſelves, to the end that we may do no ſhameful act. We are taught alſo to love Glory, Sciences and Arts; to love in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent paſtimes, and to love beauty and vertue above all that hath been ſpoken of: in fine, we are taught that he who loves not, is not rational, and that not to have a ſenſe of all theſe aforementio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned things, is to be very much to blame. You may eaſily imagine then, that this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a belief generally held amongſt us, the Court of <hi>Cyprus</hi> muſt needs be a pleaſing abode, ſince every one there loves hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome actions, and handſome perſonages. True it is, that according to the rules of <hi>Venus Urania,</hi> the love by her permitted, is ſo pure, ſo innocent, ſo free from having any thing to doe with the ſenſes, and ſo free from fault, as ſhe ſeems to ſuffer us to love others only, that we may make our ſelves become the more lovely, through our care of meriting true glory, of becoming accompliſht, and of getting
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151701:6"/>
that Courtly Air, and pleaſing converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is only inſpired by love. This Sir, is the preſent condition of our Iſland; all delights are here, but all innocent. Love is the predominant, and univerſall paſſion in it, but ſuch a paſſion, as is not incompatible with vertue and modeſty, and which hinders not many lovers from complaining of their Miſtreſſes rigour. Publick feſtivals are here frequent, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation free enough, but wholly ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, games for prizes very uſual, pleaſing Bals, excellent Muſick, and Women in general, infinitely handſome, full of gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry, and perfectly vertuous. But of all the reſt, the Princeſſe of <hi>Salmis,</hi> ſiſter to <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> was the Court-Star, till ſuch time as ſhe withdrew her ſelf from thence. The Princeſſe <hi>Agghariſta,</hi> now Princeſſe of <hi>Cicily,</hi> is alſo very taking, and the famous <hi>Artaphil</hi> doubtleſly bears a great renown. To boot with theſe there is one called <hi>Timoclea,</hi> and an hundred o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, of ſomewhat a meaner condition, which are wonderfully handſom. But Sir, leſt I may prove too tedious, I will brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell you that the King who now reigns in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> is but two years elder then
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151701:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:151701:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:151701:8"/>
Prince <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> who is deſcended from the Race of <hi>Demophon,</hi> ſon to <hi>Theſeus,</hi> who is held in great eſteem amongſt us. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi> in his yonger years, you may eaſily judge was one of the lovelieſt perſonages which could be ſeen; for though he be now twenty eight years old, he continues to be ſo extraordinarily handſome, and ſo well behaved, as it may eaſily be gueſt what he was when a childe; and though he were wiſe even from his cradle, and knowing, even from the time he began to ſpeak, yet ceaſed he not to be of a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing humour, and comportment, ſuch as is only infuſed by youth, and the air of the Court, and which is the charm of converſation amongſt Ladies. In fine, ſet one article aſide, <hi>Philoxypes</hi> may be truly ſaid, to have fully ſatisfied and made good all the precepts of <hi>Venus Urania.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He reverenced the Goddeſſe, he loved his Prince, kept the Laws, he loved his Country, his fellow Citizens, was am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious of glory, which he went inqueſt of at fifteen years of age in the <hi>Mileſean</hi> War, wherein he gave ſingular teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his carriage. He loved the Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and all the liberal Arts; delighted in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151701:8"/>
innocent paſtimes, and loved vertue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all things; but as for beauty, he had only a general admiration for it, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver felt in himſelf, any particular addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or adheration to any whatſoever handſome Lady. You may imagin Sir, how ſtrange this inſenſibility appeared, in a Court where it met not with any exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and in a man ſo fit to occaſion love. Yet was he ſo lovely, as he was not for this the leſſe beloved; he was ſo liberal, ſo magnifical, ſo full of complacency, and ſo civilly behaved, as he was the wonder of the world.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Solon</hi> after having eſtabliſht thoſe famous Laws at <hi>Athens,</hi> went from thence, reſolving to forgoe his Country for ten years, to the end that he might make no alteration there, he came to our Court; <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> who was then but eighteen years old, had a great affection for him, as he had likewiſe for <hi>Philoxetes;</hi> inſomuch, that as long as <hi>Solon</hi> abode in our Iſle, <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxetes</hi> gave over all his other delights, and the frequenting of the Ladies companies to faſten himſelf totally to him: whom that he might enjoy with the more free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, he carried him to a Town of his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151701:9"/>
which is called <hi>Apia;</hi> built by <hi>Demaphon</hi> in a very ſtrong, but rocky ſituation, and of hard acceſſe, all the Countrey about it being craggy, dry, and exceeding barren. <hi>Solon</hi> being come thither, ſhewed him how that they that laid the foundations of that Town, might have made it much more pleaſanter, if they had built it upon the banks of the River <hi>Claria,</hi> in a ſpaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and fertile plain, which lies at the foot of the Mountain, where the other Town was ſituated; hardly had <hi>Solon</hi> ſpoke his thought, when <hi>Philoxypes</hi> reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to put it in execution, and began al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready to give all neceſſary orders for it. And indeed <hi>Solon</hi> was the Architect who guided this great enterpriſe, <hi>Philoxypes</hi> giving him the glory thereof, for he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led this new Town <hi>Soly,</hi> to perpetuate the memory of the name of <hi>Solon.</hi> This place being not far from <hi>Paphos,</hi> one of our Kings moſt uſual abodes, they went oft to the Court; where our Ladies com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained ſometimes of <hi>Solon,</hi> who by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaving them of <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> bereft them of their faireſt ornament; and to ſhew you how great this Prince his inflexibility was, <hi>Solon</hi> whoſe vertue is not auſtere, to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151701:9"/>
juſtifie himſelf to thoſe that blamed <hi>Philoxypes</hi> for this, telling him that love was a paſſion, which ſweetned all other paſſions, and which did ſometimes exceed them all. That for his part, he confeſt he would never ſet his whole heart againſt it, and that he thought it no ſhame to be once in his life overcome thereby. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi> ſaid in his defence, that he loved all that was lovely, that he had a paſſion for all beautiful objects, and that no man ever lov'd ſo much as he. But notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all his univerſal affections, there was no one ſo fair in all the Court, who could boaſt in her particular to have inthralled his heart; and who peradventure had not more then once conſulted with her glaſſe, to know by what innocent art this ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous heart might be taken: but at laſt, after having ſtaid a good while, <hi>Solon</hi> went his way much taken with <hi>Philoxypes</hi> his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and made ſome verſes in his praiſe before he imbarked for <hi>Egypt.</hi> He who was commended by all <hi>Greece,</hi> did highly commend this young Prince; ſaying, that Nature had taught <hi>Philoxypes</hi> in eighteen years, what Art could not teach in an Age, and that a man might ſee in him by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151701:10"/>
way of prodigy, all the ages of man put together; that is to ſay, the innocence of infancy, the charms of youth, the forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of a more advanced age, and the wiſdome of old age. After his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Philoxypes</hi> was ſomewhat melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but this humour being over, he ſpent ſome time in travel, and did not only ſee whole <hi>Greece,</hi> but likewiſe the famous Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Carthage,</hi> which did then wage war with the <hi>Maſsiliens,</hi> who inhabit a place which they have of late made famous, by a cry'd up Academy, wherein eloquence, and all the <hi>Grecian</hi> Sciences are rarely well taught.</p>
            <p>I will not relate unto you all the gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant actions he did in <hi>Africa,</hi> nor what befel him during that Journey, which continued till ſome moneths before you came to <hi>Cyprus;</hi> where <hi>Solon</hi> ſtayed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while again, not ſuffering himſelf to be ſeen almoſt by any one. But I will tell you that <hi>Philoxypes</hi> at his return to Court, charm'd all the world; and that the King himſelf grew ſo far in love with him, as never was known ſo great a favour as his, nor yet ſo little envyed; neither did he make uſe thereof, but for his Maſters glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151701:10"/>
and to do good to as many as he could; he rceceived no rewards, but to enrich ſuch as ſtood in need thereof; all the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſes he gave, were good; he did none but good offices: and thus he ſtood fair in the opinion of the great ones, and of the people, as well as in that of the King; and there were none but our Ladies who continued to accuſe him of inflexibility. Thus did he live amidſt delights, in the ſtatelieſt and moſt gallant Court of all the world, without envy, without love, and without melancholy. But the King was not this mean while ſo happy as he; for after having had ſome flitting paſſions, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> had notwithſtanding much diſquieted him, he fell mightily in love with the Princeſſe <hi>Aretephile,</hi> who certainly is very beautiful, and hath an hundred good qualities; but who withal this was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly ambitious. The King was no ſooner aware of the violence of this his paſſion, but that he diſcovered it to <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes,</hi> and entreated him to intercede for him with <hi>Aretephile,</hi> who at that time did often viſit the Princeſſe <hi>Agariſta,</hi> ſiſter to <hi>Philoxypes.</hi> You may imagin this Prince did not refuſe to aſſiſt him, ſince his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151701:11"/>
was innocent; yet did he ſometimes crave pardon of the King, if he did not much bewail him in his diſquiets: For Sir, ſaid he, love being a malady which I am not acquainted with, and which I have much to imagine is ſo great as man would have it thought, I confeſſe I doe not ſo much compaſſionate your Majeſty, as perdaventure I ought; &amp; conſequently, I may perchance not ſo fully exaggerate your ſufferings as I ſhould do, when I ſpeak with the Princeſſe <hi>Aretephile.</hi> Fear not <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> ſaid the King, that I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of your inflexibility; on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, if you had a more tender heart, I would not have choſen you for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident of my paſſion: and did I think that you could become my rival, I would not give you Commiſſion to ſpeak ſo of ten with my beloved Princeſſe. But my intention not being to ſpeak of the Kings love, otherwiſe then as it relates neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily to <hi>Philoxypes</hi> adventures; I will on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell you that though <hi>Aretephile</hi> were ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſht to ſee her ſelf beloved by the King, yet aiming at the Crown of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> ſhe thought ſhe was a little to diſguiſe her ſenſe thereof, and to make it a harder
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151701:11"/>
matter for the King to win her, then ſhe had found it to win the King: So as this Princeſſe behaved her ſelf with much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion and reſervedneſſe, and mingling continually ſeverity with mildneſſe, the King ſtood long in need of <hi>Philoxypes</hi> aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, whom <hi>Aretephile,</hi> who knew what power he had with the King, uſed with all poſſible civility. <hi>Philoxypes</hi> was not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſometimes much troubled at the continuance of this paſſion, which made him for his recreation, go to a very ſtately houſe, which the famous <hi>Solon</hi> had cauſed to be built for him neer <hi>Soly,</hi> and wherein he had made a collection of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever <hi>Greece</hi> had of moſt rare &amp; curious, were it either for pictures, or ſtatues. In this place it was, which is called <hi>Claria,</hi> where wondring ſometimes at the Kings paſſion, he did me the honor to bemoan himſelf to me of his employmen, and he himſelf gave me a thouſand pleaſant marks of his inflexibleneſſe, by thoſe things which he uttered againſt love. This mean while though the King were much in love with <hi>Aretephile,</hi> yet he had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to do to perſwade himſelf to marry her, becauſe indeed in reaſon he ſhould
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151701:12"/>
much rather have married the Princeſſe <hi>Thimoclea,</hi> by reaſon of ſome claim ſhe pretended to have to the Principality of <hi>Amathuſa;</hi> inſomuch as the King being yet unreſolved what to doe, had not as yet acquainted <hi>Aretephile,</hi> nor let her be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted that his love tended meerly to ſet her upon the Throne; but only fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the cuſtome of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> he had ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently witneſſed his ſervice, and to purchaſe her eſteem, had done whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a handſome and ingenious Prince ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> could doe, who though he were himſelf inſenſible of love, was notwithſtanding a very great gallant; ſo as <hi>Aretephile</hi> who was abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolved never to part with her heart for leſſe then a Crown, treated the King ſometimes ſeverely enough, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as the whole Court was troubled thereat, and <hi>Philoxypes</hi> delight lay onely in Hunting, and in his ſtately Country houſe. Some other times <hi>Aretephile</hi> fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring leſt ſhe her ſelf might extinguiſh the fire which ſhe had kindled in the Kings heart, was ſomewhat more kinde unto him, and by the Prince his Joy, rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the whole Court. 'Twas then in one
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151701:12"/>
of theſe pleaſant conjuncture of times, that <hi>Phyloxypes</hi> to oblige the King, made the Princeſſe of <hi>Salamis</hi> his ſiſter, and the Princeſſe <hi>Aghariſta</hi> doe him the honour to entertain the King upon a day that he invited the King and all the Court to goe from <hi>Paphos</hi> to <hi>Claria,</hi> and to paſſe one whole day in his retiredneſs, which indeed deſerved to receive ſo Princely a company. Never was there ſo gallant an Aſſembly as this; it was wholly compoſed of young and handſom perſonages, of great birth, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: and one would have ſaid, that fortune had favoured <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> in orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it ſo as that all perſons of quality who were peeviſh or of ill humour in the Court, were either ſick that day, or buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about ſome important affairs, ſo as this well compacted company was not troubled with the importunity of any of their companies: On what ſide ſoever they did caſt their eye, they met with nothing but goodly objects, there was no fear of being wearied or anoyed. <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xypes</hi> had taken ſuch excellent order for all things, were it either for the ſtately furniture of the houſe, for the magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151701:13"/>
of the Feaſt, or the excellency of the Muſick, as the King to give him the higheſt praiſe he could, ſaid aloud, that if <hi>Philoxypes</hi> had been in love, and that his Miſtreſſe had been in that company, he could have done no more then he did. On the contrary, Sir, ſaid <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> I think that if I had been in love, all things would have been much more in diſorder, then they are; it ſeeming impoſſible to me that a man ſhould loſe his reaſon, and yet have leiſure enough to think of ſuch trivial affairs. The King began then to oppoſe <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> and to tell him that he did little know the effects of this paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and this he did more then once, as well for that he could hardly find a more pleaſing entertainment by diſcourſe, as alſo that by reproaching <hi>Philoxypes</hi> with his ignorance of love; he thereby found an opportune means to make the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe <hi>Aretephile,</hi> who liſten'd unto him, know that the paſſion he had for her, had made him very expert therein, <hi>Philoxy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes</hi> did defend himſelf the beſt he could. Sometimes he ſaid the fear of not being beloved kept him from loving; ſometimes that he had ſo nice a ſoul as did avoid
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151701:13"/>
ſuch pleaſures as could not be purchaſed without pain; and conſequently that love not being a voluntary thing, he was not to blame for that he did not love: and for his laſt reaſon, he ſaid that the difficulty of the choice made him that he neither did, nor could reſolve on any; for Sir, ſaid he to the King, how is it poſſible to have the affrontedneſs to prefer any one of ſo many handſome perſonages as I ſee before all the reſt? Ah, <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> ſaid the King, the more you ſpeak of love, the more pity doe you move in me; and (ſpeaking low in his ear) the more ſaid he doe you make me ſee that my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident will never bee my rival. After this, all the Ladies, and all the men of quality, began to argue the matter with him; he did ſometime almoſt hate them all for their reproaching him with his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexibility. When they had dined, <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi> led all this fair aſſembly into a ſtately gallery, painted all over by the hand of an excellent Maſter, named <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drocles,</hi> who is of the Iſle of <hi>Samos,</hi> and who having finiſht this rare work, ſome few days before this great Feaſt, was returned to his own Countrey.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:151701:14"/>
The ſtory of <hi>Venus Urania,</hi> was the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of all thoſe pictures, in whom no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but modeſty was to be diſcerned. The Painter had not drawn the Graces all naked, as they uſually are drawn, but had clothed them in tranſparent tiffeny, which rendred all thoſe figures very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful; in one of the draughts, you might ſee <hi>Venus</hi> deſcend from Heaven in a Chariot, all of burniſht gold drawn by Swans; a thouſand little <hi>Cupids</hi> ſeemed to hover about her, and to be the firſt that lighted in the Iſle of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in the ſame piece, to prepare all things to receive her; in another piece, all thoſe little <hi>Cupidons,</hi> erected unto her an Altar of Turffs, and made dreſſings of flowers to adorn her; in another piece, this Goddeſs teacheth <hi>Cupid</hi> how to chuſe his golden ſhafts, which he meant to uſe; and in another, ſhe put a Torch into his hand, and ſhewing him the Sun which is painted at the top of that piece, ſeems as if ſhe would tell him that ſhe would have the flames wherewith he ſets hearts on fire, to be more pure then the beams of this glorious conſtellation. In fine, Sir, this Goddeſs is repreſented in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151701:14"/>
above twenty parts of this gallery; but though in different poſtures, you may ſtill diſcerne the ſame countenance. Though all in this Gallery bee beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, this figure is incomparably be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all the reſt: all the reſt are pictures, but this ſeems to be effectually a divine perſonage; for certainly there was never any thing ſeen of ſo much handſomneſſe; all the fair Ladies who <hi>Philoxypes</hi> had brought thither, were amazed to ſee it, and maugre themſelves confeſt that their glaſs ſhewed them nothing like it. All their eyes were fixt upon a face ſo full of beauty, and they all agreed in one, that the Painters imagination had far outdone what ever nature had done of moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſht. After they had well eyed this <hi>Venus,</hi> for my part, ſaid the Princeſs <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retephile,</hi> I would fain know whether <hi>Philoxypes</hi> heart could reſiſt a perſonage who ſhould perfectly reſemble this pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture? Since I have been able (replyed he) to behold all theſe Ladies that are here, without daring to profeſſe my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, it is to be believed, I ſhould be as inſenſible for her, or rather as full of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect for her, as I have been for all the reſt that I ſee, who are no leſs fair then he
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151701:15"/>
this <hi>Venus.</hi> Tis not notwithſtanding (ſaid he ſmilingly, and without any other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, then to ſay ſomewhat of gallantry to entertain converſation) that I am not glad that this picture is only the effect of the famous <hi>Mandrocles</hi> imagination. For I confeſs unto you there is a certain char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, modeſt, and paſſionate aire in the eyes of this Goddeſſe, which would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure pleaſe me too much, were it a living beauty. <hi>Philoxypes</hi> had no ſooner ſaid this, but all the company began to ſmile at this firſt mark of his tenderneſſe, which they had never before obſerved in him. There was not any one of them who would not willingly, if it had been poſſible, have inſpired life into this pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, that they might ſee whether <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi> might be bent by her or no; and whether his rebel heart to love, would prove proof againſt her extraordinary charms. If this could be, ſaid Princeſs <hi>Thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moclea,</hi> I wiſh at leaſt that this fair perſonage ſhould have as much ſweetneſs in her ſoul as in her eyes, to the end that nothing might be wanting to <hi>Philoxypes</hi> happineſs. On the contrary, ſaid the Princeſs of <hi>Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis,</hi> me thinks it were to be wiſht, that (to puniſh my brother for his inflexibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty)
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151701:15"/>
ſhe were as cruel, as fair; and I doubt me, added <hi>Aretephile,</hi> whether for his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter puniſhment, ſhe were not to be wiſht to be proud and ſtupid: or rather, ſaid Princeſs <hi>Agheriſta,</hi> inconſtant, fickle, alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her humour every day; and for his yet farther puniſhment, added the King ſmilingly, that ſhe were all that you all have ſaid. At theſe words <hi>Philoxypes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired ſo much favour of them, as that they would ſuffer him to enjoy that quiet which liberty beſtowes on them who poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe her: but the Sun being already low, he mentioned a walk to this fair company, who without reſiſtance glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accepted thereof. He led them into a large plot of ground, which makes an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſland; for he had drawn a branch of the River of <hi>Claria</hi> round about it. Paſſing from thence over a little bridge, with ballaſters of braſs, he led them into an allie of Orange Trees, twelve hundred paces long, which the Sun could never get into, ſo large are thoſe Trees, and ſo thick covered with leaves and flowers. Amidſt this Allie there croſſes a Channel of running water; at laſt you come to a place where eleven Allies croſs one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151701:16"/>
at the end of which, the river is every where ſeen, as if it were ſo delighted with that place, as it were loth to leave it. All theſe Allies are either of Orange Trees, or Citron Trees, or Myrrhe, or Lawrel, or Pomegranats, or Palm Trees: but after being come to the end of one of theſe Allies, into which <hi>Philoxypes</hi> ſent them, they found themſelves in a large Meadow, which is cut through in the middle by the River, which gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in that place, ſeems to be a great channel, which hath on its banks neither canes, nor ruſhes, nor reeds, nor little ſhrubs, but is only bordered by thick turff, and all beſprinckled over with Flags of differing colours, with Narciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuſſes, with Lillies, and all other flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, which love moiſture and freſhneſs. There are likewiſe on this River, great ſtore of Swans, which ſwim ſo demurely, as you would think they were afraid to trouble the water which bears them up: and that there might nothing be wanting to this entertainment, <hi>Philoxypes</hi> had ſo ordered it, as this River was all covered over with Boats, made like Gallies, pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with lively colours, and guided by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151701:16"/>
young Boyes in Maratin apparel, but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry handſome; who rowing gently with Oars painted red and green, came to the bank to receive this gallant company, who were played unto on ruſtick Muſick by yong Shepheards very quaintly clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, who drove heards along that Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow on the other ſide of the River. Their Shepheards crooks were all trimmed with braſs guilt over, &amp; ſtrewed over with cyphers; their Flutes and little Bagpipes were as well deckt as were their ſheep, all whoſe horns were loaded with flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. In divers parts of this Meadow, were an hundred lovely Shepheards, clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in white, with hats of roſes, who to make the place the more pleaſing, mixt the melody of their voices to the ruſtick Muſick aforeſaid. So ſweet a place being doubtleſly proper to infuſe joy, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, being no diſpoſition to cruelty; the King found <hi>Aretephile</hi> a little more gentle; and all the worſt treated lovers of this company, found at leaſt ſome truce to their ſufferings, and were maugre them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves delighted with ſo lovely a place, which was bounded about by a very high Palleſade, wherein Niches placed at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151701:17"/>
diſtances, were ſtatues of white Marble, the rareſt that were ever ſeen in <hi>Greece.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I may ſeem to be my ſelf inchanted in a place ſo full of charms, ſince I ſtay ſo long thereon: I muſt then haſte to make this fair company depart, whom <hi>Philoxypes</hi> waited on back to <hi>Paphos,</hi> after having offered them a famous banquet. Some few days after, being teturned home, with intention to entertain himſelf alone there for two days, he ſpent all that time very contentedly: But <hi>Philoxypes</hi> his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour lying rather to like general beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, wherein art hath nothing to do, then thoſe where art undertakes to perfect na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; went out of his Park, and unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied by any ſave one ſervant, he went to the River ſide, intending to walk along it till he ſhould come to the head therof, which is not far from thence, and which certainly is one of the goodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt things in the world: For this miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Spring-head, which of it ſelf makes a River, is incloſed by Rocks of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acceſſible height; at the foot of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, and higheſt whereof, is a large cave which extends it ſelf even to the loſs of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151701:17"/>
ſight, both on the right hand &amp; on the left, under unacceſſible Rocks. At the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of this Cave, is a ſilent ſpring, which ſometimes riſeth up to the top of the den, and ſometimes falls ſo low, as it is not above five or ſix foot high. This inequality is the cauſe why the River of <hi>Claria,</hi> as well as all the others of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> paſs rather for a fair Torrent, then for a River; though this be not poſitively ſo, for it is never altogether dried up, as are all the reſt. As he went towards this Cave, he got off horſe-back, leaving his horſe with his ſervant, commanding him to wait his return, and not to follow him.</p>
            <p>Thus did he walk all alone, along theſe Torrents, with the ſight and noiſe whereof, he was much delighted, when raiſing up his eyes, he might ſee ſome twenty paces off, a very handſome wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, though in a mean habit, who was ſate upon a Rock, all covered over with moſs; and who ſeemed to take pleaſure in eying attentively the fall of waters which came ruſhing at her feet, as if to do her homage. At firſt <hi>Philoxypes</hi> thought not to trouble the contentment of one
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151701:18"/>
whoſe humour was ſo conformable to his, to ſit muſing upon the River ſide, and to turn a little aſide, that he might not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt her. But being come a little neerer, and ſeeing that her apparel though clean, and handſome, gave her not out to be a perſonage of quality, he went directly towards her, becauſe that was the eaſieſt way. But being come very neer her, and the noiſe his walking made, having made this woman look about, he was ſtrangely taken; not only to ſee the handſomeſt creature in the world, but to diſcern per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly that, that miraculous <hi>Venus</hi> which he had in his Gallery, and which he had alwayes taken onely for the effect of a handſome imagination, was really the picture of this perſonage; <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſht at this ſo ſtrange apparition, chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his colour; and ſaluting this maid with more civility then her condition ſeemed to require, he advanced yet nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer her; but ſhe riſing up in haſte, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not without a bluſh paid him his ſalute, as if ſhe had been troubled to be ſeen alone in that place, ſhe haſted to go unto an old man and a woman well-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced in years, who were not above
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151701:18"/>
twenty paces off her; yet fearing by like to be followed, ſhe turned her head twice towards <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> who was ſtill the more dazeled with her beauty, and more confirmed in his opinion. This Prince ſurpriſed at this encounter, had a great deſire to know who this yong and ſo wonderfully handſome maid might be; and to know alſo how <hi>Mandrocles</hi> could come to draw her picture; and why <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drocles</hi> had always told him, that the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture which he had drawn, was only an effect of his fancy: He followed her with his eyes as far as he could; but having ſtood ſtill a pretty while, not knowing why he did ſo, he loſt ſight of her amongſt thoſe Rocks after ſhe was come up to thoſe ſhe went unto, ſo as he could no more diſcover her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philoxypes</hi> did not overmuch endevour it, though his minde led him very much thereunto, but coming neer the River ſide, in ſtead of continuing to walk to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Spring head, he went down the ſtream; and were it by hazard, or out of deſign, he happened to reſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon the ſame Rock covered with moſs, on which he had ſeen the fair maid
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151701:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:151701:19"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:151701:20"/>
ſit. <hi>Philoxypes</hi> being there, could think on nothing, but on this fair unknown one, and upon the pleaſing adventure which had befaln him. He then remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred the diſcourſe which had paſt in the Gallery, and what he had ſaid of that pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture which every one ſo much commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; and delighting to entertain him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon this ſubject, how glad ſaid he unto himſelf, would Princeſſe <hi>Aretephile</hi> be, if ſhe knew what had befaln me, and how would the King mock me if he heard it? They would certainly ſay, that the Goddeſs had wrought a miracle to puniſh me, by making me meet with a Country wench, of whom to make the object of my choice. But ſaid he, preſently after, this Country maid is fairer then whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver there is of beauty in the Court; and I ſhall ſufficiently revenge my ſelf of all our Ladies, if I can once more meet with her, and let them ſee her. He then reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to return the next day to the ſame place, and in the mean time not to ſpeak of her till he had found her again. He then returned home, but full of amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; at his firſt arival, he went ſtrait to his Gallery, and grew ſo confident in his
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151701:20"/>
belief, that his <hi>Venus Urania</hi> was the very picture of this fair unknown one, as he doubted no more thereof. He compared all the features of this picture, with the image which he bare about in his mind, not finding any difference between them ſave that the original was farre above what ever <hi>Mandrocles</hi> with all his art, could repreſent. He ſeemed to have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in her face, a much more pleaſing youthly aire, a much more majeſtical modeſty, and a ſweetneſs infinitely more alluring. In fine, the Prince <hi>Philoxy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes,</hi> who had wont to be more in his Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, then in his Gallery, perceiving that the ſight of this picture detained him there, whether he would or no, went forth much perplext to ſee that once in his life time, he could not maſter his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. He paſt the reſt of that day, and all the next night, not being able to eface this pleaſing phantoſm out of his minde. The next day he returned to the ſame place where he had ſeen that fair one, ſtill thinking how he ſhould be pleaſed to cauſe her be ſeen by the King, and the whole Court. But though he went up the River, even up to the head thereof, he
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151701:21"/>
could not finde her; he ſought her long in vain; and being angered thereat, he ſought whether he could not finde ſome little track about that place where he had ſeen the fair unknown one; but it being all Rocky, no impreſſion of foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps could be ſeen there, nor could there be any track found amongſt the Rocks. Deſperate then, as he was not to finde any knowledge of what he ſo much deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, he returned back, abſolutely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving not to return any more to that place: yet was he no ſooner at home, but that he wiſht to be at the River ſide; he enquired of all his ſervants, if they had never met any body thereabouts, which reſembled that <hi>Venus;</hi> and askt them very particularly, into what pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and into what houſes <hi>Mandrocles</hi> went when he painted his Gallery? They an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that they had never ſeen her whom he ſpoke off, and that <hi>Mandrocles</hi> was a ſolitary man, who ſaw no body, who ſpent all his time in deſigning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe Rocks; and that he took almoſt always the way towards the head of <hi>Claria. Philoxypes</hi> not able to learn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more, did what he could to think no
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151701:21"/>
more thereon; but though he had reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to return next day to <hi>Paphos,</hi> he ſtayed at <hi>Claria,</hi> (for his houſe bears the name of the River which paſſeth by it) and whatever deſigne he had, never to return to ſeek out the fair unknown one, his feet maugre himſelf, bare him always towards the place where he had met her. Hee returned often from thence, not knowing why he would not willingly go thither, nor why he went thither, not having any thought of ſo doing. But at laſt yeelding to his curioſity, he retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned towards thoſe Rocks, reſolving to ſuffer himſelf to be guided by fortune; leaving always his ſervant and his horſe where he left them the firſt time.</p>
            <p>He wandred then long amongſt thoſe Mountains, when being weary, he ſate himſelf down, which he had hardly done, upon a neighbouring Rock, when hee might diſcover afar off a little Cottage, in a place which appeared very ſavage unto him: ſo as riſing up, it may be, ſaid he unto himſelf, 'tis here where the Gods have hidden the Treaſure, which I ſeek for. And indeed he had not walked far, when he ſaw the fair unknown one, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151701:22"/>
by the ſame old man, and the ſame woman which he had formerly ſeen, and by three or four others all meanly clothed, which ſeemed to take a by-way which led to a little Temple, which lies towards the Sea ſide, and which was built for the accommodation of ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, who traffique in that Iſland, and land on that ſide. The Temple not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing above ſix furlongs from this little ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral habitation, 'twas but a walk to go thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on foot.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philoxypes</hi> raviſht at this encounter, went towards them; and addreſſing his ſpeech to the old man, after having ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, and looked on the fair unknown, with more admiration then at firſt; Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſaid he, know you who they be that live in that little houſe which I ſee yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der amongſt the Rocks? Sir, ſaid he, they are people who merit not the honor you do them in ſpeaking to them; nor doe I know how my Cabbin ſhould cauſe curioſity in a man of your condition.</p>
            <p>Whileſt the old man ſpoke, <hi>Philoxypes</hi> had his eyes fixt upon the fair unknown one ſo attentively, as he made her bluſh, and forced her to turn her head aſide;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151701:22"/>
he willingly would have ſpoken to her, but that (as he told me afterward) hee was affraid to ruine himſelf in ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing an inchantment; and that he ſhould finde as much rudeneſſe in her converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as ſhe had ſweetneſſe in her eyes; to boot, that he ſaw her to be ſo modeſt, as he eaſily imagined ſhe would not ſpeak long unto him in her parents preſence, (for he perceived ſhe behaved her ſelf as if ſhe were the old mans daughter) hee enquired alſo of the good old man, if he went oft to that Temple? whether his abode there had been long? whether he were of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> or no? whether that were his whole family? and a hundred other things to continue the converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. To all which, though the other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered exactly, <hi>Philoxypes</hi> did hardly hear any thing he ſaid; &amp; thus they parted, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had tane his leave of them all, hardly knowing what he ſaid.</p>
            <p>Not having learnt any thing, but that he had once more ſeen the fair unknown one, that ſhe was much more lovely then he had thought her to be, that he knew her abode, and the Temple whether ſhe ſometimes went. He purſued her with
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151701:23"/>
his eyes as far as he could; but at laſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſhamed of what he did, and ſeeking a reaſon for it, he returned back the ſame way, and went into his Gallery, it being the only place in all his houſe, wherein he pleaſed himſelf. When he was come thereinto, he began to walk with more diſquiet then he had wont to be acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted withall. And far from his former deſign of bringing the fair unknown one to the Court, he did as far as in him lay, put on a reſolution of never ſeeing her more himſelf: ſo much was he affected with this ſecond ſight.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe, he went forthwith out of his Gallery, got on horſe-back, and returned to <hi>Paphos;</hi> the King who loved him dearly, and who had as much of friendſhip for him, as of love for the Princeſſe <hi>Aretephile,</hi> complained of his ſo long abode in the Countrey, and made as much of him as could be. He imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately entreated him to viſit the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe <hi>Aretephile,</hi> becauſe there had been ſome little quarrel between them, which he acquainted him withall, making the moſt he could of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phyloxypes</hi> obeys him, viſits the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151701:23"/>
and makes them friends: but let him do what he pleaſeth, or go whither he will, his thoughts are ſtill buſied about the fair unknown one; he compares her with all the beauties that he ſees, and whether he behold <hi>Aretephile, Thimoclea, Aghariſta,</hi> or whoſoever elſe, he can ſee none but his ſiſter, the fair Princeſſe of <hi>Salamis,</hi> who comes any way neer her for beauty; but he preferred the other a thouſand times before her, as being a thouſand times more beautiful, then whatſoever the world hath of beauty. Two days after he returned to <hi>Claria,</hi> and the next day he went to the aforeſaid lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Temple, whether thoſe that were of the Iſland went ſeldome or never, it being only built for ſtrangers.</p>
            <p>And this was the reaſon wherefore the beauty of the fair unknown one, had not been noiſed abroad, neither in <hi>Apid,</hi> which is not far from thence, nor in <hi>Soly</hi> which is very neer it, nor in <hi>Claria,</hi> which joyns upon it. <hi>Phyloxypes,</hi> then maugre himſelf, went thither, whether he was no ſooner come, but he ſaw the fair maid ſtill accompanied with the ſame compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who devoutly prayed to the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151701:24"/>
that is there adored. In fine, Sir, to keep that no longer from you, which <hi>Philoxypes</hi> had much adoe to acknowledg to himſelf, this laſt ſight fully conquered him; for the ſacrifice being ſomewhat long, love had time enough to faſten him with his chains not to be untyed. You may believe it had been eaſie for <hi>Philoxy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes</hi> to have ſpoken to this maid, as ſhee came out of the Temple, and to have followed her home, if he had pleaſed; but though love had already gotten the upper hand in his heart, yet had it not driven out ſhame from thence. And <hi>Philoxypes</hi> did me the honour to tell mee afterwards, that he was ſo aſhamed of his own weakneſſe, and of the meanneſs of this maids condition as he ſometimes wiſht to be dead.</p>
            <p>This little aſſembly being gone, and he being returned home ſtrangely perplext, what ſaid he to himſelf, is it poſſible that <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> that unflexible <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> who could never be wrought upon by all the fair Ladies of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> ſhould be in love with one born in a Cottage, bred up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Rocks, and ſavage people? Ah, no, no: it cannot be. I would rather rip
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151701:24"/>
out my heart, then ſuffer it any longer to retain ſo mean, and ſo unworthy an affection. But (ſaid he preſently after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards) there is ſomewhat of Divinity in Supream beauty, which is not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted. And if this unknown one be more fair then all the Princes of the world, ſhe better deſerves the love of the inflexible <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> then all they do. Yet I am ſure, ſaid he, when the wiſe <hi>Solon</hi> told me, That a man might without ſhame be once in his life time overcome by love; he underſtood it not to be by the love of a ſhepherdeſs, as doubtleſly ſhe is—at theſe words not having power to end his ſpeech and ſay, Whom I love; ſhame ſtopt his mouth, and for a while he ſaid nothing.</p>
            <p>Then ſuddenly re-aſſuming his ſpeech, No, no, ſaid he, <hi>Solon</hi> would not approve the folly which poſſeſſeth me: For in fine, to love a perſon ſo beneath ones ſelf, a perſon, whoſe name one is affraid to ask; one to whom one hath never ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and to whom I dare not ſpeak, for fear of finding her mind unworthy of her beauty, one who peradventure will not underſtand my language, who peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath neither vertue nor goodneſſe,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151701:25"/>
and whom the Gods have endowed with extraordinary beauty, only for my confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and to make mee deſpaire; once more it cannot, it muſt not be; ſo dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful an evil muſt be early withſtood; and as there are ſome venomes whoſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief is only cured by themſelves, the fair unknown one muſt cure me of the malady ſhe hath cauſed in me.</p>
            <p>I muſt once more ſee her, and ſpeak to her, to the end that the blemiſhes of her minde, and her rude converſation, may drive that beauty from out my heart, which her charming beauty and pleaſing eyes hath placed there. But good Gods, replyed he unto himſelf, is it poſſible ſo fair a perſonage ſhould have any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faults? Think <hi>Philoxypes</hi> what thou wilt do; and fear leſt whilſt you think to finde a cure for your evil, you render in incurable.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Philoxypes</hi> reaſoned with himſelf, who in effect reſolved to go the next day to the Cottage, where the fair unknown one dwelt, with intention to ſpeak unto her, and ſo to cure himſelf, imagining that his ſhame to ſee himſelf in that Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and the maids groſſe converſation,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151701:25"/>
would infallibly ſalve his paſſion. But he knew not that 'tis an uſuall effect of love to make thoſe who are in love, make uſe of all pretences, whereby they may come near thoſe whom they love, not knowing themſelves why they goe thither.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philoxypes</hi> failed not then to goe the next day towards the rocks, at foot wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of according to his cuſtome he left his ſervants: But as he went he was much diſquieted; ſometimes hee wiſht this young maid might neither have wit nor attraction; and by and by, deſired again he might meet with nothing in her which might detract from her beauty. In fine, not knowing whether he deſired to be ſick or cured, whether he would be free or a captive, and not knowing alſo under what pretence to make this odd viſit, he marcht on till he came to a little Valley, ſeated between Rocks, ſtoln as it were from the world, and very fit, to ſay the truth, to hide ſo infinite a precious trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. At the foot of this little Valley, there lies a pleaſant Meadow; and upon the ſide of theſe Rocks, a little Wood of Myrtle '&amp; wild Pomegranats, interming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151701:26"/>
with ſome Orange Trees. At the bottome of this Wood, there ſtands a little Houſe very low built, but in indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent good repair: As <hi>Philoxypes</hi> drew neer it, his troubles re-doubled, and hee was almoſt tempted to turn back, ſo aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med was he of his weakneſs. But at laſt being forced on by love, he entred into the fore-Court of this houſe, cloſed in with Lawrels no higher then ones elbow, which are very common in this Iſland. At laſt, ſeeing a door open, he came into a little Chamber, decently, though but meanly furniſhed; in which, he found the fair unknown one, and two other women who made Garlands of flowers, intending to carry them the next day to the Temple, and give them to the Prieſt who lived there, to adorn the Victime, which was to be offered, there in ſacrifice. You may imagin, how much aſtoniſhed this young maid might be, to ſee ſuch a one as <hi>Philoxypes</hi> enter her Cabin, who is always richly clothed, and who as you know, is of a very ſtately behaviour; ſhe no ſooner ſaw him, but riſing up in haſte ſhe let all her flowers fall, thereby affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Philoxypes</hi> occaſion of commencing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151701:26"/>
converſation, who ſtooped down to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther up the faln flowers: Sir, ſaid ſhe, endeavouring to hinder him, pray trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble not your ſelf, for our Woods and Meadows abound in the like, ſo as I may eaſily repair this loſſe, if theſe were ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. Thoſe which your Woods and Fields produce, ſaid he, are not of ſuch worth as theſe, which I reſtore you, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have not been gathered by ſo fair a maid as you. Sir, ſaid ſhe, bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Goddeſs to whom I intend to offer them, will look more upon the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of my heart, then upon my face, which certainly hath nothing in it, which may occaſion you to ſpeak as you do. But Sir, ſaid ſhe, (not giving him leave to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt her, to the end ſhe might change the diſcourſe) you have perhaps ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to command my Father, who will bee very much troubled that hee is not here, that he might have the glory to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey you: but he is gone forth with my Mother, and will not return till night.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philoxypes</hi> hearing her ſpeak with ſo much judgement, and ſuch civility, hee having at moſt expected nothing but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, and ſimplicity in her converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151701:27"/>
had hardly the power to anſwer her. He beheld her with admiration, and liſtened to her with aſtoniſhment; he obſerved a decent negligence in her apparel, and her tone of ſpeech ſo exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively charming, as he was raviſht; ſhee ſpoke not only Greek, but with all the Atique purity, and Courtly ſmoothneſs; her action was moreover infinitely beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, having nothing in it, neither of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, nor yet of Clowniſh. He found ſuch modeſty in her looks, and ſo lovely a freſhneſs in her complexion, as he had hardly liberty to reply; yet after ſome ſtrivings within himſelf, 'tis true, faire maid, ſaid he, I had ſomewhat to ſay unto your Father, but till ſuch time as I ſhall ſee him, give me leave to ask you why he makes choice of ſo ſolitary an abode. Sir, ſaid ſhe, ſuch is my reſpect unto him, as I never informed my ſelf of what you deſire to know; but I have ſometimes thought that this place is not of his choice, and that he lives here, only to fit his minde unto his fortune, which not having deſtin'd him a Palace, hinders him not from thinking himſelf happy in his Cottage.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:151701:27"/>
But is it poſſible, ſaid he, that this au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtere ſolitarineſs ſhould not ſeem tedious to you? Sir! (replyed ſhe with a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſmile) you will doubtleſly think me very ruſtick and ſavage, when I ſhal dare to ſay, that the only trouble I have met withall amidſt theſe Rocks, ſince I have lived here, is that wherewith I am now poſſeſt, to ſee you in a place, where I uſe not to ſee any one; and where cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly I would not ſee you, were I in a condition to do otherwiſe; it not appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſeemly to me, that one of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, ſhould buſie himſelf in talking ſo long with ſuch an one as I am. I ſhould be very unhappy, ſaid <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> if I ſhould have offended you, or have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared too importunate: but lovely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage, tell me I beſeech you, your name, and your Parents name, and tell me what God or Goddeſs tis that comes to inſtruct you in theſe Woods? Sir! ſaid ſhe, my name is <hi>Policrite,</hi> my Father is called <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anthes,</hi> and my Mother <hi>Megiſto;</hi> but as for thoſe Gods which you ſay doe teach me, they have as yet taught me ſo little, as I am ignorant even of civility: to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes which, I ſhall take the boldneſs to ſay,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:151701:28"/>
that ſince thoſe on whom I depend are not here, I ſhall deſire you not to take it ill, if I intreat you not to tarry any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in a place, wherein you will finde more of incommodity, then content. I ſhall not alter my minde, replyed <hi>Philoxy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes</hi> for what you ſay, but muſt once more affirm, that doubtleſly the Gods have in a moment inſpired you, with what others have much adoe to learn in their whole lives. For that you ſhould be the faireſt maid in all the world, and fairer in a Cottage, then Queens are in their Palaces; though this be very much, yet is it not impoſſible, but that living a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Woods and Rocks, you ſhould behave your ſelf, and ſpeak as you doe, 'tis this, fair <hi>Philocrita,</hi> that I cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend; nor can I imagin that you were born here amongſt theſe ſavage Rocks; 'Tis true, Sir! ſaid ſhe, I am not of this Iſland by birth; but was ſo young when I parted from <hi>Creta,</hi> as I hardly remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber any thing thereof. Tis true, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation which I have here, cannot have given me the accent of the Countrey, for I ſpeak with none but thoſe of this fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who are no more of <hi>Cyprus</hi> then I.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:151701:28"/>
What, <hi>Policrite,</hi> ſaid <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> do you ſpend your whole time without ſpeaking, and yet ſpeak as you do? Once more, this Cottage is unworthy of you; and ſome means muſt be found out to draw you hence. I am ſo well contented here, Sir, ſaid ſhe, as I ſhould thereby receive an injury; and I imagine you have no ſuch deſign; therefore I conjure you to leave me in that ſolitarineſs that you found me; for neither will I ſay much more unto you, not being able to ſpeak any thing of mine own experience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> who obſerved that this yong maid was indeed troubled to ſee him tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſo long with her, though it were in no diſ-obliging manner, was loth to anger her; ſo as with much violence uſed upon himſelf, after having ſaluted her with ſuch reverence, as if ſhe had been upon a Throne, he offered to be gone. But, Sir, ſaid ſhe, with much candour, you know my name is <hi>Policrite,</hi> and I cannot tell my Father what his name is, that hath done him the honour to enquire after him. You may tell him, replyed this Prince, tranſported with love, my name is <hi>Philoxypes.</hi> Alas, Sir! anſwered <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locrita,</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:151701:29"/>
I beg your pardon, if I have not uſed you with ſuch reſpect as I ought. Is not then, ſaid he, my name unknown unto you? No, Sir, ſaid ſhe, and I have heard my Father, though he knows you not himſelf, ſay ſuch things of you by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of others, as I am ſure will make him rejoyce exceedingly, when he ſhall know that you will do him the favour to command him any ſervice. <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> inchanted to hear <hi>Policrite</hi> ſpeak in ſuch ſort, ſaid unto her a thouſand paſſionate and obliging things, if ſhe would have underſtood them; to which ſhe ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed with ſuch readineſs and modeſty, as he ſtill became in love with her more and more.</p>
            <p>He then took his leave of her, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from this Cottage, with an uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable ſorrow, being come to the ſame place where he firſt ſaw her, he ſtayed; and beholding on the one ſide his goodly and magnificent Palace of <hi>Claria,</hi> and on the other ſide this little Countrey Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage: Ah, <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> cryed he, who would believe, that in the condition thy ſoul is in, thou canſt prefer this unlucky Cottage before that ſtately Palace? and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151701:29"/>
that thy heart ſo inſenſible of love, and ſo ambitious of true glory, can abaſe it ſelf before <hi>Policrite</hi>'s feet? But then, ſaid he again, is it poſſible that <hi>Philoxypes</hi> ſhould love any thing which is not the handſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt thing in the world? And if it bee ſo, <hi>Policrite</hi> ought to be the object of his deſires and love. I ſay, <hi>Policrite,</hi> in whoſe looks is no art, whoſe words are ſincere, all whoſe thoughts are innocent, who knows not what a ſin is, whoſe heart is not prepoſſeſt with any paſſion, who as yet loves nothing but the Woods, Fields, Flowers, and Fountains; who is hardly conſcious of her own beauty, and whoſe inclinations are doubtleſly all vertuous. But when all is done, ſaid he, after a little pauſe, love is a weakneſs, from whence I have till now defended my ſelf, onely becauſe I did verily believe, that it was handſome not to be capable thereof; but to love a perſonage of ſo unequal birth, is a folly, which I ought by all means to withſtand. For in fine, with what face ſhall I dare to appear at Court? How fair ſoever <hi>Policrite</hi> bee, I dare not ſhew the irons ſhee makes me wear; they muſt either be broken by force, or
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:151701:30"/>
ſo cunningly conceald, as no man may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver diſcern them.</p>
            <p>With this reſolution did <hi>Philoxypes</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn home, and from thence to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos;</hi> but he was ſo poſſeſt with melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, as hee was forced to fain himſelf ſick. The King, who ſaw him that very night, both with himſelf, and with the Princeſs <hi>Aretephile,</hi> perceived his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity, and preſſed him to know the cauſe: But <hi>Philoxypes</hi> anſwered him as he had done the reſt. The Court was very great that day, and all that was gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, was there; which occaſioned <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi> in his ravings, to inquire of himſelf an hundred and an hundred times, why, ſince he was to love, it was not ſome of thoſe illuſtrious perſonages? Yet though he would uſe violence upon himſelf, and endevor to love by reaſon, he could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſs it. And <hi>Policrite</hi>'s image was ſo deeply imprinted in his heart, as nothing could eface it. He paſſed over 3 days thus with very much diſquiet, and on the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> maugre himſelf, he returned to <hi>Claria,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Cleanthes,</hi> whom at his firſt approach, he found leaning upon that little Palliſado of Lawrels, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:151701:30"/>
his Court. As ſoon as this wiſe Old man ſaw him, he ſtept unto him, and received him with ſuch Civility as had nothing of Ruſtick in it. Sir, ſaid he, I thought my Daughter had been deceived when ſhe told me your Name, which kept me from coming to <hi>Claria</hi> to receive your Commands; to boot, that 'tis hard to imagine, that a Man of my Fortune and Age may be any wayes ſerviceable to ſuch a Prince as you. Vertue and worth, ſaid <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> makes friends unto it ſelf of all Ages, and of all Conditions. But <hi>Cleanthes</hi> the only thing I deſire to know of you, is whether it be out of neceſſity, or out of choice, that you inhabit this little Houſe? for, if it be the former, you ſhall not tarry long here; and if the latter, I will come and live with you ſometimes; at which <hi>Cleanthes</hi> ſmiled, and ſaid, Poor Cottages, Sir, are no proper abodes for great Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. 'Tis very true, ſaid <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought great Worth to be confin'd to little Cottages, but doth much better be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come great Palaces: I therefore proffer you my Houſe <hi>Claria,</hi> where you and your Family may live more commodiouſly then here. Sir, replyed <hi>Cleanthes,</hi> 'tis
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:151701:31"/>
handſome for a perſonage of your condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and worth to be willing to relieve the diſtreſted, but it were not juſt to abuſe that Goodneſs, which may be better em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd on ſome better occaſion. For, in fine, Sir, I ſuffer no want in this Cottage, my minde being no greater then it; I here live in quiet; and finding in this little corner of the earth ſufficient to keep me from being troubleſome to any body, I live here much more happily then thoſe who live in Palaces, and whoſe deſires are not therein bounded. But wiſe <hi>Cleanthes,</hi> ſaid <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> will you not tell me what Fortune 'tis that hath brought you hither, and acquaint me preciſely with your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition? Sir, ſaid the good Old man, I am deſcended of honeſt Parents, of an indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Fortune; for mine, you ſee it is mean enough, and I aſſure you my worth is not extraordinary. I was forc't to foregoe my Country, for many reaſons, too long now to tell, and to ſeek out a place of Retirement in this Iſland, where I have lived a good while; but ſaid <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes,</hi> are you not affraid leſt <hi>Policrite,</hi> who may juſtly be termed a Treaſure, may not be ſafe in ſuch a place as this?
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:151701:31"/>
if I ſhould grant, anſwered <hi>Cleanthes,</hi> that <hi>Policrite</hi> ſhould be what you ſay, ſince this Treaſure is only known by Prince <hi>Philoxy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes,</hi> I ſhould think it ſafe enough; you have reaſon, Father, ſaid he, for what you ſay, for I engage my ſelf to protect you, againſt what, or whoſoever ſhall go about to injure you. After this <hi>Cleanthes</hi> led him into his Houſe, where he found <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſto, Cleanthes</hi> wife, who received him ſo Civily, as he eaſily diſcern'd that there was nothing of Ruſtick nor ſavage in this family. Shee had by her young <hi>Policrite,</hi> and another Maid handſome enough, whom <hi>Policrite</hi> called Siſter, and whoſe name is <hi>Dorida:</hi> But, good Gods, how fair did <hi>Policrite</hi> appear to <hi>Philoxypes</hi> that day? Her Hair which hung careleſly over her Neck, and which were the one half covered by a thin Tiffany, were ty'd back behinde her head, with a Garland of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range and Pomegranate flowers, over which hung a thin Veile, with which ſhee covered her Face when ſhe went in the Sun, and which very well became her Dreſſing: The reſt of her Apparel was white, of a handſome ſhape; her Sleeves, which were very large, were truſt back
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151701:32"/>
with Ribbonds of ſeverall colours; and rhough there was nothing of ſtately in this habit; and that inſtead of Pearles and Diamonds, ſhee was only deck'd with flowrs, yet was there ſomwhat of ſo hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom and ſo comely in her Dreſſing, as ſhe never appear'd ſo fair to <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> the more he ſaw her, the more he was in love with her; and were it that he entertained <hi>Cleanthes,</hi> that he ſpoke to <hi>Megiſto,</hi> that he addreſt himſelf to <hi>Policrite,</hi> or that he ſaid ſomewhat of civility to <hi>Dorida,</hi> he was ſtill more and more taken. What did he not doe to make them tell him ſomewhat more then <hi>Cleanthes</hi> had told him, and to perſwade them that he might fit them with a better Lodging? He offer'd <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anthes</hi> Jewels to diſpoſe of at his pleaſure; but let him doe what he could, he could learn nothing, nor obtain nothing, ſave on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leav to come and viſit them ſometimes, which they granted him, meerly becauſe they knew not how to deny it him. I will not ſtay to tell you how frequently <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi> returned thither during twelve Dayes ſpace which he ſtaid at <hi>Claria,</hi> without returning to <hi>Paphos;</hi> but I will tell you, that <hi>Cleanthes,</hi> who had under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151701:32"/>
enough, and <hi>Megiſto</hi> who wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not any, eaſily perceived that it was <hi>Policrite</hi>'s beauty which occaſioned this Prince his ſo frequent Viſits, he read her a long Leſſon, and wiſht her to have a care of her ſelf, and that ſhe ſhould conſider that <hi>Philoxypes</hi> his affection could not but redound to her prejudice: and that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe ſhould live with him, as with one whom ſhe ſhould never look upon but meerly with reſpect, not ſuffering him to engage her in any particular affection. This mean while <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> who percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved he ſhould never have the Freedome to ſpeak to <hi>Policrite</hi> in particular, unleſſe it were by chance, came ſo often thither, as he met her once unaccompanied by any ſave the young <hi>Dorida.</hi> This being too fair an occaſion to let ſlip, he drew near unto her, and expreſſing much Love in his looks, Think not, <hi>Policrite,</hi> ſaid he, that I have any thing of miſ-becoming to ſay unto you, though I have diligently watched to entertain you alone; 'Tis only that not knowing how you will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive my affection, I was not deſirous to have any witneſſes of my misfortune or happineſs. Sir, ſaid ſhe, with a Maidenly-bluſh,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:151701:33"/>
before you ſpeak, conſider I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you where you are; mark well the Cottage wherein I live, and ſee what Cloaths I wear. No, <hi>Policrite,</hi> reply'd he, I ſee nothing but your Eyes, and had you a Crown of Diamonds on your head, I ſhould no more minde it then what you ſpeak of; ſo firmly are my lookes fixt upon your Beauty. Permit me then, Sir, ſaid the diſcreet and fair Maid, to teach you another thing, which it may be you are ignorant of, and which ought to keep you from ſaying any thing of unfit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to me. 'Tis, Sir, that this very <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite,</hi> whom you ſee in this Country Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, who is thus ſimply attir'd, who is only known to theſe Woods and Rocks, hath notwithſtanding her meanneſſe and ſimplicity, ſo tender a ſenſe of Honour, that ſhould you offend her never ſo little therein, ſhe were able to dye for ſorrow and diſlike. Be carefull then, Sir, to ſay nothing which may make <hi>Policrite</hi> beleev, that you know her not; for, in fine, ſhe hath ſuch a paſſion for Vertue, as ſhe ſhould have much adoe not to hate thoſe who ſhould ſay any thing unto her in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition thereunto. Fear not, ſaid he,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151701:33"/>
faireſt <hi>Policrite,</hi> that I ſhall ſay any thing to you, which ſhall offend you, at leaſt which ſhould offend you; for I proteſt unto you in the preſence of the gods, who hear me, that the paſſion which you have for flowers, fountains, and for theſe inameld fields, is not more pure, nor more inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, then that which I have for <hi>Philocrita;</hi> and if there be any difference between them, 'tis that the affection which I bear to her, is ſo violent and ſtrong, as there is nothing which I ſhall not willingly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to witneſs it unto her: You can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not better do it, Sir, ſaid ſhe, then in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me the favour to ſay no more ſuch things unto me, which will onely ſerve to trouble the quiet of my life, ſince if I ſhould not believe you, I ſhould certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſomewhat troubled to think you would laugh at my ſimplicity; and if I ſhould believe you, I ſhould almoſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair, for being the cauſe why a great Prince ſhould contract a paſſion ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of him, and from whence he can never reap any advantage.</p>
            <p>For in fine <hi>Policrite</hi> knowing her ſelf, and knowing you alſo, would not her ſelf commit a fault, nor yet cauſe you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:151701:34"/>
one for love of her; do not therefore ingage your ſelf Sir, in ſo angerſom an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture: Let me alone (ſaid ſhee, looking upon him with an eie, which did rather detain him then drive him away, though it were done without art) let me alone I ſay, amongſt our woods and rocks, and get you to your palaces where you will be much better then here. <hi>Philoxypes</hi> was aſtoniſhed to hear <hi>Policrite</hi> ſpeak thus, when throwing himſelf at her feet, no, no divine <hi>Policrite</hi> ſaid he, you are not what you appear to be; and though you were ſo, yet would your vertue place you in a degree above all the Queens in the world. Sir ſaid ſhee, raiſing him up, think not that I am to be wonn by flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; for though I know not the world by mine own experience, I know it by my Parents relation. I therefore know that love is a dangerous paſſion, and not knowing preciſely what it is, I know it ought to be avoided; and that I ought rather to apprehend that love which you ſay you bear me, then any other. And wherefore, <hi>Policrite</hi> ſaid he, do you thus treat that innocent paſſion, which you raiſed in my heart? becauſe ſaid ſhe, it
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:151701:34"/>
cannot be but injurious to <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> or to <hi>Policrite.</hi> but ſay for God's ſake ſaid he, ſuppoſe that <hi>Policrite</hi> were a Princeſs, or that <hi>Philoxypes</hi> were of the ſame condition that <hi>Policrite</hi> is; what would you then think of him? I cannot tell ſaid ſhee, but this I know ſir, that though I ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem him never ſo much, nay, though I ſhould love him very much, <hi>Cleanthes</hi> and <hi>Megiſto</hi> ſhould alwaies abſolutely di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe of me. Say then ſaid he, if they ſhould be favourable, would you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any repugnancy obey them? Sir ſaid ſhee, ſmiling a little, I have been ſo told that I muſt not lightly truſt any one, as I think it not convenient to reveal ſo great a ſecret to you. Hereupon <hi>Cleanthes</hi> and <hi>Megiſto</hi> returned, and broke off their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe; <hi>Philoxypes</hi> preſently obſerved that theſe two perſons were troubled at his viſits; he therefore reſolved not to be ſo frequent in them, leaſt he might for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver loſe a happineſs, which now he might ſometimes enjoy. Thus, Sir, <hi>Philoxypes</hi> after ſome ſhort diſcourſe departed, and returned not onely to <hi>Claria,</hi> but to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos,</hi> whether the King had alſo ſent for him; not being able to let him be ſo long
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:151701:35"/>
alone and ſolitary, all the Ladies, and the whole Court complained of him, and could not comprehend the reaſon of his ſo long retirement; The King continued to give him new teſtimonies of his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, by beſtowing on him the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Cithera,</hi> which was falne void by the death of the former governor. He acquainted him with what had befalne him during his abſence, with Princeſs <hi>Aretephile,</hi> and conjur'd him to ſpeak al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to her in his behalf. For ſaid he, <hi>Aretephile</hi> hath taken a phancy to be ſure of the Crown of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> before ſhe give me her heart, and I will have her give me her heart, before I give her the Crown. <hi>Philoxypes</hi> promiſed the King to ſpeak to <hi>Aretephile,</hi> but it was with ſuch ſadneſs as all the Court took notice of it. He did almoſt always little better then rave, he would miſtake, and ſay one thing for another, he ſhunn'd company, and as ſoon as he could, he returned to <hi>Claria.</hi> He found more reſiſtancy in <hi>Policrite,</hi> then he thought to have met withall; for ſhe, fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all things, durſt hardly look upon this Prince; the difference of his condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, though it made her more obliged
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:151701:35"/>
unto him in her ſoul, yet was it the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why ſhee treated him ſo coolly. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi> would have preſented the whole Family, but they all refuſed to receive any. This mean while he was ſtil more unhappie; for though he loved <hi>Policrita</hi> paſſionately, and that he valued her more then all the world beſides, yet could he never put on a reſolution of making any one acquainted with this his ſo mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly placed paſſion: He would certainly have been able to live with <hi>Policrita</hi> in any deſert Iſland; but he knew not how he could avow the marrying a Maid of her condition, to the world; yet did he ſtill love her with a reſpectfull affection, not giving way to any ſinfull deſire: That pure and unartificial vertue which he ſaw in <hi>Policrita,</hi> infuſed into him a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reſpect for her, then if ſhee had been ſeated on a Throne; he then perceiv'd he loved, without hope of ever finding a remedy for his evil, upon leſſer tearms, then reſolving to abandon the Court, and Kingdom, and to ask <hi>Policrita</hi> of <hi>Cleanthes</hi> upon ſo vexatious tearms; but that which moſt of all afflicted him was, that he knew not how he ſtood in <hi>Policrita's</hi> affection;
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:151701:36"/>
he found her milde and civil, he obſerves no marks of hatred in her countenance; but there was therein alſo ſo great a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedneſs, and ſo exact a modeſty, as he could not penetrate her thoughts: He thought alſo, that <hi>Policrita</hi> was grown ſomewhat more melancholly then ſhee had formerly been, and indeed he was not miſtaken, for <hi>Philoxypes</hi> his handſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, his good behaviour, his wit, and civility, being things not to be ſeen with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out likeing; young <hi>Policrita</hi> could not ſee her ſelf belov'd of ſuch a Prince as he, without having her heart a little toucht with acknowledgement; yet ſeeing her ſelf in a condition ſo farre beneath his, and out of a ſence of vertue ſhee muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt this budding affection, ſhe could not but be afflicted at this conqueſt which ſhee had made; and to bemoan her ſelf thereof to her dear <hi>Dorida</hi> who had wit enough. Siſter! ſaid ſhe unto her, how happie are you in compariſon of me, who can take pleaſure in walking abroad, in gathering of Flowers, in hearing birds ſing, and the fall of waters, and in not being reduced to a condition of complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of too much good fortune: For in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:151701:36"/>
fine <hi>Dorida, Philoxypes</hi> heart is a conqueſt which I am ſure the greateſt Queens would be proud to have made; yet whilſt they might innocently rejoice thereat, I muſt be therewithall afflicted: I could wiſh I had never ſeen him; or at leaſt I think I could: For when all is done, though methinks I could heartily deſire that he would love me no more, yet am I glad to ſee him. But if love, repli'd <hi>Dorida,</hi> be ſo powerfull a thing as it is ſaid to be, how know you but that <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi> may love you well enough to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry you? Ah Siſter, anſwered ſhe, as I would do nothing miſbeſeeming me, ſo neither would I that <hi>Philoxypes</hi> ſhould do any thing that might miſbeſeem him to do: But, ſaid <hi>Dorida,</hi> by like then you love <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> ſince you intereſt your ſelf in his honour, againſt your ſelf. <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crita</hi> bluſht at this diſcourſe, and looking confuſedly upon <hi>Dorida,</hi> if you were better acquainted with this paſſion then I, ſaid ſhe, I would tell you whatſoever my ſoul is ſenſible of, to the end I might know what to think of it; But I cannot yet believe that this dangerous diſeaſe be yet got into my heart; for if you remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber well, we have heard <hi>Cleanthes</hi> ſay, and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:151701:37"/>
we have read it more then once, that love makes one loſe their reaſon; that it cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a thouſand pains, and vexations, that it ſometimes makes people do amiſs; and I thank heaven, I do not yet feel any of all this; me thinks my reaſon is free e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and I am well enough pleaſed with the melancholly which poſſeſſeth me: For tis true, I oft times talk I know not what, but I delight in doing ſo; and though I would not love <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> yet there are certain moments wherein I am well enough pleaſed that he ſhould love me: But as for any thing of fault, ſo farre am I from being willing to commit any, as I proteſt unto you, that were it for no other reaſon, then not to loſe <hi>Philoxypes</hi> his eſteem and good opinion, I would die a thouſand deaths rather then do any thing that ſhould be unjuſt. You may then believe, that whilſt I love vertue, and would become worthy the affection of ſo great a Prince, I will never do any thing contrary to reputation. I believe you, anſwered <hi>Dorida;</hi> but for all this Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter mine, you deceive your ſelf, if you believe you love not <hi>Philoxypes:</hi> For in a word, you do not love what you lov'd
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:151701:37"/>
before you knew him, you are ſomewhat more comely, you conſult oftner with the Chriſtall fountains, and you are quite another thing then you were. Ah Siſter, replied <hi>Policrite,</hi> if that were true which you ſay, I would quickly take order for it, I would never ſee <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> but to uſe him harſhly; to the end, that he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting me, I might no longer love him. Theſe two young people having entertained themſelves thus upon the bank of a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle rivelet, <hi>Cleanthes</hi> and <hi>Megiſto,</hi> who had altered their minds, came thither; and bidding <hi>Dorida</hi> withdraw a little; <hi>Megiſto</hi> began to ſay; <hi>Policrite!</hi> it is not many days ſince I told you, that in reſpect of your condition, you ſhould never look upon <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> but with a great deal of reſpect; but fearing leſt through that inequality which you may believe to be between you and him, you may not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be ſo much obliged to him for his affection, as indeed to put ſomewhat too great an eſtimation thereupon: <hi>Clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes</hi> and my ſelf have reſolved to tell you, that your true condition conſidered, you are not bound to behold <hi>Philoxypes</hi> at any time, but with a great deal of indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency:
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151701:38"/>
For in a word, ſaid <hi>Cheanthes,</hi> not to diſguiſe the truth from you any longer, you are what you think not your ſelf to be, and we are likewiſe that which you know not, and what you ſhall not as yet know; becauſe the Gods have not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted us as yet to let you know it: But to ſhew you how much you are more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged then you think for, to be vertuous, know <hi>Policrite</hi> that you are of as Noble blood as any is in all <hi>Greece:</hi> And how anſwered <hi>Policrite,</hi> interupting him, am I not what I alwaies thought to be? No daughter ſaid he; to number Kings amongſt your Anceſtors, is not the greateſt mark of honour that you make boaſt of. There is ſomewhat of more Auguſt in your race, then what I ſpeak of: Therefore that I might raiſe up your heart, I thought it good to truſt you with this important ſecret, (which I charge you not to reveal to any one) as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to let you know the better how much bound you are not to doe any thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of your Fathers houſe, nor of the condition you are born in. <hi>Policrite</hi> was exceedingly joy'd to hear <hi>Cleanthes</hi> ſpeak after this manner, though her joy was
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151701:38"/>
not over quiet; for ſhee was in trouble to know more preciſely what was told her. Father ſaid ſhee, leave me not in ſuch perplexity; tell me a little more plainly, I beſeech you, ſo pleaſing a truth, and let me know who I am.</p>
            <p>The Gods have forbidden us it, my daughter, anſwered he, by the mouth of an Oracle: you muſt be content with what you have heard: but make uſe thereof to defend your ſelf againſt <hi>Philox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ypes</hi> love; and far from looking on him, as on a Prince who hath don you too much honour: look rather on him, as on one whom you ſhall favour by your per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance.</p>
            <p>This is not, ſaid <hi>Cleanthes,</hi> to deny, but that <hi>Philoxypes</hi> is indow'd with all the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and qualities requiſite for a great Prince; but tis, my childe, to let you know, that there is a certain pride which doth not miſ-become a young maide to defend her ſelf thereby againſt love, when we have an eſteem; for thoſe that are above us, tis hard to gainſay, if they intreat. And on the contrary, when we believe them to be beneath us, or at leaſt but our equals, we ſtand not much upon
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:151701:39"/>
denying them unjuſt things. <hi>Policrite</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured then <hi>Cleanthes</hi> and <hi>Megiſto,</hi> That though ſhee had known nothing of what they now had told her, ſhee ſhould never have done any thing contrary to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency which ſhee had learnt of them. But how much were they miſtaken, if their deſign were to hinder <hi>Policrite</hi> from lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Philoxypes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sometimes ſhee was filled with joy, to know that ſhe was of Noble deſcent; and afterwards, being willing to make uſe thereof; to drive thereby the begining of affection which <hi>Philoxypes</hi> worth had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready raiſed in her, out of her heart, ſhee found it the more fortified by this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. For ſaid ſhee, the knowledge of what I am, doth not take from the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which I ow him; ſince he knows not that I am any thing more then what I ſeem to be.</p>
            <p>But for me, who now know what I am, why ſhould I not hope that the Gods per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting <hi>Philoxypes</hi> to know my true condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, may not ſo order it, as that I may love him and be blameleſs, and be belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by him innocently? No, no, <hi>Policrite</hi> added ſhee, let us no longer defend our
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:151701:39"/>
heart any longer with ſuch opiniatrecie; let us content our ſelves with concealing our recentments, &amp; do nothing that ſhall be faulty: &amp; let us not reject, as a miſchief the love of a Prince, to whom the wiſeſt king of the world would not refuſe to giv his daughter. But it may be, ſaid ſhe, that <hi>Philoxypes</hi> doth but counterfeit, that he hath ſinful thoughts towards thee, and that thy ſimplicity abuſeth thee.</p>
            <p>Stay then, ſaid ſhe, to be reſolved here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and make trial of his conſtancy and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, by an appearing indifferency, which may leave him without hope.</p>
            <p>Thus was <hi>Policrite</hi> minded, when <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi> came to her; as ſoon as ſhe ſaw, him ſhe b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gan to go towards her Cottage; but he, advancing haſtily, ſtayed her; yet not being above twenty paces from it, and there being two of her women-ſervants at work in a Cloſe hard by them, ſhe ſtayed. What, <hi>Policrite,</hi> ſaid he, you ſhun a Prince, who ſhuns all the world for love of you? Sir, ſaid ſhe, (after ſomewhat more an imperious manner then before, though ſhe intended not ſo to do) I do what peradventure you ought to doe: For in fine, what advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:151701:40"/>
can you hope for by your viſits and ſolicitations? The contentment ſaid he, to hear from your fair mouth, that you do not hate me: If that be all you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be ſatisfied in, replyed ſhe, you may eaſily compaſſe your deſires; but ask no more, upon pain of refuſall. What, lovely <hi>Policrite,</hi> ſaid he, will you never love me, and ſhall all I can do to win your affection, prove uſeleſs? no, 'tis impoſſible, were you as incenſible, as thoſe pictures which I have of you. My pictures, replyed <hi>Policrite?</hi> Yes, added <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> I am not ſo unfortunate as you think for; in deſpight of you, and without your conſent, I have the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of ſeeing you daily.</p>
            <p>Ah! ſaid <hi>Policrite,</hi> I perceive <hi>Mandro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> hath betrayed me, and hath falſified his word. <hi>Philoxypes</hi> askt her then, how ſhe came to know <hi>Mandrocles?</hi> She told him how that famous Painter walking daily when his leiſure would permit him, amongſt thoſe rocks to draw ſome lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skips, had one day by chance light up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their houſe: where, having ſeen her, he had begg'd leave of <hi>Cleanthes</hi> to draw her pict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, which <hi>Cleanthes</hi> would have
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:151701:40"/>
refuſed him, but that ſeeing his impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, he was afraid leſt he might ſpeak of her to him at <hi>Claria,</hi> and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he gave way unto his deſire, upon condition that he ſhould not make uſe of this picture, in any of his pieces, but as of a head made by fancy and imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and making him take a ſolemn oath, never to ſpeak with any body whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, of any acquaintance he had with them. That ſince that time, as long as <hi>Mandrocles</hi> tarryed at <hi>Claria,</hi> he came to teach her to deſign, and had drawn her picture in twenty ſeveral poſtures. She then enquired of <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> whether <hi>Mandrocles</hi> had ſpoken to him of her, or no? And he told her the whole truth: but you may perceive, ſaid <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> that the Goddeſs whom you repreſent, intends not that you ſhould always be inhumane, ſince ſhe would her ſelf appear in your vizage.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid ſhe, not being of your Iſle, my devotion leads me rather to be a Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs to <hi>Diana,</hi> then to worſhip <hi>Venus U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rania;</hi> therefore it is not this your reaſon that will prevail with me: to boot, that his Goddeſs approving only of ſuch paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:151701:41"/>
as are innocent, will certainly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver councel me to admit of yours. Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues ſelf, replyed <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe you to it; and did you know my heart, you would need no other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor then your ſelf. It would take up ſo much time, replied ſhe, to make me know it, as I ſhall adviſe you not to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake the work. But ſaid he, if I do undertake it, and if I make it evident to you, that never man loved any thing as I love you, what will you then think? I would think, ſaid ſhe, that you were very unfortunate, in having ſo paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately loved one, who is unworthy of ſo much honor. But ſaid he, would you think your ſelf any waies obliged unto me? I ſhould be ſorrie for you, ſaid ſhe, and would wiſh your cure either by ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, or by forgetfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>Ah! cruel maid, ſaid he, wiſh it rather by your compaſſion and charity; and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe me only that you will afford me lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to perſwade you, that I am the moſt in love of all men. To do as you ſay, ſaid ſhe, would be to be ſomewhat per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded thereunto already; therefore (and with this, ſhe walked towards her Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage)
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:151701:41"/>
I will liſten no longer to you. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this manner did <hi>Philoxypes</hi> paſs away his time; having but very few moments of delight, amongſt many howres of anguiſh.</p>
            <p>This mean while, he could not endure to tarry at <hi>Paphos,</hi> and when he went thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, all he could do, was only to viſit the Princeſſe <hi>Aretephile,</hi> which the King compelled him to do; but he appeared ſo melancholly, and ſo changed, as he was hardly to be known. The King, who loved him dearly, was much afflicted to ſee it; he together with the whole court, ſought what might be the occaſion of this alteration; but they could not finde it. The King askt it of <hi>Philoxypes</hi> ſelf, but could learn nothing. <hi>Philoxypes</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring alwaies, that it was ſome melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which proceeded certainly from his temper, and from ſome little indiſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of health.</p>
            <p>But ſaid the King, ſolitarineſs is no u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual cure for ſuch incommodities; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ought not to go any more to <hi>Claria:</hi> Yet affairs went ſtill on thus, yea even when Winter was come, which did the more aſtoniſh the whole Court; they
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:151701:42"/>
knew he built no more at <hi>Claria,</hi> that the Painters and Engravers, who had been ſo long there, were all gone; that the ſeaſon was foul; that when he went thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, 'twas but with a ſmall train; and that he walked alwaies alone: they ſaw a ſtrange ſadneſſe in his face, and a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful alteration; and all this without any appearing cauſe. The King heaped favours and honours upon him; he askt him an hundred times, what he vvould deſire of him: he had not any one ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie; the whole Court loved him; hee was exceeding rich; he appeared not to have any ſickneſſe, as the Phyſitians could perceive: In fine, his melancholie and retiredneſſe, were things which could not be gueſt at. The whole Court talkt of nothing elſe; and the King was ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly troubled at it; who, not knowing how to inform himſelf of what <hi>Philoxypes</hi> ail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he bethought himſelf of me, whom he knew this Prince did love particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and in whom he did more confide, then in any other.</p>
            <p>Thus upon a day, when <hi>Philoxypes</hi> was gone to <hi>Claria,</hi> the King ſent for me; and after having aſſured his Majeſtie, (as it
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151701:42"/>
was true) that I knew nothing of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular concerning this Prince his melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, he did me the honour to command me to go to him, and to uſe all my cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to diſcover what it was that was in his minde: For, ſaid he, <hi>Leontidas,</hi> I doe ſo love <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> as I cannot live con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent unleſſe I ſee he do ſo likewiſe; and were it to give him half my Kingdom, I would doubtleſly do it, rather then not to give him ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>I then departed, reallie intending to endeavour to ſatisfie the Kings curioſitie, who certainlie ſtood in need of <hi>Philoxy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes</hi> preſence, to counſel and comfort him concerning <hi>Aretephiles</hi> behaviour; for I think there was never known a ſtiffer combat between ambition and love.</p>
            <p>I went then to <hi>Claria</hi> where I found <hi>Philoxypes</hi> in his uſual melancholie; the which I made the greater, becauſe I hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred him from going that daie to <hi>Clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes.</hi> At firſt ſight of me, he endeavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red notwithſtanding, to inforce himſelf to honor me ſo much, as to ſeem glad to ſee me; but it was after a faſhion, which made me eaſilie ſee that his heart gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid his words; and that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151701:43"/>
any friendſhip he had for me, he wiſht I had tarried ſtill at <hi>Paphos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leontidas!</hi> ſaid he, I am much behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to you for coming to viſit me in a ſeaſon, when the Countrie hath loſt all its ornaments; and when the Court is fulleſt of diverſions.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid I, you commend me with leſs reaſon, then the Court complains of you; for to forgo <hi>Paphos</hi> for <hi>Claria,</hi> when you are there, 'tis to forgo the Court, for the Court; nay, for the moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing part of the Court: but to forgo <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos,</hi> only to ſeek out ſolitarines at <hi>Claria,</hi> as you do, Oh, Sir, ſaid I, (not ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him notwithſtanding of any paſſion) 'tis all that a Prince in love, who is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on bad tearms with his Miſtreſſe, can do. <hi>Philoxypes</hi> bluſht at theſe words, and looking upon me with a kind of ſmile, which did not, notwithſtanding drive the melancholy from his countenance; I perceive, <hi>Leontidas,</hi> ſaid he, I am not ſo much beholding to you, as I had thought, ſince doubtleſlie you are come hither rather to chide me, then to viſit me.</p>
            <p>I am come, Sir, ſaid I, to trie whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:151701:43"/>
I may not be able to ſerve you in a time when all the world believes that ſomewhat of great importance, which they cannot gueſs at, doth afflict you. <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ontidas,</hi> ſaid he, I am much bound to you, but I ſhould be ſo more, if you could hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Court from looking ſo far into my heart. For I confeſs ſaid he, I finde it ſomewhat hard that a man may not look inwards ſometimes, though whilſt he does ſo, he is hardly maſter of his own minde.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid I, were you leſs beloved, you would not ſuffer under this perſecution which you complain of: This kinde of Love replied he, cauſeth in me no ſmall ſuffering: For what can I more rational<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do, then to conceal my Melanchollie in a retiredneſs, to the end that I may not trouble the joy of others. But Sir, ſaid I, tis the cauſe of this Melanchollie which every body ſeeks after, and none can finde: as for my particular, I muſt crave your pardon if I do. For Sir, tis not am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition that torments you. No, <hi>Leontydas,</hi> ſaid he, if I were ſick of that diſeaſe, the King would quicklie cure me. Neither is it revenge, ſaid I, for not being hated
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:151701:44"/>
by any, it is not to be believed that you are poſſeſt with hatred. You have reaſon for what you ſay, ſaid he; and ſighing ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, I think I am mine own greateſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. It is not ſaid I again the paſſion which you have for books, for that paſſion may cauſe ſolitarineſs, but not ſuch melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as you are poſſeſt withall. And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, you have had that paſſion a long time, without the product of ſo bad an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. It is not books certainly ſaid he, which cauſe my trouble, which were I capable of reaſon, would rather be my comfort. It is not Love ſaid I, that torments you, for you ſee none that can cauſe it in you. Conclude then, ſaid he, taking me in his arms, that there is no more to be ſaid, but that I hate my ſelf, that I have loſt my reaſon, and if my friends be wiſe, they will let me alone, and will leave the knowledge, or cure of my malladie, to the proceſs of time.</p>
            <p>Sir ſaid I, ſhall <hi>Leontidas,</hi> who hath ſo particular an affection for you, be dealt withall as others are? ſhal he have known nothing more of your concernments, then do your enemies, if any ſuch you have? Ah, Sir, ſaid I, you muſt if you pleaſe do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe:
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:151701:44"/>
&amp; to prove to you that <hi>Leontidas</hi> doth in ſom ſort deſerve you ſhould do ſo, know Sir, that hitherto I have ſpoken un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you as a ſpie, ſent by the King, who will know at whatſoever priſe, what tis that afflicts your minde. But after having boot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly acquitted my ſelf of my Commiſſion, I ſpeak no longer Sir, as one ſent by the King, but as one who is reſolved to ſerve you with his life, if it ſhall be needfull; and never abſolutely to give you over till he know the cauſe of your Melancholy: for Sir, if there be no cauſe of this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, and that it be but a diſtemper of humours, I muſt ſtay here, that I may endeavour, mauger your ſelf, to divert you; and if there be any cauſe for it, <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ontidas</hi> muſt likewiſe ſerve you therein, if there ſhould redound no other benefit to you thereby, then to help you to keep it concealed from the King, and from the whole Court, if you deſire it ſhould be concealed from them.</p>
            <p>I do not know any way, ſaid he, to keep it undiſcovered better, then to tell it to no body.</p>
            <p>But Sir, ſaid I, if you treat me with this indifferencie, when I ſhall return to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos,</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:151701:45"/>
and the King ſhall ask me what I think of your Melancholie, I muſt needs ſay ſomething to him.</p>
            <p>And what will you ſay to him, replied <hi>Philoxypes?</hi> I think Sir, ſaid I, that to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge my ſelf for the little confidence you have in me, I will ſay what I do no waies believe, to wit, that you are in love; and that the ſhame of your former inflex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs, or of your new weakneſs, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders you from avowing it: nay, I will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure tel him, ſaid I, in mockerie, that that <hi>Venus Urania,</hi> which people have ſo much quarrel'd with you about ſince the great feaſt which you made here, and which did precede but a few daies your melancholy humor hath ſtruck you effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ually in love. In fine ſir, there is nothing of ſo odd, which I ſhall not ſay to revenge my ſelf for the wrong you do the paſſion which I have to your ſervice.</p>
            <p>During this diſcourſe; <hi>Philoxypes</hi> chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged colour twentie times; and were it out of friendſhip, or out of my importu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nitie, or that indeed thoſe that are in love love naturallie to ſpeak thereof, he took me by the hand, led me into his Cabinet, and after having made me take ſundrie
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:151701:45"/>
ſolemn Oaths, never to diſcover what he ſhould ſay unto me; and all this with as much ceremonie, and preſſure, as if he had ſome conſpiracie to diſcover unto me againſt the ſtate, or ſome attempt upon the Kings Perſon; he told me that he was in love.</p>
            <p>What Sir, ſaid I, theſe retirements, theſe Melanchollies, and this impenetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſecret, which all the world in vain ſeeks to finde out: is it onely that you are in Love? Ah, <hi>Leontydas,</hi> ſaid he, mock not at my miſery; for it is greater then you can imagine. But Sir, ſaid I, I have much ado to imagine that you can be ſo unfortunate as you ſay, ſince <hi>I</hi> cannot conceive that there is e're a Princeſs in the Kingdom (except ambitious <hi>Arete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phile,</hi> who will be Queen) who will not favourably entertain your affection, when you ſhall make it known unto her. Alas! ſaid he, with a ſigh, Love hath dealt much more cruellie with me then you are aware of; and ſince <hi>I</hi> muſt diſcover unto you the ſecret of my heart, know that <hi>I</hi> have met with an invincible reſiſtance, in one who lives amongſt theſe rocks, and dwels but in a cottage.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:151701:46"/>
Yes <hi>Leondidas, I</hi> have found a maid, or to ſay better, <hi>I</hi> have found virtue it ſelf, wholely pure, and under the viſeage of <hi>Venus Urania,</hi> which hath and doth yet reſiſt me. A maid who is not touch'd with ambition; in whom beautie cauſeth no affectation nor pride; who hath ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie and wit, gallantrie and ſinceritie; and who in a ſandie and deſart place, which the Gods alone have pointed out unto me: ſpeaks better then all the wittieſt Ladies in the Court</p>
            <p>But when all this is done, ſhe lives in a Cottage, her condition appears to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mean, if <hi>I</hi> conſider all that is about her; and when <hi>I</hi> conſider onely her ſelf, or do but hear her ſpeak, ſhee appears to be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a throne: Her Governours are virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and diſcreet, but ſtill <hi>Leontidas</hi> they live in a Cottage, and will not abandon it. At laſt ſaid he with tears almoſt ſtanding in his eies, <hi>I</hi> am the moſt unfortunate of all men: <hi>I</hi> have a paſſion which <hi>I</hi> cannot overcome, and which <hi>I</hi> will not have known: <hi>I</hi> too much reſpect <hi>Policrite</hi>'s worth (for ſo is ſhee called of whom <hi>I</hi> ſpeak) to have any ſinful deſire towards
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:151701:46"/>
her, which though <hi>I</hi> ſhould have, t'would be to no purpoſe: <hi>I</hi> likewiſe am too great a lover of Glorie, to reſolve to marry a maid of this condition without much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnancie,; Yet can <hi>I</hi> not live without her: my ſufferings are ſuch that <hi>I</hi> cannot expreſs them, and ſeeing no remedie for my Malladie; <hi>I</hi> bear it patientlie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out complaining of it, and void of all hope but death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phyloxypes</hi> told me this in ſo feeling a manner, as <hi>I</hi> much pittied him: He then told me all that had befallen him: How t'was he met <hi>Policrite,</hi> how he was ſurprized that it was ſhee by whom <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drocles</hi> had drawn the Picture of <hi>Venus Ura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> and all the reſt which <hi>I</hi> have told you. <hi>I</hi> was ſomewhat ſurprized at this fantaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ick paſſion, chieflie when <hi>I</hi> call'd to mind <hi>Philoxypes</hi> former inflexibleneſs; Yet did <hi>I</hi> endeavor to comfort him. Sir, ſaid <hi>I,</hi> ſuch a beauty as that is which you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent unto me, and ſuch a one as <hi>I</hi> have ſeen in the <hi>Venus</hi> in your Gallerie, bears ſome excuſe with it, of what condition ſoever the poſſeſſors are, eſpeciallie when it occaſions onelie ſom paſſing paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and which are of no long durance,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:151701:47"/>
as <hi>I</hi> wil hope yours will prove. No, no, ſaid he <hi>Leontydas,</hi> do not deceive your ſelves; <hi>I</hi> will love <hi>Polycrite</hi> till death. But Sir, not to abuſe your patience, perceiving <hi>Philoxypes</hi> grievance too great to be cured <hi>I</hi> ſmoothed it, and ſweetened it as much as poſſible <hi>I</hi> could. He then led me into his gallerie, to ſhew me his excuſe, though <hi>I</hi> had ſeen his pictures many times before: we afterwards walked abroad, but he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able onely to walk one way, we were ſoon amongſt the Rocks, in a place from whence we might diſcover <hi>Policryte</hi>'s ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation, which we no ſooner ſaw, but bluſhing with confuſion, he ſaid tis there my dear <hi>Leontydas</hi> where ſhe that <hi>I</hi> adore doth live; tis underneath that roofe, which <hi>I</hi> prefer before the proudeſt Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that <hi>Philoxypes</hi> findes ſome moments of content: and tis there in fine that all my joy and happineſs is circumſcribed. Sir ſaid <hi>I,</hi> there needs no greater proofes of <hi>Polycrytes</hi> beautie, then the ſmalneſs of her Cottage; and whoſoever ſhall ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that <hi>Phyloxypes</hi> affection is placed therein, cannot doubt but that he hath ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued the matter with himſelf as much as he was able.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:151701:47"/>
In fine, Sir, after that he had enlarged himſelf in expreſſing <hi>Policrytes</hi> charming beautie, not ſuffering me to ſee her for fear of offending her: <hi>I</hi> muſt think of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to <hi>Paphos,</hi> for <hi>I</hi> had promiſed the King to return that very night. <hi>I</hi> asked <hi>Phyloxypes</hi> what <hi>I</hi> ſhould ſay unto him; any thing ſaid he my dear <hi>Leontydas</hi> rather then the truth of my adventure: For in the minde that <hi>I</hi> am of, <hi>I</hi> think that <hi>I</hi> ſhould run mad if the King ſhould know it.</p>
            <p>I then left him after he had made me ſwear a hundred times, not to diſcover the leaſt part of his misfortune. I went to finde out the King, who expected me with much impatiency, and who had pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely withdrawn himſelf early, to the end that I might ſpeak with more free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to him when I ſhould return.</p>
            <p>And How, <hi>Leontydas,</hi> ſaid he? what doth our ſolitarie companion do?</p>
            <p>Sir ſaid I, terming him as you do, your Majeſty may eaſily gueſs at what he does. He muſes, he walks, he reads; looks upon his pictures, and ſtatues; goes from one place to another, and ſeeking eaſe every where, he findes it no where.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:151701:48"/>
But <hi>Leontydas,</hi> ſaid he, you ſpeak to me as <hi>Philoxypes</hi> doth, and tis not that which I expect from you.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid I, I have done all I am able to ſatisfie your Majeſtie; but I confeſs my journey hath not been ſo ſucceſsfull as I hoped for: For all that <hi>Philoxypes</hi> ſaies, is only that he findes himſelf ſomewhat ill diſpoſed, and that he is poſſeſt with a Melancholy which he cannot maſter.</p>
            <p>Did you ask him ſaid the King, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were not that he did wiſh for ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what which I have not be thought my ſelf to give him, becauſe I knew not that he did deſire it?</p>
            <p>Oh, Sir, ſaid I, (thinking I had done well) it is not ambition that torments <hi>Philoxypes</hi> who is ſo ſatisfied with your Majeſties goodneſs, as he deſires nothing more then what he hath.</p>
            <p>Have you then diſcovered, ſaid he, that he hath any thing of private diſcontent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any one of this Court? For if it be ſo, I will make his intereſt mine, and will as ſeverely revenge any injury done unto him, as if it had been done unto my ſelf.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid I, <hi>Philoxypes</hi> appears to be ſo well beloved of all the world, as tis hard
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:151701:48"/>
to think any one ſhould injure him. I know not then what to imagine, ſaid the King; but if <hi>Philoxypes</hi>'s Ambition be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, and that it is not hatred nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge that doth trouble him, he muſt needs be in Love.</p>
            <p>Your Majeſtie, Sir, ſaid I, doth too wel know <hi>Philoxypes</hi>'s inflexibleneſs, to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect any ſuch thing in him. No <hi>Leonty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>Philoxypes</hi> paſt obduretie, is not a Reaſon ſtrong enough to perſwade me that he is obdurat ſtil. I am almoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident that tis this paſſion which robs me of <hi>Philoxypes</hi>'s companie; For in fine he hath all the marks of one in love. His countenance is altered, he not having been ſick; he is melancholly without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny appearing cauſe: he doth little elſe but rave; he cannot ſtay long in a place; he conceals his melancholly from us; he cannot endure that one ſhould take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it; he gives over thinking of his affairs; he viſits none but by conſtraint, and unleſs it be the Princeſs <hi>Aretephile,</hi> whom he hath ſeen by my command, he hath not viſited any one Ladie ſince we were at <hi>Claria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid I, part of what you alleadge to
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:151701:49"/>
prove that <hi>Philoxypes</hi> is in Love, me thinks makes for the contrarie: For if he were in Love, he would certainly ſeek out the partie beloved; we ſhould never ſee him from her: inſtead of being me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanchollie, he would ſtudie to play the Gallant more, and would be the more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciable: and inſtead of ſeeking out ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs, as he doth, me thinks he ſhould rather add to the Court diverſions: and that his chiefeſt imployments ſhould be muſick, Baals, converſation, and going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad.</p>
            <p>You ſay well, anſwered the King, for what concerns ordinarie paſſions, or ſuch Lovers as have been fortunate in their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections; but there are certain giddie headed paſſions out of the common road, which ariſing from a melanchollie an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, feed themſelves therewithall, and ſhun whatſoever affords delight. But that which doth a little trouble me, is that I cannot imagin who tis that <hi>Philoxy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes</hi> can love, &amp; be hardlie dealt withal by; for certainly there is never a Ladie in all my Court, who would not glorie in ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving wonn his heart: and moreover I have not obſerved that he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:151701:49"/>
himſelf to converſe with any one in particular, yet doubtleſlie <hi>Philoxy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes</hi> is in Love.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid I, be not ſo reſolute in your aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion, till you have ſtronger proofes thereof, and till you may at leaſt conject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture who it is he is in love withall. The King began then to number over all the Ladies of the Court, one by one, &amp; found not any one of them that he was likelie to be in Love withall.</p>
            <p>He then began to walk not ſaying one word: ſoon after I ſaw ſome colour com in his face, and preſently, me thought, he was much diſquieted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Leontydas,</hi> ſaid he, you know more then you will tell me.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid I, I have ſaid nothing but truth unto your Majeſtie. For in fine <hi>Phyloxy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes</hi> his Ambition is ſatisfied; he hath no enemies that I know of; and if I be not deceived, the faireſt Ladies of the Court have no great power over him.</p>
            <p>Ah! <hi>Leontydas,</hi> ſaid he, you conceal the truth from me; but I know it without your telling. Yes, <hi>Leontydas,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>Philoxy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes</hi> doth Love, and ſo love, as doubtleſlie he is much afflicted thereat, and which he
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:151701:50"/>
will withſtand and overcome: were not my thought true, he would not make his paſſion ſo great a ſecret. But good Gods, ſaid he, how unfortunate am I? and to what ſtrange extremitie am I reduced; for in fine, <hi>Leontydas,</hi> ſaid he, confeſs the truth, <hi>Phyloxypes,</hi> mauger himſelf, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come my rival, and his grief for it is the cauſe of his melanchollie.</p>
            <p>Ah! Sir, ſaid I, (not having leaſure to think of what I ſaid) I know not the cauſe of <hi>Philoxypes</hi> his melanchollie; but I very well know he is not in Love with Princeſs <hi>Aretephile,</hi> and that he too much reſpects your Majeſtie to ſuffer ſuch a thought enter his breſt.</p>
            <p>Think well <hi>Leontydas,</hi> ſaid he, on what you ſay: you aſſure me you know not the cauſe of <hi>Phyloxypes</hi> his melanchollie, and yet you know he is not my rivall: once more <hi>Leontydas,</hi> if you know the buſineſs, let me know it: or if you know it not; confeſs my ſuſpitions are well grounded, and fear not for all this, that I wiſh any harm to <hi>Phyloxypes:</hi> on the contrarie I ſhal be beholden to him for it.</p>
            <p>I was extreamly troubled to hear the King talk thus; for without violating
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:151701:50"/>
what we hold moſt ſacred, I could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal <hi>Philoxypes</hi> his ſecret, which he had made me ſwear above a hundred times not to do.</p>
            <p>To conſent likewiſe that the King ſhould ſuſpect him to be his Rivall, me thought it was a buſineſs of too great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance to leave him in that opinion; but the more I perſwaded him to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, the more firmly did he believe it. No, ſaid he, I am cauſe of mine own miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, and of <hi>Phylxoipes</hi> his misfortune too: tis <hi>I</hi> who made him viſit <hi>Aretephile</hi> more then any other; tis mine own hand that hath enthrall'd him, and tis <hi>I</hi> who am the cauſe of all his ſufferings: For ſaid he, <hi>I</hi> eaſilie comprehend he ſeeks out all this ſolitarineſs onely to rid him of this paſſion: nay, <hi>I</hi> have obſerved that of late he hath been troubled as oft as <hi>I</hi> have ſpoken to him to ſpeak to <hi>Aretephile,</hi> that he hath ſhun'd ſuch Commiſſions as much as he could; and I am too much perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that he hath argued the buſineſs ſtifly with himſelf, and I am the onely cauſe of what he ſuffers.</p>
            <p>Good gods, ſaid he, how great is my misfortune? there is not any one man in
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:151701:51"/>
all my Kingdom, whom I ſhould not hate if he were my rival, unleſs it be he; and there is not any Ladie in the Court, in whoſe Love he would not have been hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, except <hi>Aretaphile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Sir, ſaid I again, I proteſt unto you he is not in love with her; and I proteſt to you, replied he, expreſſing an extream grief, that <hi>Philoxypes</hi> is my Rival; for were it not ſo, he would not conceal his paſſion from me.</p>
            <p>The reſpect he bears to you, ſaid I, ought to hinder him from ſo doing, if he were in Love.</p>
            <p>No, no, replied he, you ſhall no longer abuſe me; and I am equally perſwaded of <hi>Philoxypes</hi> his love, of his innocencie, and of my misfortune. For in fine, that the man in the world that I love beſt, ſhould fall in Love with the onelieſt Ladie that I can Love: and that I ſhould ſee my ſelf cruelly neceſſitated, either to forſake <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retaphile,</hi> or to ſee <hi>Philoxypes</hi> die, it is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufferable adventure.</p>
            <p>Sir, I beſeech you, ſaid I, expect till ſhe hath once more ſeen <hi>Phyloxypes,</hi> and have abſolutelie commanded him to diſcover his heart unto her, before you reſolve on
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:151701:51"/>
any thing; and if you pleaſe I will bring him hither to morrow morning.</p>
            <p>No, no, replied the King, you ſhall not ſtir out of the Pallace this day; nor ſhall you ſee <hi>Phyloxypes</hi> before me. In effect this Prince gave one of his ſervants charge over me; and commanded me to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw into a Chamber, which was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for me in the Pallace.</p>
            <p>'Twould be too difficult a thing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent unto you my vexation, and the Kings diſquiet: ſince to tell you true, he had as much friendſhip for <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> as Love for <hi>Aretaphile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who ever ſaw, ſaid he, (for he himſelf told it afterwards) an adventure like to mine? I have a Rival whom I muſt love in deſpight of me, and who gives me more occaſion to love him, for the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction he bears to my Miſtreſs, then for all the ſervice he ever did me; and then for all the good Offices he hath done me to her, it being certain that I need onely look upon him, to ſee what he ſuffers in my conſideration; and that I need onely conſider what life he leads, to ſee how much I am beholden to him. I obſerve in his eies a melancholly, which makes me
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:151701:52"/>
apprehend his death: and I ſeein all his actions, viſible ſigns of his love to <hi>Areta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phile,</hi> and of his reſpect to me. What ſhall I do, ſaid he? ſhall I ſeem not to know this paſſion, and let <hi>Philoxypes</hi> die? But tis no longer time to conceal what I think, ſince <hi>Leontidas</hi> knows it. <hi>Leontidas</hi> who is ſo much his confident, and ſhares ſo deeply in his friendſhip: ſhall I alſo tel <hi>Philoxypes</hi> that I know his love, and not complain of him? and if I ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, how weak a ſuccor would this be? I ſhould peradventure haſten his hour of death, by making him diſpair. But ſhall I quit <hi>Aretaphile,</hi> and let my friendſhip ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed my Love? <hi>Philoxypes</hi> his paſſion is unjuſt; but paſſions are not voluntarie, and he hath done what ever he could, or ought to have done, ſince not being able to keep from loving, he hath yet kept from making his love known; and hath rather choſen to hazard his life by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectfull ſilence, then to preſerve it by making his paſſion known, which he knows will diſpleaſe me.</p>
            <p>The King paſt the night in this manner very unquietly: ſometimes he was agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated with anger, and hatred, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:151701:52"/>
whom he hated, or on whom he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to be revenged: ſometimes he did a little blame <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> for not having at the very firſt acquainted him with his paſſion: ſometime he betook himſelf to <hi>Aretaphiles</hi> beauty; but at laſt he blamed himſelf.</p>
            <p>Then ſuddainly conſidering the pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full condition into which <hi>Phyloxypes</hi> was brought, and what an unhappy life he led, his heart was ſo touched with compaſſion as he did almoſt love his pretended Rival, better then his Miſtreſs. He then called to minde, how that all the favours he had received from her, had been husbanded, and obtained by <hi>Phyloxipes</hi> his means. He paſt the next morning in like perplexitie, and ſtrange irreſolutions; at laſt having dined ſomewhat early, he went well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied to lie that night at <hi>Claria,</hi> not affording me any opportunitie to give a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny notice thereof to <hi>Philoxypes;</hi> for he into whoſe cuſtodie I was given, thinking it had been for ſome buſineſs of another nature, treated me as a priſoner of the State and would not give me the leaſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie.</p>
            <p>The king commanded me to follow him,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:151701:53"/>
ſo as I came with him to <hi>Claria,</hi> he not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſpoken one word all the way long, but muſing ſtill on his adventure: But when we were come thither, <hi>Phyloxipes</hi>'s people told the King, that their Maſter was not at home; and that according to his cuſtom, he was walked out all alone. The King informed himſelf carefully of one of his ſervants, who had a long time waited on him, whether he knew not the cauſe of his Maſters melancholly: this ſervant who loved his Maſter dearly, that he might make uſe of the honour the King did him in ſpeaking to him, ſaid;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir, I know not what my maſter ayles, but this I know, that if your Majeſtie out of your goodneſs finde not ſome means to cure him of the Melancholly which poſſeſſeth him, he will certain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly not live long; For he eats little, hardly ſleeps at all, does nothing but ſigh, cannot endure that one ſhould ſpeak to him about buſines, wanders whole daies in the fields; and I once heard him cry out, when he little thought I did ſo. Good gods, what would the King ſay, if he ſaw how great my ſadneſs is! and how hardly would he gueſs at the cauſe of my death?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In fine Sir, ſaid this man, with tears al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in his eyes, <hi>I know not what to ſay, but</hi>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:151701:53"/>
               <hi>I am very certain your Majeſty will loſe the faithfulleſt of all your ſervants, if you loſe the Prince my Maſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whileſt this man ſpake thus, I was ſtrangely in pain; for I ſaw all that he ſaid tended to confirm the King in his Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: I was much the better for beckning unto him, he never looked on me, ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent was he to what he ſaid.</p>
            <p>The King on his part ſighed, and having left the other, well, <hi>Leontidas,</hi> you will not have it that <hi>Philoxypes</hi> is in Love, nor that it is <hi>Aretaphile</hi> whom he loves? Sir, ſaid I, I confeſs I am ſtil of that belief, and I would your Majeſty could reſolve to be ſo too.</p>
            <p>O, Unfortunate <hi>Philoxypes</hi> cried the King! (not anſwering me) how ſad is this diſtemper? and how unfortunat am I my ſelf, that I cannot abſolutely cure thee of the Malladie that poſſeſſeth thee. I would then have gone to finde out <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes,</hi> that I might acquaint him with the Kings ſenſe before he ſaw him, but the King would not ſuffer me: but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the way be ſhewn unto him, which <hi>Philoxypes</hi> moſt uſually went, we went di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly towards the head of <hi>Claria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:151701:54"/>
               <hi>Philoxypes</hi> was this mean while gone to <hi>Cleanthes</hi> his houſe, where the face of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs was a little altered; for <hi>Policrita-knowing</hi> that her condition was not what ſhe believed it to be, <hi>Philoxypes</hi> his deſert had made a further advancement in her heart then formerly: neither could ſhe ſo well hide her affection, but that <hi>Cleanthes</hi> and <hi>Megiſto</hi> were much to their grief aware thereof.</p>
            <p>Yet was <hi>Philopyxes</hi> ne're a whit the more happie: for <hi>Policrite</hi> having tane a Fancie to make tryal of his affection by an appearing indifferency, did very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully conceal from him, the affection ſhee had for him.</p>
            <p>And in truth that very day that the King came to <hi>Claria,</hi> where we miſt of <hi>Phyloxypes,</hi> ſhe had cauſed as much trouble in him, as admiration. For being gone to her, and having found her at the root of a a tree, where ſhee was deſigning out a corner of the countrey which pleaſed her, he began to entertain her with his paſſion, and to tell her how it grew ſtill more violent upon him.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid ſhe, if I may be permitted to do ſo, I ſhould tell you, That if you deſire
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:151701:54"/>
to win my good eſteem, you ſhould do better to tell me, that your paſſion grows every day more moderate: for to tell you the truth, I do ſomewhat apprehend theſe extravagant paſſions, which I have heard ſpoken of, and which they ſay, does diſorder reaſon, makes men loſe the reſpect they ow to virtue, though it inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite in a Cottage, and which occaſion a hundred ſtrange things, the very hearing whereof cauſeth horror; Therefore, Sir, if you would oblige me, you will ſatisfie your ſelf with telling me, you have affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction enough for me, to wiſh if it were poſſible that Fortune had been more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious to me, that I had been born of a higher condition then I am, or at leaſt this not being ſo, I might reſt content with my own condition, without envying o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>To love you with indifferencie, ſaid <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> (who acquainted me after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with this their converſation) your beautie ſhould be indifferent, your virtue and diſcretion ſhould be ſo alſo: in fine that inexpreſſable Charm, which <hi>I</hi> finde in every of your words, looks, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, ought not to inchant me as it doth:
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:151701:55"/>
But divine <hi>Policrite,</hi> apprehend nothing from the violence of my paſſion; for the ſtronger it is, the fuller of reſpect ſhall <hi>I</hi> be, and the more obedient to your will.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid She, if what you ſay be true, ſpeak no more thereof <hi>I</hi> beſeech you; for not comprehending that <hi>I</hi> may lawfully give you any part of my affection, mee thinks I ought intreat you to entertain me no longer with yours.</p>
            <p>But Divine <hi>Policrita,</hi> ſaid he, for whom do you reſerve that Glorious affection, which you cruelly affirm I ſhall never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy?</p>
            <p>At theſe words ſhe bluſht, and modeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bowing down her eyes, I reſerve it ſaid ſhe, for our woods, fields, rocks, and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, whereof Sir, ſaid ſhee, ſmilingly, I think you will not be jealous.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not be jealous of them ſaid hee, but I ſhall envy them, and I ſhall not eaſily endure that you ſhould love things to my prejudice, which cannot love you again. But cruel maid, will you ſay nothing to me of more obliging? and forgoing the Court as J do for love of you, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing what ever is in the world, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:151701:55"/>
it be <hi>Policrite;</hi> is it poſſible you ſhould not deal with me a little leſs ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely? J do not deſire you to love me, ſay onely that you are not ſorry that J love you; and add if you pleaſe, that if J be not beloved, tis becauſe you neither do nor will love any thing.</p>
            <p>For what's to come, ſaid <hi>Policrite,</hi> tis a thing to which J ought not to anſwer with ſuch aſſurance; and as you knew not the day before J had the honour to be known unto you, that you ſhould ſo oft for go your Pallaces to come to this Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage wherein I live: how do I know whether the reſolution which I now take of ſuffering no affection to enter my heart, will ſtill continue? No, Sir, wee muſt not truſt ſo abſolutely in our ſelves; nor can I anſwer otherwiſe then for my preſent opinions.</p>
            <p>Shew me then, replied he, what they really are; to the end I may know what to do.</p>
            <p>Sir<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſaid <hi>Policrite,</hi> having much e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem, and much of reſpect for you, I muſt confeſs I ſhould be ſorry that you ſhould love one long, whoſe condition were not anſwerable to yours, and that I
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:151701:56"/>
could not receive a much greater diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> who knew not the hidden ſenſe of theſe words, anſwered, That ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream beautie had in it, ſomewhat of Coeleſtiall, which did ennoble all thoſe that were therewithall indued.</p>
            <p>In my opinion ſaid ſhee, a certain pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion is requiſite in all things to occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on love, therefore do not deceive your ſelf; and if I were at any time to love a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny body, it ſhould certainly be one of my own condition: nor ſhould I ever reſolve to marrie any one that were not ſo.</p>
            <p>What <hi>Policrite!</hi> ſaid <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> much afflicted, do you ſpeak the truth?</p>
            <p>Yes; Sir, ſaid ſhee, and time will make you finde it ſo.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Policrite,</hi> replied he, you remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber not that you are a miracle, and that there are no men of your condition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mid'ſt theſe rocks, who deſerve ſo much as to look upon you.</p>
            <p>I will then love nothing, Sir, ſaid ſhee, and ſo ſhee roſe up, for ſhee ſaw <hi>Clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes</hi> and <hi>Megiſto</hi> coming, who much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at this Prince his ſo frequent viſits, eſpecially, having obſerved what they
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:151701:56"/>
thought they had done in <hi>Policrites</hi> beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, deſired him not to give himſelf the trouble to come ſo often thither.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> who was ſomewhat moved at thoſe cruel words (as he underſtood them) which <hi>Policrite</hi> had uttered which made notwithſtanding ſo much for him, could not with his accuſtomed moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on receive the diſcourſe of <hi>Cleanthes</hi> and <hi>Megiſto,</hi> but anger might eaſilie be ſeen in his face, and grief in his eyes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cleanthes,</hi> ſaid he, ſince I come not hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to rob you of the treaſure which the Gods have given you, withſtand not the ſatisfaction which I finde in admiring that virtue in <hi>Policrite</hi> which you have infuſed into her.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid <hi>Cleanthes,</hi> though I very well know your worth, I cannot but fear leaſt <hi>Policrite</hi> who hath not yet lived long e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to know preciſely what bounds to put to the reſpect ſhe ows you, may be failing in ſomething either to you, or to her ſelf.</p>
            <p>No, no, ſaid <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> ſomewhat roundly, you need not fear what you ſay, you may rather fear leaſt her ſeverity and yours make me loſe my reaſon. In
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:151701:57"/>
fine this converſation, though full of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to <hi>Policrite,</hi> was ſo paſſionate, as <hi>Cleanthes</hi> and <hi>Megiſto</hi> were much troubled at it, and <hi>Policrites</hi> ſelf was ſufficiently diſquieted thereat, and was ſorry that ſhe had ſpoken ſo deſpitefully to <hi>Philoxypes.</hi> But at laſt this Prince departed much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented, and much in love: and as he returned back with intention to get on horſe back where he had wont to leave his followers, he met the King who was lighted on foot, and on whom I had the honour to wait.</p>
            <p>You may imagine how much he was ſurpriſed at this ſight. As ſoon as he ſaw the King, ſtriving as much as he could to hide his Melancholy, he mended his pace, and having done his obeyſance, Sir ſaid he, your Majeſty quits <hi>Paphos</hi> in a ſeaſon wherein you are not much accuſtomed to ſeek out ſolitary walks.</p>
            <p>You have reaſon for what you ſay, ſaid the King, but it ſeems leſs ſtrange to me that I ſhould come to ſeek for <hi>Philoxypes</hi> at <hi>Claria,</hi> then that I ſhould finde him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Rocks. The day being fair e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, though in Winter, the King who could no longer ſtay from acquainting
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:151701:57"/>
               <hi>Philoxpesy</hi> with what he had in his heart, made a ſign to the few atht waited not him to ſtand off, and commanded me to ſtay.</p>
            <p>There remained none then with him but <hi>Phyloxipes</hi> and my ſelf; we all ſtood ſilent for a good while, and certainly had all of us much differing thoughts. The King ſeeing <hi>Philoxypes</hi> ſo altered, ſo me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, and ſo perplex't endevoured to make his friendſhip out go his Love: <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi> would have found by the King's eyes and mind, what the King had to ſay to him, and why he had taken this jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, fearing by the ſignes which I made, leaſt he had diſcovered his paſſion.</p>
            <p>For my particular, I was ready to go wilde, to think I could not advertiſe <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes,</hi> nor durſt not tell the King what I knew of his love, whom he took to be his Rivall; but at laſt this long ſilence where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in every one of us ſaid ſeveral things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſelves, was firſt broke by the King, who looking in a much obliging manner upon this Prince, imbraced him, and ſaid, be not offended that I know the ſecret of your ſoul, and that I am not ignorant of the paſſion which torments you.
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:151701:58"/>
               <hi>Philoxypes</hi> ſurpriſed to hear the King ſpeak thus, looked with a bluſh upon me; and the King imagining (as it was true) that he thought I had betrayed him, looked upon me too: and to puniſh me (as he told me afterwards) for not having told him the truth, not giving me leave to ſpeak, and not diſabuſing <hi>Philoxypes</hi> in what he had conceived of me: once more ſaid he, my dear <hi>Phyloxypes,</hi> be not afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that I have diſcovered your love, and believe I eſteem you never a whit the leſs.</p>
            <p>Sir, replied <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> me thinks if your Majeſtie did know the true cauſe of my affliction, you ſhould be ſo good as to bewail me, and not to ſpeak of it.</p>
            <p>No, <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> replied the King, my goodneſs ſhall extend it ſelf much further then ſo, for you: I am come hither ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly to accompany you in your ſolitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: for ſince I cannot make you happy, I muſt at leaſt make my ſelf unhappy with you.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> you altogether con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found me; take no ſuch reſolution I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, leave me to bear the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my weakneſs alone, and believe
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:151701:58"/>
me I ſhall infinitely praiſe your goodneſs, if you wil ſuffer me to die in peace amidſt theſe woods, and rocks.</p>
            <p>The King touched with extream com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, once more ſtraitly imbraced <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes,</hi> and looking upon him with a very ſad look, I crave your pardon ſaid he <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes,</hi> if I cannot as yet abſolutely yeild <hi>Aretaphile</hi> to you: but I am come hither to endeavour to gain ſay for your ſake the paſſion I have for her, as you have ſtroven a long time for my ſake to ſuppreſs the paſſion which ſhee hath occaſioned in you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philoxypes</hi> ſurpriſed at the Kings diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, felt two contrary agitations at the ſame time: he was grieved to finde his odd opinion, and joyed that he knew not the true cauſe of his love, as he thought he had done. And believing that he might eaſily diſabuſe him in a thing ſo falſe as the former was, he reſolved to continue the concealment of his true paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>The King then had no ſooner ſaid what I have told you, but <hi>Philoxypes</hi> ſtepping back a little, ſaid, what Sir! does your Majeſty ſuſpect me of ſo much boldneſs
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:151701:59"/>
as to be your Rivall? Confeſs, ſaid the King, for I know your misfortune hath been ſuch, as not to be able to reſiſt <hi>Are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphiles</hi> charms. But <hi>Phyloxipes,</hi> I blame you not for it; twas I that firſt made try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all thereof; <hi>I</hi> know how inevitable they are; you have done more then I my ſelf ſhould have done: it may be had I your part to play, <hi>I</hi> ſhould have betrayed my maſter, inſtead of reſolving to die of grief and ſorrow, as you have done for my ſake. Thus <hi>Phyloxypes,</hi> I am not diſpleaſed with you for loving <hi>Aretaphile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid <hi>Phyloxypes,</hi> to witneſs unto you that I am not in love with her, I promiſe you never to ſee her more, nor yet ever to come within <hi>Paphos,</hi> or at leaſt never to ſpeak to that Princeſs.</p>
            <p>I very well know ſaid the King, your Generoſity rather leads you to reſolve on death, rather then to be failing in your duty. But <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> to the end you may not object unto me, That I have done nothing to vanquiſh my ſelf, I am come to ſtay at <hi>Claria,</hi> as well as you, that I may endeavor to cure my ſelf of this paſſion, and to yeild up <hi>Aretaphile</hi> to you. You on your ſide ſhall do the like, and he
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:151701:59"/>
that is firſt cured, ſhall ſurrender his part in her to the other.</p>
            <p>But my dear <hi>Phyloxypes,</hi> ſaid he, you are yet more unhappy then you think for, for when I ſhould ceaſe to love <hi>Aretaphile,</hi> you would not have wonn her heart: you know how ambitious ſhe is, that her ſoul is onely ſenſible of greatneſs: and when I ſhould have yeilded up my miſtreſs to you, unleſs I ſhould alſo yeild my Crown unto you, you would not winne much upon her inclination.</p>
            <p>But in fine ſaid he (not affording <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi> leaſure to anſwer him) if I yeild up <hi>Aretaphile</hi> to you, it will not be hard for me to yeild you up my Crown. And in a word, I will not be upbraided with your death.</p>
            <p>I will do what I can to cure my ſelf, to the end that you may cure your ſelf; and if we can neither of us cure our ſelves, we will at leaſt die together.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> I vow by whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I hold moſt ſacred, and moſt holy, that I have not the leaſt pretence to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs <hi>Aretaphile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What then ſaid the King, who did not believe him, is the cauſe of your retreat
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:151701:60"/>
and Melancholly? I confeſs Sir, <hi>I</hi> was a hundred, and a hundred times ready to break my word which I had paſt to <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes;</hi> but ſeeing the trouble he was in, end that in fine he could not reſolve to all the King the truth, I with held whilſt <hi>Phyloxypes</hi> anſwered, That what his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie did command, did not deſerve his curioſitie, and that he could not tell it him.</p>
            <p>Being by this time late, we returned to <hi>Claria,</hi> where the King ſpoke ſtill after the ſame manner to <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> as <hi>Philoxy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes</hi> did alſo to him. Having found a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of time to entertain <hi>Philoxypes</hi> alone, I would have perſwaded him to have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted the King with the truth; but he could never reſolve to do ſo, ſaying it would be ſufficient to let him ſee he was not in love with <hi>Aretaphile,</hi> if he ſhould never ſee her more.</p>
            <p>This mean while, the more obſtinacie, and grief the King found in <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> the more did he compaſſionate him, and the more he laboured to overcome his own paſſion.</p>
            <p>And to this purpoſe he ſtayed eight daies at <hi>Claria,</hi> all which time <hi>Philoxypes</hi>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:151701:60"/>
readie to go mad, as well in conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Kings opinion, and more for that he could not get to ſee <hi>Polycryte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not think the King would ſo ſoon have left this retiredneſs, had he not been advertiſed that an Ambaſſador from <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> was come to <hi>Paphos,</hi> which forc't him to return. But <hi>Philoxy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes,</hi> do he what he could, muſt needs go along with him: No ſaid the King, <hi>I</hi> will not ſee <hi>Aretaphile,</hi> without ſeeing you at the ſame time. The Melancholy which I ſhall ſee in your eyes, muſt be to me an antidote againſt the Charms which I ſhall ſee in hers.</p>
            <p>We went then to <hi>Paphos,</hi> but good gods how little delightfull was the Court then, and how much troubled did the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor finde the King, who was three daies without ſeeing <hi>Aretaphile,</hi> and <hi>Philoxypes</hi> being in unimaginable pain for the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid reaſons, ſeemed to grow ſtill more melancholy, whereat the King was ſtill more and more afflicted.</p>
            <p>Ambitious <hi>Aretaphile</hi> was this mean while not without her perplexity, as well by reaſon of the Kings journey to <hi>Claria,</hi> as that he came not to viſite her; and for
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:151701:61"/>
that ſhee heard he was returned wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſad.</p>
            <p>But at laſt the King deſirous ſtil to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm himſelf in his belief, brought <hi>Philoxy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes</hi> with him to Princeſs <hi>Aretaphile,</hi> hoping to diſcover his paſſion better there, then in any other place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> who thought there was no better means to undeceive the King, then in leting him ſee that he took no pleaſure in looking upon this Princeſs, was ſtil care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to look another way; but that which he did to dis-deceive the King, did the more deceive him: for ſaid he to himſelf, unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate <hi>Philoxypes</hi> cannot indure the ſight of her whom he loves, and whom he will not love.</p>
            <p>He accuſed himſelf then of too much inhumanity, in expoſing him to ſo great a puniſhment, and ſeeing how ſtrangely perplext he was, his viſit was not long.</p>
            <p>This mean while, he having during this viſit eyed his pretended Rivall, as much as his miſtreſs, and having been much diſquiet, the Princeſs was not much ſatisfied with his converſation, and knew not whereunto to attribute the cauſe of the change which ſhe ſaw in him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:151701:61"/>
At his coming forth he ſaid a thouſand obliging things to <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> and <hi>Philoxy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes</hi> made as many proteſtations to him of his being unconcerned in <hi>Aretaphile.</hi> But at laſt, that <hi>I</hi> may ſhorten my diſcourſe as much as I may; <hi>Philoxypes</hi> being perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Kings conceit, anger'd at <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anthes</hi> diſcourſe, much afflicted at what <hi>Policryte</hi> had ſaid, and much more that he could ſee her no more, and that he durſt not return to <hi>Claria,</hi> fell dangerouſly ſick, all the Phyſitions gave up their opinions, that unleſs ſome cure were found for his Melancholy, he would infaliblie die. The feaver continued ſeven daies upon him very violently, during which time the King was greatly diſconſolate; and during which time I had tane a little jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to <hi>Amathuſe,</hi> about ſome buſineſs that I had there, for I think if <hi>I</hi> had been at <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phos,</hi> I ſhould have had much adoe to have kept <hi>Philoxypes</hi> his ſecret from the King.</p>
            <p>As oft as the King came into his cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and ſaw him in that pitifull conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he reſolved to think no longer on <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retaphile,</hi> but as ſoon as he came from him, or that <hi>Philoxypes</hi> grew any thing better, this reſolution ſlackned a little.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:151701:62"/>
Nor was he yet reſolved what to do, but the feavor having at laſt left <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> and the Phyſitians continuing ſtill to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that he would infallibly die, if the cauſe of his Melancholy whence his mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy proceeded were not taken away: the King ſeemed to have put on a very ſtrong reſolution to pluck from out his ſoul the paſſion which poſſeſt him.</p>
            <p>He then reſolved to viſite <hi>Aretaphile</hi> no more, who not knowing what to think of this change in the King, thought it might be he was offended that ſhee had not all this while been to ſee <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> whom he ſo dearly loved, eſpecially ſince almoſt all the Ladies of the Court had been to viſit him. For during his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Princeſs of <hi>Salamis,</hi> and Princeſs <hi>Agariſta</hi> had never left him, ſo as the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies might with decency enough go thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>Yet ſo it happened, that the day that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retaphile</hi> came thither, <hi>Philoxypes</hi> being much better then he was, they were gone forth, ſo as <hi>Aretaphile</hi> going accompanied with four or five of her women, found him all alone. Tis true ſhee was not there long without company, for the King came
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:151701:62"/>
thither preſently after. <hi>Philoxypes</hi> bluſht when he ſaw him come in, and ſeemed ſo amazed at this encounter, as if he had been really in love with <hi>Aretaphile;</hi> the King who obſerved this his change of countenance, being much concernd to ſee that he ſhould be the cauſe of <hi>Philoxypes</hi> danger: after a great ſtrife within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, drew near to Princeſs <hi>Aretaphile,</hi> who out of her reſpect would have given him her place, which he would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of: and after having looked upon her a while without ſpeaking, he ſigh't, and ſaid, Madam, will you not cure <hi>Philoxypes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid ſhe, if his health depend on me, your Majeſty ſhould ſoon be eaſed of the grief his ſickneſs cauſeth in you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> who found a great alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Kings countenance, was afeard leaſt he might ſay ſomewhat which might have made <hi>Aretaphile</hi> know his opinion of him; wherefore not affording the King leaſure to reply,</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid he, though <hi>I</hi> believe Princeſs <hi>Aretaphile</hi> be able to do great things, and to charm great pains, yet <hi>I</hi> think I may ſay without offending her, that thoſe evills
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:151701:63"/>
which I lie under, depend not on hers wil; &amp; that none but the Gods them ſelve can withdraw me from the grave. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi> pronounced theſe words in ſo ſad a manner, as endeavouring to overcome whatſoever oppoſed his deſign of ſaving <hi>Phyloxypes:</hi> drawing yet a little nearer to the Princeſs <hi>Aretaphile,</hi> for fear leaſt they that were in the chamber might over hear him.</p>
            <p>Madam, ſaid he, (making a ſign to <hi>Phyloxypes</hi> that he would not be interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) I ſhall tell you a thing which will much ſurpriſe you. <hi>I</hi> conjure you not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding to give it a favourable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation; and to oblige me ſo far as to believe that upon better tearms then the ſaving of <hi>Philoxypes</hi> life, <hi>I</hi> would not tell it you, no not though mine own life were concerned therein.</p>
            <p>Oh! Sir, cried out this ſick Prince, if your Majeſty end what you have begun to ſay, you will haſten my death inſtead of retarding it.</p>
            <p>Princeſs <hi>Aretaphile,</hi> amazed to hear what ſhe heard, and not able to gueſs what the matter ſhould be, looked ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times upon the King, ſometimes upon
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:151701:63"/>
               <hi>Philoxypes;</hi> but at laſt the king compleating his determination, tis you, Madam, ſaid he, to the Princeſs <hi>Aretaphile,</hi> who ſend <hi>Philoxypes</hi> to his grave; your charms have been more powerfull then his reaſon, though his nobleneſs hath been yet grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then his love. He loves you divine <hi>Aretaphile,</hi> not daring to tell you ſo; Hee will not ſo much as acknowledg it, yet I know for certain, that unleſs you take compaſſion on him, he will infallibly die.</p>
            <p>I therefore ſpeak no more to you in my own behalf, ſaid he, in a ſtrange Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly manner, but deal leſs rigorouſly with him, then you have done with me, ſince he deſerves it better: and if your Ambition be not to be ſatisfied without a Sovereign power, I promiſe you divine Princeſs, that if I cannot place <hi>Philoxypes</hi> upon the Throne, he ſhall alwaies be ſo near it, as his place ſhall hardly be diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able from mine.</p>
            <p>In fine ſaid he, if <hi>Philoxypes</hi> die, I ſhall die, and ſo <hi>I</hi> ſhall for ever loſe you: but if you ſave <hi>Philoxypes, I</hi> may at leaſt hope to languiſh on a while, and to ſhare part of your eſteem, not being able to pretend
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:151701:64"/>
any longer to any part of your affection. Nor think not ſaid he, That this which I do, is any mark of weakneſs in my affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſince on the contrary it denotes the violence thereof.</p>
            <p>For in fine, if I could reſolve to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don you, and to follow <hi>Philoxypes</hi> to the grave, <hi>I</hi> would not yeild up to him the part <hi>I</hi> pretend to have in your affection, though he be more worthy thereof then <hi>I;</hi> but not being able to ſee him die for my ſake, without expiring with grief, I muſt live, that he may live, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently muſt endeavour for a while to prolong the ſatisfaction I take in ſeeing you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aretaphile</hi> was ſo aſtoniſht to hear the King ſpeak after this manner, and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi> ſo afflicted, as aſtoniſhment and ſorrow producing the ſame effect in theſe two perſonages, they ſtaid a good while without ſpeaking.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aretaphile</hi> had opinion good enough of her beauty, to ſuffer her ſelfe eaſily to be perſwaded that <hi>Philoxypes</hi> was in love with her, and ſhe had likewiſe opinion good enough of his Generoſitie, to believ he durſt not diſcover his paſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:151701:64"/>
But as nothing that was not King could touch her heart, ſhe was ſtrangely per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plext to hear what ſhe heard, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſhe thought t'was peradventure but a pretext ſought by the King to break with her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philoxipes</hi> on his ſide thinking that at the laſt he muſt be fain to tell the King the truth, that he might diſabuſe him, was ſo ſtrangely confuſed, as he could not open his mouth: ſo as the King ſeeing them both ſo ſurprized, and finding that peradventure his love might quickly make him unſay all that his friendſhip had made him affirm, roſe up, and without expecting what <hi>Aretaphile</hi> would anſwer. Madam, ſaid he, the pittifull condition which you ſee <hi>Philoxypes</hi> is in, perſwades you better then <hi>I</hi> can do, and he doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly will pardon me, if I ſpeak not ſo long to you for him as I have formerly done to you for my ſelf: which ſaid, he went his way, though <hi>Philoxypes</hi> deſired him to tarry; aſſuring him that he would wholly diſabuſe him.</p>
            <p>This mean while, though <hi>Aretaphile</hi> had a great minde to be gone too, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing imbitterd in minde, and deſirous to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:151701:65"/>
know a little more preciſely, what the buſineſs of this ſo ſtrange adventure would prove, ſhee ſtaid a little after the King, and looking upon <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> who appeared to her to be ſo ſtruck mute, as if he had been in love with her: is it you <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> ſaid ſhee, that have loſt your reaſon, or is it the King? for <hi>I</hi> confeſs unto you I know not whether of the two it is, and that I cannot comprehend either of you.</p>
            <p>I confeſs Madam, ſaid <hi>Phyloxipes,</hi> that I am not maſter of my reaſon, but Madam, tis a maladie which you are no waies cauſe of, and whereof I accuſe you not: had you any deſign then ſaid ſhe, to make me loſe the Kings good opinion? or is it that the King ſeeks ſome bad pretext to bereave me of it? But if it be ſo <hi>Philoxy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes,</hi> there needs not ſo far a fetch about the buſh. You need but give me reaſon of the leaſt ſuſpition, and I aſſure you <hi>I</hi> ſhall not long lament the loſs of ſo divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a heart as his is. For til now the King did alwaies love his Crown better then Princeſs <hi>Aretaphile,</hi> and by his this daies diſcourſe, he will make me believe that he loves you better then me.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:151701:65"/>
Madam, ſaid <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> I beg it as a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour from you, not to blame the King up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo ſmall reaſon; and not to blame in him the compaſſion he is pleaſed to have of an evill, which he believes you to be the cauſe of.</p>
            <p>engage my ſelf Madam, to free him from the error of his opinion; for though your charms be without compare, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect which I have alwaies born to you, and that which <hi>I</hi> ſhall alwaies bear to the King, have aſſuredly warranted me from almoſt an inevitable danger, for thoſe who have not had ſo powerfull reaſons to withſtand your beauty: therefore Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, do not diſquiet your ſelf, and do me the honour as to promiſe me to pardon the Kings injuſtice, in deſiring that <hi>I</hi> ſhould ſhare with you in a heart where you ought onely to reign.</p>
            <p>But Madam, the King had given me the place which I now enjoy, before he loved you; you ought not therefore be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled thereat.</p>
            <p>No, no, replied ambitious <hi>Aretephile,</hi> you will not eaſily be able to juſtifie the King: he is Generous, I confeſs, but he is but a bad lover, and whoſoever can yeild
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:151701:66"/>
up his intereſt in the party beloved, his love is certainly very indifferent.</p>
            <p>This being ſaid ſhee bid him farewell, and left <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> ſo much grieved, as his maladie encreaſed. Fearing then leaſt he might die, and leave the King in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion he was in, he ſent to deſire him that he might ſpeak with him; and this was juſt as I returned from <hi>Amethuſa.</hi> I happened to be by the King when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived this meſſage, who inſtantly went to <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> but with ſo much diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, as I pitied him: he had repented himſelf more then once of what he had ſaid to <hi>Aretaphile,</hi> and not knowing whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe might not have ſaid ſomewhat of obliging to <hi>Philoxypes</hi> after he had left them together, he returned unto him much diſquieted.</p>
            <p>When we came thither, he enquired whether the Princeſs <hi>Aretaphile</hi> had tarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there long after him or not, and being told not, he entered into <hi>Philoxypes</hi> cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, who was glad to ſee me with the King.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid he, I ſee it is time that I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs my weakneſs to you, and that I diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe you.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:151701:66"/>
The King, who could not reconcile theſe two things, anſwered him onely with a ſigh, and being ſet down by his bed ſide, <hi>Philoxypes</hi> ask'd him pardon for the trouble he had put his Majeſty to, and deſired me to acquaint the King with what I knew of his adventure; deſiring him not to be offended that I had not told his Majeſty the truth, ſince unleſs I ſhould have drawn down the anger of Heaven upon me for perjury, I could not have revealed his ſecret, after the Oaths that he had made me take to the contrary I then began to acquaint the King with all that I knew touching <hi>Philoxypes</hi> love: but all I could ſay to him, appear'd to bee ſo incredible, as it was a long time before he could beleeve it. At laſt he told <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes,</hi> that unleſſe he ſhould let him ſee <hi>Policrite,</hi> he would not beleeve what hee had heard.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philoxypes</hi> perceiving the Kings obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacie, told him, that though he was very ill, he would be carried to <hi>Claria,</hi> in caſe he were any thing better the next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, imagining he ſhould ſooner recover his health being near <hi>Policrite,</hi> then if he ſhould ſtay at <hi>Paphos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:151701:67"/>
All this while the King did not believe what I had told him; ſometime a man might ſee ſome ſign of rejoycing in him: ha! my dear <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> would he ſay, is it poſſible that you were not my Rival, and that I was deceived: if it be ſo, I think I ſhall adore that <hi>Policrite</hi> you ſpeak of, inſtead of blaming the love you bear her; ſince thereby I ſhall not be inforced to yeild up what I hold dearer then my life, and that my confident will not prove my rival.</p>
            <p>But obſerve ſir, the extraordinary ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of love. <hi>Philoxypes</hi> was very ſick when he ſent to deſire the King to come unto him: but when once he had any thought of returning to <hi>Claria,</hi> hee grew better: hee ſlept all the next night qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly enough, and the next day was carried in a Litter to <hi>Claria,</hi> whither the King went to lie that night.</p>
            <p>The next day <hi>Philoxipes</hi> left his bed, and the following day, notwithſtanding all his weakneſs, he got on horſeback together with the King, waited on but by very few: and came to the foot of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains where they were to light. Being there, the King followed by none but <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:151701:67"/>
and my ſelf, went towards <hi>Clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the</hi>'s Cottage, which as ſoon as we diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> who had need enough howſoever to reſt, ſtaid a while, and ſhewing it to the King, Sir, ſaid hee, ſtrangely confuſed, ſee the place which made me forgo <hi>Paphos:</hi> ſee the inch of all the earth, that likes me beſt, and where you go to ſee one, who peradventure will rather make you <hi>Philoxypes</hi> his Rival, then <hi>Philoxipes</hi> ſhall prove yours.</p>
            <p>He ſpoke this with a ſmile, by which it viſibly appeard, that the hope of reſeeing <hi>Policrite</hi> had brought joy into his heart: yet did he fear diſpleaſing her, and to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger <hi>Cleanthes,</hi> by bringing the King thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but there being no remedy, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to do it, neither did this fear juſtle out his joy.</p>
            <p>When the King had ſufficiently conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the greatneſs of Philoxypes his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, in reſpect of the meanneſs of <hi>Policrites</hi> Cottage; and that he had not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding acknowledged that there was ſomewhat of wilde in that deſert, which was not diſpleaſing: we went on, and came at laſt to that little Paliſadoe of of Lawrels, wherewith <hi>Cleanthes</hi> his
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:151701:68"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:151701:68"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:151701:69"/>
Court was incloſed. We entered there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into, and <hi>Philoxypes</hi> ſtepping before the king, went to the houſe, where he found the dore ſhut: he knock'd, but no body anſwered, which made him at firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that <hi>Cleanthes</hi> his whole family was gone to the Temple, where hee once ſaw <hi>Policrite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet ſince there might be ſome body there who might not hear, he knock'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and knock'd ſo hard, that a young ſlave who ſerved <hi>Cleanthes,</hi> came and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened the door, who very well knowing <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> told him, after that <hi>Philoxypes</hi> had ask'd him where his maſter was, that he could not tell him what he deſired to know; and that all that he knew was, that <hi>Cleanthes, Megiſto, Polycrite,</hi> and <hi>Dori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> were gone from thence, and were not to return thither any more: that they had carried along with them the women, which they had brought from their own Countrey; and that his Maſter had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded him to wait his further directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons there, not knowing wherefore he was gone, nor why he left him there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> ſurpriz'd and afflicted at this Diſcourſe, was a good while without
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:151701:69"/>
ſpeaking; The King thought at firſt that there was ſome trick in it, and that <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi> had made me ſay what I had ſaid, only to abuſe him; but at laſt this young Slave being ſtept into the Houſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning preſently; Sir, ſaid he to <hi>Philoxy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes,</hi> when <hi>Policrite</hi> was ready to depart from hence, ſhe drew me aſide, unſeen by any one, and gave me this which I give to you, ordaining me ſo to doe if you ſhould come hither. <hi>Philoxypes</hi> taking immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately what the Slave preſented him with, opened the Letter, whilſt the King did me the honour to ſpeak with me, and read theſe enſuing words:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Policrite <hi>to</hi> Philoxypes.</head>
                  <p>I Know not Sir, whither it is that<hi>Policrite</hi> is convey'd, but I very well know that <hi>Philoxypes</hi> is the cauſe of her exile: not being perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, likely ever to have the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to ſee him. I thought I might
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:151701:70"/>
without blame, let him know my minde by this Letter, which <hi>I</hi> refuſed to acquaint him withall, the laſt time which I ſpoke with him. He may then be pleaſed to know, that at firſt not eſteeming my ſelf worthy of his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, by reaſon of my birth, I with-held mine from him as much as I was able; but that having learnt ſince, that I am not of the condition I appeared to be, and that there have been Kings of my Race: I confeſs I was gladded that I could not reproach <hi>Philoxipes</hi> for having an inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on too diſproportionable for his degree: and that I thought it became me to let him know what I am, to the end he may not think he doth any thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of himſelf, if he ſometimes think upon <hi>Policrite,</hi> who wil alwais with much contentment think upon his
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:151701:70"/>
worth, whether his fortune be to lead his life in a Cottage or in a Palace.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>POLYCRITE.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>PHILOXYPES, as ſoon as he had read this Letter, came to the King, and preſenting it unto him; Sir, ſaid he, your Majeſty may read in this Letter my inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, and my misfortune. The King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan then to read aloud what <hi>Policrite</hi> had written; but good God in what pain was the unfortunate <hi>Philoxypes</hi> that he could not interrupt him; but as ſoon as he had read it out, looking upon him with a fixt and grieved eye; how ſay you now? Sir, ſaid he, am I yet in love with Princeſs <hi>Aretaphile,</hi> or am I not the moſt unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate man in the world? the King, imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing him, asked him pardon for his ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and of the trouble he had given him; but my dear <hi>Philoxypes</hi> ſaid he, I ſhall be ſufficiently puniſhed for it, as well in reſpect of your ſorrow, which ſhal al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies be mine; as for <hi>Aretaphile,</hi> who will not eaſily forgive me, yet ſaid he, you
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:151701:71"/>
have wherein to rejoyce, ſince you learn two things at once of great importance, and of great conſolation. For now you know that <hi>Policrite</hi> loves you, and that ſhe is of Princely deſcent: Could you have asked more of the Gods, if you had been to have had your wiſhes granted you?</p>
            <p>Ah! Sir, ſaid <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> that which you alleadge to comfort me, is the greateſt part of my misfortune: For tis true, I finde that <hi>Policryte</hi> does not hate me, and that ſhee is of birth equall with my ſelf, but at the ſame time this lovely and cruel perſonage tells me, ſhee ſhall never ſee me more, and that ſhee knows not whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhee is carried.</p>
            <p>Oh! Sir, I ſhould be more to blame were I in love with Princeſs <hi>Aretaphile,</hi> but I ſhould be leſs miſerable: I ſhould have reaſons to gainſay my paſſion; but here I ſee nothing which doth not forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and augment it.</p>
            <p>In fine after <hi>Phyloxypes</hi> had ſufficiently bemoned himſelf, he left the King, and went to ask a hundred things of the young ſlave, without being able to learn any thing, either of <hi>Policrites</hi> birth, nor
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:151701:71"/>
whither <hi>Cleanthes</hi> &amp; <hi>Megiſto</hi> were gone; all he could learn was only that twas above a fortnight ſince they were gon: nothing elſ could be gotten out of this young Slave, neither by prayers, promiſes, nor threats, whoſe fidelitie <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> for all his rage, could not chuſe but approve of: but not being able to learn any more, he waited back upon the King to <hi>Claria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For my part <hi>I</hi> was never more at my wits end; for the king was ſo ſad, as well for his own occaſion, as for thoſe of PHI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LOXIPES, as he could not reſolve to ſay any thing, neither by way of bemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning himſelf, nor yet of comforting PHILOXIPES, whom he ſo dearly lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <p>PHILOXYPES on his part was more perplex'd: he was ſorry to forgo that Cottage though his beloved was no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger there; he ſometimes looked back up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, ſometimes he looked upon <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites</hi> Letter, which the king had given him back.</p>
            <p>He would ſomtimes lift up his eies to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, then again fix them on the earth, and walking ſometimes without ſpeaking, ſometimes fetching deep ſighs, he ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:151701:72"/>
not to know whether the king were there or no, or whether he were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, ſo deep was his melancholy. At laſt we came to <hi>Glaria,</hi> but good Gods how ſad was the converſation the reſt of that day.</p>
            <p>At laſt ſaid the king to <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> you have this advantage, to know that <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryte</hi> is much obliged to you, that ſhe hath nothing to reproach you withall, that you have not offended her, and that whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhe is, if ſhe think of you, tis onely to bewail your abſence: where on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, I have incen'ſt <hi>Aretaohile,</hi> whoſe aſpiring ſoul does doubtleſly accuſe me of want of affection, and who will take it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ill, that I preferd your life before my love to her.</p>
            <p>But Sir, ſaid the afflicted <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> you know where the Princeſs <hi>Aratephile</hi> is, you may make your reaſons known to her, you may ask her pardon for that fault, which an exceſs of Generoſity made you commit: you may ſit and ſigh by her, and may appeaſe her anger. But for my part Sir, ſhould I complain, ſhould I ſigh, ſhould <hi>I</hi> pour forth torrents of tears a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt theſe Rocks, would all this reſtore
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:151701:72"/>
to me my <hi>Policryte?</hi> ſhould I thereby learn where ſhee lives? It may be <hi>Clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes</hi> is put to ſea, and it may be I ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver know, neither who <hi>Policryte</hi> is, nor where ſhee is.</p>
            <p>Ah! Sir, ſaid this diſconſolate Prince, if you knew the cruelty of my adventure, you would eaſily know that I am the moſt unfortunate man in the world: for if I loved one that did hate me, deſpight might cure me: if <hi>I</hi> loved one that were inconſtant, the ſcorn I ſhould have of her weakneſs, might conſolate me: if <hi>I</hi> were jealous, a part of my melancholy would paſs away in ſeeking how I might preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice my Rivals: were <hi>Policrytes</hi> abſence bounded, the hope of her return, how long ſo e're it were, would allay my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents Nay, vvere any perſon vvhom I ſhould love, dead, I think my ſufferings vvould not be ſo great as they are. For in fine, my mallady is ſuch, as doth ſtupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie reaſon, and makes the ſoul almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible.</p>
            <p>In this manner did the king and PHI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LOXYPES entertain themſelves. I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to comfort them both, but to tell you truth, my reaſons vvere not liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:151701:73"/>
unto; as for <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> he knew not what remedy to ſeek for; for having learn'd by the ſlave who gave him <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite</hi>'s letter, that twas a good while ſince ſhee went away, he could not dream of following her, nor knew he where to ſeek after her.</p>
            <p>All he could do, was to give order to his people to watch night and day about the Cottage, with directions to ſtay any who ſhould come thither, that they might learn by them what this too faithfull Slave would not diſcover; and to follow him wherſoever he ſhould go, believing probably that <hi>Cleanthes</hi> had not left him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone in that houſe, without ſome ſecret reaſon, and without having a deſign to return; or at leaſt to ſend ſomebody thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on his behalf, or that the Slave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſhould return to him.</p>
            <p>As for the King it fared not thus with him: he knew that it was at <hi>Aretephiles</hi> feet that he was to ſeek for pardon: he would not, notwithſtanding make his dear <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi> returne ſo ſoon to <hi>Paphos,</hi> but ſtaid the next day at <hi>Claria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though there was no hope of find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Policrite, Philoxypes</hi> deſired the King
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:151701:73"/>
that he would be pleaſed to ſend to all the ports of the Iſland, to know whether <hi>Cleanthes</hi> had tane ſhipping in any of them or no, it being eaſie to be known, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the many women that were in his company, which would make him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable. The King promiſed him to do what he deſired, but conjured him alſo not to refuſe to go with him to <hi>Paphos,</hi> to aſſiſt him in getting <hi>Aretaphiles</hi> pardon. <hi>Philoxypes</hi> appeared viſibly diſpleaſed to be forced to return to the Court, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo much obliged to the King, and the king being upon ill tearms with his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, onely out of his Love to him, he thought it became him to go, as he did. When we were come to <hi>Paphos,</hi> the King went that very night to Princeſs <hi>Areta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philes</hi> lodgings, and found her onely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with her women. She recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him with all the civility that was due to his condition, but alſo with as much coolneſs as could be expected from an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed party.</p>
            <p>Seeing <hi>Philoxypes</hi> with the king, Sir, ſaid ſhee, with a malicious ſmile, did not I tell you <hi>Philoxypes</hi> would recover with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my medling with him. Madam, ſaid
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:151701:74"/>
he, <hi>Philoxypes</hi> is much worſe then I belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him to be; but thanks to Heaven, I will not lay his death to your charge, ſince you are not the cauſe of his diſquiet. May it pleaſe the Gods that you put not <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi> in a condition of reproaching you with my death!</p>
            <p>No, no, Sir, ſaid ſhee, your life is in no danger, as long as <hi>Philoxypes</hi> lives, your Majeſty needs fear nothing. Alas Madam, cry'd the king, deal not ſo hardly with me! Alas, Sir, ſaid ſhee, go not about I beſeech you to perſwade me to things ſo directly oppoſite one to another, in ſo ſhort a time; it is not above four or five days ſince you did me the honour to tell me at <hi>Philoxypes</hi> his lodging, that you would no more ſue to me for your ſelf; that my affection was a thing wherein you did no longer deſire a part; and if I remember well, you did alſo intreat me not to deal ſo rigourouſly with <hi>Philoxy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes,</hi> as <hi>I</hi> had done with you. And it may be, ſaid ſhee, (expreſſing an extremity of Malice) that yeelding much to your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treaties upon that occaſion, I ſhould have granted what you have demanded for <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> had my friendſhip been neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:151701:74"/>
to ſafe his life; but ſince God be thanked, he needs it not, he may be pleaſed to content himſelfe with my e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem; and your Majeſty may likewiſe be ſatisfied with my reſpect, which is all I can, or ought to give you. For in fine to make me believe that you love me, after being able to permit that another ſhould love me, and you your ſelfe wiſh me to love him, is a thing not eaſie to be underſtood, nor yet eaſily disjeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: beleive me, Sir, ſaid ſhee, to love ones rival, better then ones Miſtreſſe, is a thing whereof there are not many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, and which may allow me to let thoſe know, who ſhall be acquainted with the buſineſs, that tis an excellent way to make a faithful ſervant, &amp; a very bad invention to make a Princeſs love him, who treats her after that maner. Shal the compaſſion <hi>I</hi> had of <hi>Philoxipes,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, replyd the king, deſtroy me for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in your good opinion? me, I ſay, who underwent an unexpreſſable tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, before I could reſolve to pitty him? me, who did not yeild you up, ſave onely becauſe <hi>I</hi> could not abandon you, and who found that PHILOXYPE'S
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:151701:75"/>
death did haſten mine? If you could have loved <hi>Aretaphile,</hi> anſwerd the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, more then Philoxypes, you would have lamented his misfortune and yours; you would have endeavoured to have cu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red him by abſence, or by a thouſand otherwaies; you would have bewaild his death when it ſhould have happened, and would yet have been comforted, by the ſole ſight of <hi>Aretaphile:</hi> but becauſe you love PHILOXYPES better then you love <hi>Aretapile,</hi> you reſolve without much difficulty to loſe her. Yet Sir, you could yeild up to PHILOXYPES no more then that part which you held in her, which was not peradventure ſo great as you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</p>
            <p>Ah! inhumane princeſſe ſaid the king, make me not diſpair, and know that when I made a ſurrender of you to <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes, I</hi> was reſolved to die. It may be Sir, ſaid ſhee, If I had ſo much weakneſſs as to lend a favourable ear to what you now ſay, that upon the firſt occaſion that ſhould preſent it ſelf,; and upon the firſt ſuſpicion you ſhould have that any one ſhould bear me never ſo little good will, you would again conjure me to be
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:151701:75"/>
his cure. No, no, Sir, ſaid ſhee, with a yet more ſerious face, you never lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved me, nor do you know what it is to love: Love is ſomewhat above reaſon, or generoſity, which hath reaſons of its own: a man may give his own life for his friend, but as for the Miſtreſs whom he loveth, it would be more juſt, and more uſuall, to quit all his friends for her intereſt, then to yeild her up to any one friend. In fine ſaid ſhee, you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance have thought you could have li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved without me; for had you dream't you muſt have dyed, me thinks you might as well have dyed without yeilding up <hi>Aretaphile</hi> to <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> as after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſurrendered her to him. But Sir, ſince you have rather choſen to ſpecifie an extraordinary mark of Generoſity, then to give the commoneſt proofe of love, I have no more to ſay; neither have I more to do, but to preſerve my heart as free as it hath allwaies been. The king ſeeing he could not appeaſe this haughty ſpirit, call'd <hi>Philoxypes</hi> in into his aid; come ſaid he, come make amends for the fault which you have innocently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; and if you will preſerve my life,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:151701:76"/>
as I would have done yours, be a mean of replacing me in the condition wherein I was before I had compaſſion of you. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, ſaid <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> addreſſing his ſpeech to the Princeſs, if you judge of the Kings love to you, by his Friendſhip to me, what may you not expect from thence; ſince to ſave my life, he could for ſome few moments onely renounce the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſo ineſtimable a jewel. And will you not then believe, That upon the leaſt occaſion which ſhould preſent it ſelf, he would for your ſervice ſacrifice, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> but even all his ſubjects, nay, even his own life? No Sir, ſaid ſhe, you are not ſo much bound to the King, as you imagine, and inſtead of your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring me to judge of his love to me, by the friendſhip he bears to you, I ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe you to judge of his friendſhip to you, onely by his love to me; and to believe, that ſince he was able to yeild me up, he never had ſo reſolute a paſſion for <hi>Are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphile,</hi> as to deſerve that <hi>Philoxypes</hi> ſhould be much beholden to him, for what hee hath done for him, ſince he would have done the like for any other. But cruell princeſs, ſaid the King, what will you
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:151701:76"/>
have me to do? me thinks ſaid ſhe, <hi>I</hi> ſhould demand no unjuſt thing of you, if <hi>I</hi> ſhould humbly intreat you to think no longer on <hi>Aretaphile,</hi> and quietly to enjoy the life of <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> which hath coſt you ſo little.</p>
            <p>Ah, ſaid he, if I ſhould have purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the life of <hi>Philoxipes,</hi> at the loſſe of your affection, I ſhould have bought it more deare, then if I ſhould have given my Crown for it. Confeſs the truth, ſaid this malicious Princeſs, if <hi>Philoxypes</hi> had been as ſick of Ambition, as you did think him love ſick, he would not for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain be yet cured, and you would not ſo ſoon have forgon your Scepter, as you did <hi>Aretaphile. Phyloxipes,</hi> who eaſilie conceived the hidden ſenſe of theſe words, whereunto the King replyed not, ſo was he over born with grief, ſaid, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, if the King ſhall confeſs unto you that he hath done amiſs, and ſhall ask your pardon for it, will you be more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exorable, then are the Gods, and will you ſhew no mercy? when the King ſaid ſhee, ſhall have done to cure me of any malady of minde, if any ſuch ſhall befall me, ſo extraordinary a thing, as that
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:151701:77"/>
which he hath done for you, <hi>I</hi> ſhall then ſee of what minde I ſhall be. In fine, Sir, All that the King and <hi>Philoxypes</hi> could do or ſay, did no waies avail with this impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Princeſs.</p>
            <p>When they were come from her, and were returned to the Palace; <hi>Philoxypes</hi> who was well acquainted with <hi>Aretaphiles</hi> humour, told the King, he knew a way how to work his reconcilement with her: Alas, ſaid the King, there are few things I would not do to purchaſe that content: ſpeak therefore, my dear <hi>Phyloxypes:</hi> muſt I be long in pain? muſt I ſigh abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and pour forth abundance of tears? and muſt I be everlaſtingly proſtrate at her feet? No Sir, ſaid he, you ſhall onely put the Crown upon her head. But re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the King, I would gladly not have owed <hi>Aretephiles</hi> love to her Ambition; on the contrarie, I would have had the Crown of <hi>Cyprus</hi> to have been a reward of her affection to me.</p>
            <p>Five or ſix daies being thus paſt over, and <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> not being able to tarry any longer at the Court, he deſired leave of the King to return to CLARIA. Thoſe who the King had ſent to the Port towns
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:151701:77"/>
vvhich vvere neereſt to <hi>Paphos,</hi> returned at the ſame time, but brought no news of <hi>Policrite;</hi> ſo as the unfortunate <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xypes</hi> returned to his ſolitarineſs in great deſpair.</p>
            <p>He had yet engaged the King not to diſcover the cauſe of his melancholy; nor vvere there any that knew it, but he, the Princeſs <hi>Aretaphile,</hi> and my ſelf; nor did the Princeſſe know any more, then that <hi>Philoxypes</hi> vvas faln in love vvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> one that he knew not.</p>
            <p>It would be very hard to relate unto you what life he led; when it was fair weather, he went to viſit <hi>Policrite's</hi> Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and all the places where he had ſeen her, or ſpoken with her; he went to ask more queſtions of the ſlave who was there, and whom they had ever had an eye unto, not finding any one that ſpoke with him, nor that he ſpoke with any one. But all the addreſſes this Prince could make, could not prevail againſt the fidelity of this ſlave, who deſerved a better condition.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Philoxypes</hi> could not walk a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, he walked in his Gallery, gazing on the picture of his dear <hi>Policrite.</hi> When
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:151701:78"/>
he call'd to mind how contented a life he led before he fell in love, he almoſt wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he had never ſeen <hi>Policrite;</hi> but when he remembred her charming beauty, her bewitching mind, and the happy howres which he had enjoied in her company, though ſhee had alwaies concealed the eſteem ſhe had for him; he preferr'd all the ſorrows he had ſuffered ſince he was in love, before all his former pleaſures.</p>
            <p>Oh! would he ſometimes ſay to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, when he ſhould read <hi>Polycrite</hi>'s let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; how ſweet, how pleaſing, and how cruel things have I learnt in one day? <hi>Policrite</hi> is of illuſtrious birth, <hi>Policrite</hi> will alwaies remember me, and <hi>Policrite</hi> will never more ſee me. Alas, if it be ſo, ſaid he, why have I not recourſe to death, and what ſhall I do with ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate a life? Then ſuddenly remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that <hi>Policrite</hi> was alive, and that ſhe did not hate him, he conceived a beam of hope, that peradventure ſhee might make enquirie after him, and knowing how miſerable a life he led, ſhe might at laſt reſolve to let him know in what part ſhe lived.</p>
            <p>This thought afforded him only ſo
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:151701:78"/>
much hope as to keep him from dying; not ſo much as to comfort him in his misfortunes. Living then in this manner all the reſt of the Winter, he went ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to ſee the King, when the King could not come to him; and deſpairing of all remedie, he only expected death, or news of <hi>Policrite:</hi> the one or the other, whereof were the object of all his thoughts, &amp; the bounds of all his deſires. The Spring it ſelf, which ſeems to inſpire joy into whole nature, wrought no alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in him. He beheld the roſes in his Gardens bluſh, with the ſame melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie as hee had ſeen his knots white with Snow in Winter. Thoſe who watched over <hi>Cleanthes</hi> his ſlave, brought him word one morning, that he was ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dead. This anger ſome news did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>double his grief, in as much as for that he ſeemed concerned in any thing which belonged to <hi>Policrite;</hi> and that this ſlave appeared to him worthy of ſuch good fortune, as that in loſing him, hee loſt almoſt all hopes of ever diſcovering where <hi>Policrite</hi> was. He forbare not notwithſtanding, to have watch kept for a while, to ſee whether any bodie
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:151701:79"/>
ſhould come to that rural Cottage, or no: but at laſt, wearie of wearying out his people, he diſpenced with their further trouble therein; and abandoned his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune abſolutely to the guidance of the gods.</p>
            <p>As he was one daie in this ſad mood, <hi>Solon</hi> came to <hi>Claria:</hi> hee was at firſt much joied to hear a name he ſo dearlie loved; but conſidering what an alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there was in him, ſince he had ſeen him, and how confounded he ſhould bee to acknowledge his weakneſs to him, though he knew that lawful love was not a paſſion to which <hi>Solon</hi> had declared himſelf an enemy, this joy ſuffered a little allay. He went notwithſtanding with much eagerneſs to meet him; but ſadneſs having ſo deeply ſeiſed upon his heart and eyes, the ſatisfaction which he received to ſee the famous <hi>Solon,</hi> was ſo inward, as there hardly appeared any ſign thereof in his countenance. <hi>Solon</hi> no ſooner ſaw him, but he obſerved his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy; and <hi>Philoxypes</hi> on his part, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king on <hi>Solon,</hi> in ſtead of the peacefull phyſiognomy, and that chearful and pleaſing aſpect which he had wont to
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:151701:79"/>
have in his eyes, he ſeemed to ſee a great deal of ſorrow.</p>
            <p>The firſt complements being over, and <hi>Philoxypes</hi> having brought <hi>Solon</hi> to his chamber; Sir, ſaid he, the ſight of you would ſurely much rejoyce me, did I not ſee ſome ſigns of ſorrow in you, of which I muſt needs requeſt to know the cauſe. Noble Prince, reply'd <hi>Solon,</hi> I ſhould have prevented you, and have deſired to know the cauſe of your melancholy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore having afforded you leaſure to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form your ſelf of mine. But I confeſſe unto you, the Law-giver of <hi>Athens,</hi> is not at preſent in a condition of preſcribing Laws unto himſelf; and that the ſorrow I feel, is ſtronger then my reaſon. <hi>Philoxy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes,</hi> embracing him then ſtraitly, conjured him to tell him the reaſon thereof, and deſired him to believe he would do all that laie in his power to comfort him.</p>
            <p>But Sir, ſaid he, <hi>I</hi> thought that Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie had been a ſalve to you againſt all the misfortunes of life; and that ſorrow was a thing unknown to <hi>Solon,</hi> to whom whole <hi>Greece</hi> gives the name of wiſe.</p>
            <p>Philoſophie ſaid this famous Athenian, is a vain-glorious art, which boaſts of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:151701:80"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:151701:80"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:151701:81"/>
in places, wherein ſhe hath no great power; ſhe may doubtleſly ſaid he, teach men to bee vertuous, make them know whole nature, teach them how to diſcourſe, and give them Laws and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts for the government of Kingdoms, and Common-wealths; Nay, ſhe may oft times make us overcome our paſſions; but when an equitable feeling, which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture gives us, is to be overcome, believe me <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> the ſame Philoſophy which hath ſometimes made us loſe Crownes without change of countenance, or which hath made us not ſtick to refuſe them, is weak in leſſe eminent occaſions. And in my particular, I may ſay I have beene thrice in my life time abandoned by her; though peradventure I have been aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by her upon an hundred difficult oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions. But yet ſaid <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> ſhall I not know vvhat 'tis that afflicts you? It very well behoves that I tell it you, ſaid <hi>Solon,</hi> ſince 'tis from you alone that I can expect any help. I will not repeat unto you, ſaid he, the ſo many particulars of my fortune which formerly I have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted you withal, for I believe you have not forgot them; but that you may
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:151701:81"/>
perfectly know the cauſe of my grief, I muſt howſoever take the riſe of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe afar off; and tell you ſome cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of my life, which you have not yet known. You know I never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that marriage was incompetible with Philoſophy and true Wiſdome, as <hi>Thales</hi> that famous Mileſian did imagine; you know likewiſe that I married a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage of great worth and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, by whom I had children, who died ſoon after they were born; one onely ſon excepted, whom I have bred up care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, intending to make him worthie of that noble bloud whence he is deſcended. He was about 14 or 15 years old, when I vvas at <hi>Milet,</hi> about ſome affairs of mine; where I viſited wiſe <hi>Thales,</hi> who was one of my very good friends. He civily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proacht me with my weakneſs, and ſaid <hi>I</hi> did ſufficiently witneſs my indulgencie to love, by a little image of <hi>Cupid,</hi> which <hi>I</hi> one day conſecrated to that Deitie, and placed in the park belonging to the Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demie, there vvhere they who run vvith the ſacred Torch, are wont to aſſemble themſelves. Paſſing from one thing to another, we ſpake of the happineſs, and
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:151701:82"/>
of the misfortunes of marriage, and thus our diſcourſe varying, as it oft fals out from our firſt ſubject, wee ſpoke of news and other ſuch like matters.</p>
            <p>Preſently after, <hi>Thales</hi> feigning to have ſome order to give to one of his folk about his own affairs, roſe to ſpeak to him in his ear, and came and took his place again. Not long after, I might ſee a ſtranger come, whom I knew not, vvho told him he was come from <hi>Ath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns,</hi> not above ten daies ago. Preſt by the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral deſire of curioſitie, to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there was nothing of new befaln in my Countrey, ſince my departure thence, I askt him whether he knew any thing of conſiderable there or no? No, ſaid he, ſave onely that the day I came away on, I ſaw the Funeral obſerved of a young youth of the beſt rank, vvhereat all the people of note in the Town, vvere pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and vvere very ſenſible of the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row this childs death vvould cauſe in his Father, vvho vvas not then at <hi>Athens.</hi> I confeſs when I heard him ſpeak thus, my colour changed, fearing my ſon might be concerned: vvhich made mee ask him whether he knew not the name of
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:151701:82"/>
that unfortunate Father? I have forgot it, ſaid he, but I know hee is a man of great integritie, and who is much eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of in that place.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe, Sir, that ſince Philoſophy teacheth ſinceritie, as well as modeſtie, I thought <hi>I</hi> might be the man ſpoken of; was willing to know the truth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offence to good manners; his name, doubtleſly, ſaid I, was not <hi>Solon:</hi> pardon me, ſaid he, his name came juſt to my memory, as you pronounced it. To what end ſerves it to deny it? I could not heare ſo ſad news vvithout ſorrow, and that ſo great as <hi>Thales</hi> pitied me, and jeſting at my weakneſs, asked me whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were advantageous for a wiſe man to marry, or no? Putting himſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by in a condition to have ſtudied Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie for others, not being able to make uſe thereof himſelf. After this, he told mee there was not one word true of all that this man had ſaid; that he had not ſo much as been at <hi>Athens</hi> of a long time; and that he had ſaid all this by his directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which he had cauſed to be given him, when he roſe from me to ſpeak in the ear with one of his ſervants.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:151701:83"/>
At my return to <hi>Athens,</hi> I found my ſon alive indeed, but I found the whole Town in confuſion, by reaſon of ſome diſorder that had happened between thoſe that were deſcended from <hi>Megacles,</hi> and thoſe that were come of them that had been of the Citonien conſpiracie. The Megarians ſurpriſed the port of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa,</hi> and re took the Iſle of <hi>Salamina,</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap> had cauſed me ſo much trouble. And to add to the misfortune, all the people were ſeiſed on with a ſuperſtitious ſnare, vvhich perſwaded them that ſpirits retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; that fantoſmes and apparitions ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared; and this imagination prevailed ſo much with moſt of them, as there was an univerſal humiliation.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who had the charge of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred things, ſaid, that they found infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible ſignes by the Victims, that the town needed purification, and that the gods were incenſed by reaſon of ſome ſecret offence committed.</p>
            <p>To this effect, by the advice of the wiſeſt ſort, they ſent an Expreſſe to <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> to <hi>Epimenides</hi> the Phaeſtien, who was and doubtleſlie is ſtill, an incomparable man, a man whoſe life is altogether pure,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:151701:83"/>
innocent, and holy: who eats no more then what is ſufficient to maintain life, and whoſe ſoul leans as little to the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as in this life it can: who is very lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the knowledge of heavenly things; and who paſſes in his Countrey, not onely for one who hath ſometimes Divine Revelations, but is by the people of <hi>Crete</hi> believed to be the ſonne of a Nymph, called, <hi>Balta.</hi> However it be ſir, he is a man of extraordinary knowledge, and virtue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Epimenides,</hi> not refuſing the intreaties that were made unto him, came to <hi>Athens,</hi> and of ſo many famous men as were in that noted Citie, did me the favour to chuſe me for his moſt intimate friend, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving through his wiſdome, and through the peoples belief in him, diſſipated all their falſe imaginations, and that by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Sacrifices, and Ceremonies, he had rid them of all their fears, he would yet ſtay a while at <hi>Athens</hi> for my ſake; where certainly he told Prodigious predictions to a hundred ſeverall people. As we were ſpeaking one day of humane weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and how little a man ought to rely upon his own ſtrength, nor yet upon Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie;
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:151701:84"/>
I acquainted him with what had befallen me with <hi>Thales</hi> the <hi>Mileſian,</hi> and how much aſhamed <hi>I</hi> was, not to be maſter of my firſt opinions. <hi>Solon</hi> (ſaid he to me) is eaſie to be overcome on that ſide, and as oft as fortune will make uſe of the affections of nature againſt him, ſhe will certainly overcome him: For he hath a ſoul as tender upon ſuch eneoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as ſtrong againſt ambition: But <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> ſaid he, you are to be bewailed if you do not reſolve to believe me; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that what you underwent whileſt you were with your friend <hi>Thales,</hi> is little in compariſon of what you ſhall one day ſuffer in the perſon of a Daughter, of whom your wife is at this preſent with Child.</p>
            <p>I have, ſaid he, obſerved your birth, and your life, and I finde that this childe, which will be ſoon born, will be a prodigie for beauty and virtue; and will alſo be one of the happieſt women in the world, if you will believe my councel: but alſo if you will not believe, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it, ſhee will be moſt unfortunate. In fine, ſaidhe, If you do not what I ſhal ſay unto you, you ſhall have the diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:151701:84"/>
to ſee that your Daughters beauty will make your Countrie deſolate; and that after having refuſed the ſovereign power (as you will one day refuſe it) ſhe will make one of your Citizens fall in Love with her, who will become the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the Common wealth, which will make her reſolve to die, rather then to marry him.</p>
            <p>I confeſe I was much troubled to hear <hi>Epimenides</hi> ſpeak after this manner; for I had heard him foretel divers things, which I had ſeen punctually fall out ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his predictions. <hi>I</hi> then deſired him to tell me what he would have me do, to preſerve a man who did ſacrifice his whole life to the glory of <hi>Athens,</hi> from having a daughter who ſhould cauſe love in him that would be the Tyrant thereof. He told me then, That ſince it was not yet known in <hi>Athens</hi> that my wife was with Childe, I ſhould conceal her great belly; ſend her into the countrey, &amp; when ſhee ſhould be brought to bed, that I ſhould cauſe this daughter to be ſecretly brought up, not ſuffering her to know whoſe childe ſhee was, nor yet any other body whoſoever, except thoſe who were
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:151701:85"/>
to have the care of her education, that if it ſhould ſo fall out, as I ſhould be forced to forſake my Countrey, I muſt during my exile, leave her in ſome Iſland upon the <hi>Egean</hi> Sea; and that things being thus carried, ſhe ſhould be infallibly happie, and I ſhould not need to fear that ſhee ſhould be beloved by the Tyrant of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens.</hi> In fine, Sir, to ſhorten my diſcourſe, I obeyed <hi>Epimenides</hi> his his adviſe; I ſent my wife into the Countrey, where when her time was come, ſhee was brought to bed of a Daughter: wondering at the accompliſhment of the beginning of this prediction, I continued to follow <hi>Epemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedes</hi> his directions, who at his departure (after having refuſed all the preſents that were made him, and taking for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, onely a branch of the Sacred O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live) told me that my daughter would one day cauſe as much joy in me by her virtue, and good fortune, as ſhee would cauſe ſorrow in me by reaſon of her loſs. Theſe obſcure words continued fix'd in my memory, ſo as I put my daughter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of a Siſter of mine whom I loved very well, who was married in <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> and was come to ſee me: truſting
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:151701:85"/>
onely her, and her husband, with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret which <hi>Epeminedes</hi> had acquainted me withall.</p>
            <p>I will not ſtay to tell you, that ſoon after <hi>I</hi> loſt my wife, for which I was very much grieved; neither will I entertain you with the diſorders of <hi>Athens,</hi> which are too well known to all men; nor yet with the relation how I was ſolicited to accept of the ſovereign power, being put in mind that there had been Kings of my Race, and that one that was deſcended from the illuſtrious <hi>Chodrus,</hi> need make no ſcruple to accept the Scepter: nor vvith vvhat ſtedfaſtneſs I rejected thoſe vvho made ſo unjuſt a propoſition to me, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovving <hi>Epeminedes</hi> his predictions. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vvill I tell you vvhat Lavvs I there eſtabliſhed, you knovv them, and knovv hovv they vvere obſerved; nor yet the reſolution vvhich I took to quit my Countrey, for the ſpace of ten years; to the end that I might make no further alterations, and leave the people leaſure to accuſtom themſelves to their new Lawes.</p>
            <p>But I will tell you, that being readie
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:151701:86"/>
to take my voluntarie baniſhment from <hi>Greece,</hi> and not forgetting what <hi>Epemine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> had told me, I came to <hi>Corinth,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known: and having told my ſiſter that I was obliged to leave my Daughter in an Iſland during the time of my exile: This vertuous perſonage, who loved her no leſs then a Daughter, which ſhe had of her own, had married a Gentleman of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary worth, and who had long li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a retired live, ſo as as ſhee eaſilie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with him, not to abandon my Daughter, who really appeard to me, to be the ſweeteſt childe I ever ſaw. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted the Gods touching my deſign, who confirmed me therein. Thus I took this little Familie along with me in my ſhip; and being deſirous that the place of exile for theſe whom <hi>I</hi> ſo dearly loved, might be a pleaſant place, I choſe this Iſle to leave them in.</p>
            <p>Whileſt <hi>Solon</hi> diſcovered thus at large, <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> who longed to interrupt him, could no longer forbear: did you, Sir, ſaid he, leave a Daughter in this Iſland? Yes, ſaid <hi>Solon,</hi> with a ſigh, and I ſaw her here about four years ago, when I would be ſeen by none but by you: and Sir, if
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:151701:86"/>
I may be allowed to ſay ſo, I ſaw her ſuch a one as <hi>Epeminedes</hi> had deſiphered her, to wit handſom, ful of wit &amp; vertue.</p>
            <p>When I firſt left thoſe, to whoſe gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance <hi>I</hi> committed her, I willed them to ſaie they were of the Iſland of <hi>Crete:</hi> At this word, <hi>Philoxypes</hi> changed colour, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring that it was of thence that <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anthes</hi> ſaid himſelf to be. But Sir, ſaid he, how vvas this daughter called, that the Gods gave you? <hi>Polycrite</hi> replied, <hi>Solon. Policrite,</hi> ſaid <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> is <hi>Policrite,</hi> Sir, then your daughter? <hi>Solon</hi> ſurpriſed at <hi>Philoxypes</hi> queſtion, changed colour alſo, and feared leſt this Prince might have known ſomewhat of <hi>Policrite,</hi> which might diſpleaſe him more then the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty he was in of her life or place of abode.</p>
            <p>How Sir, ſaid he, came you to know my daughter, whom to ſaie truth, I left near enough to you, but whom <hi>I</hi> had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo left in a place, vvhere I thought not you ſhould have met with her; and that when you ſhould have met with her, you ſhould not have known her to be vvhat ſhe is? It vvas the Gods, replied <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xypes,</hi> who brought me to the knowledg
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:151701:87"/>
of her; and 'tis the Gods likewiſe, ſaid he, vvho have taken her from her Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, doubtleſly to puniſh me for not preciſely knowing the daughter of that famous <hi>Solon.</hi> At laſt, hee deſired this Law-giver to go into his Gallery, which vvas painted ſince his laſt being at <hi>Claria;</hi> and ſhewing him the ſeveral pictures of <hi>Policrite,</hi> under the figure of <hi>Venus Urania;</hi> behold, Sir, ſaid he, the Goddeſſe vvhich made me know <hi>Policrite. Solon</hi> ſurpriſed with the ſight, looked on <hi>Philoxypes</hi> &amp; not comprehending how he could come by thoſe pictures, without <hi>Policrites</hi> conſent; Sir, ſaid he, <hi>Epimenides</hi> aſſured me that <hi>Policrite,</hi> ſhould be vertuous; but theſe pictures make me believe, that being bred up amongſt the Rocks, ſhe may have become too indulgent. Ah, Sir, ſaid <hi>Philoxypes!</hi> how farre is <hi>Policrite</hi> from what you ſpeak of? but ſhall I dare to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you with my boldneſs? and ſhall <hi>I</hi> dare to enquire of you, before <hi>I</hi> acquaint you vvith my misfortune, and yours, wherefore you left her in that place? <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> who knew <hi>Cleanthes</hi> and <hi>Megiſto</hi>'s in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, who knew likewiſe how vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Policrite</hi> was, condemned his firſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitions,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:151701:87"/>
and haſted to tell him how when he firſt arrived in our Iſland, hee made <hi>Cleanthes</hi> and his Family come on ſhore as paſſengers which he knew not, that afterwards he placed them near the ſea, ſide, but that being afterwards at <hi>Claria,</hi> and whil'ſt he aſſiſted him in the building of that town to which he would give his name, being walk'd abrode all alone, he had obſerved that little deſert place, where he placed <hi>Policrite,</hi> having given <hi>Cleanthes</hi> where withall to build that little Cottage, and where withall to ſubſiſt commodiouſlie during the time of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ile. That paſſing from <hi>Africa,</hi> into <hi>Aſia,</hi> to go to <hi>Creſſus</hi> his Court, he would firſt come once again to <hi>Cyprus,</hi> that he might ſee his dear <hi>Policrite.</hi> That he had been a whole month in that Cottage, <hi>Policrite</hi> not having all that while either known his name, nor that he was her Father; and that afterwards he came to viſit him at <hi>Claria;</hi> that he confeſt he had in that jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney diſcovered ſtrange lights in the young maids underſtanding, which obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him to be very ſenſible of her loſs: For ſaid he, <hi>I</hi> can finde no bodie now in that Cottage, and cannot learn, neither
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:151701:88"/>
why thoſe that did inhabit there have left it, nor how long it is ſince they went from thence, nor vvhat vvay they are gone.</p>
            <p>But you Sir, ſaid he, be pleaſed I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you to let me hear all whatſoever you knovv of my daughter, and conceal nothing from me; for I confeſs I ſtand upon thornes. <hi>Philoxypes</hi> having obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that <hi>Solon</hi> was really very impatient to know how he came to knovv <hi>Policrite,</hi> and hovv he had got ſo many Pictures of hers, told him the vvhole truth; he made him call to mind his former inflexibility, and hovv he had told him long ſince that a man might once in his life be overcome by love vvithout any ſhame. Then he told him vvhat glorious and gallant com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany he had had at his houſe; hovv mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly this <hi>Venus</hi> vvas eſteemed by them all: the conteſtation vvhich he had vvith them thereupon; hovv aftervvards he met vvith <hi>Policrite,</hi> at the head of the River <hi>Claria;</hi> hovv ſurprized he vvas to ſee that the Pourtrait of his <hi>Venus,</hi> ſhould be the picture of this unknovvn maid; hovv much he vvas troubled that he could not finde her again; hovv happily
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:151701:88"/>
he met <hi>Cleanthes</hi> as he vvas going vvith his Family to the Temple: hovv he ſavv her the third time vvhen he found her in the Temple; hovv at laſt he diſcovered her Cottage, and his ſundry thoughts thereupon: he acquainted him vvith the firſt viſit he made to <hi>Policrite,</hi> vvhen he found her making Garlands of Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; vvhat ſpeech he had vvith <hi>Cleanthes,</hi> and <hi>Megiſto;</hi> and in fine, hovv violently he vvas taken vvith her. He told him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, hovv he had endeavoured to ſuppreſs his paſſion, by reaſon of the ſuppoſed meanneſs of her birth: vvhat an altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this paſſion had vvrought in his minde: hovv the Court vvas ſtartled at his Melancholy; the Kings odd conceipt thereupon, his diſcourſe vvith the King, and with the Princeſs <hi>Aretaphile:</hi> hovv angry this Princeſs vvas, and hovv much he himſelf was perplext: hovv it came to paſs that <hi>Mandroclus</hi> had dravvn <hi>Policrite</hi>'s Pictures; and in fine, he told him all that had befallen him: and vvhen he had ended his recitall, not affording <hi>Solon</hi> leiſure to ſpeak, thus you ſee, Sir, ſaid he, I am no longer that Inflexible <hi>Philoxypes</hi> vvhich you formerly knevv
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:151701:89"/>
me to be, but I may ſafely proteſt unto you, that I loved <hi>Policrite</hi> in a Cottage, with the ſame reſpect as if ſhee had been ſeated on a Throne: and I may alſo aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you, that my paſſion for her was as pure, as if I had known ſhee had been your daughter.</p>
            <p>Do not blame me then, I conjure you, ſince I have onely adored <hi>Solons</hi> virtue and worth in <hi>Policrite</hi>'s perſon; for tis her virtuous minde which I am more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amor'd of, then of her perſonal beauty; yet do I deſerve to be puniſh'd, for doubtleſly my frequent viſits have cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Cleanthes</hi> to change his abode. Hee knew not <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> and Imagined he might have abuſed him in <hi>Policrite:</hi> But to prove, ſaid he, that I lived reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully with her, and that I never received a favourable word from her, ſee (ſaid he, Sir, ſhewing him the letter which hee had received) the innocent and cruell ſign of acknowledgement, that this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſonage hath given me, ſince that at the ſame time when ſhee ſaies ſhe will remember me, ſhee ſaies alſo ſhe ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſee me more: yet Sir, ſaid he, if my paſſion do diſpleaſe you, you ſhall ſee
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:151701:89"/>
how ready I will be to die, as ſoon as you ſhall have given me the leaſt occaſion ſo to do; ſince that is the only way whereby <hi>I</hi> can pluck her from out my heart: but on the contrary, if you do truly love me, you will rather bewail me, then accuſe me; you will promiſe me not to oppoſe me, if the Gods reſtore <hi>Policrite</hi> to you: and you will ſuffer her to be Miſtreſs of that ſtately town which was built by your di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections.</p>
            <p>I wiſh, Sir, I were able to offer her ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Scepters; but <hi>I</hi> think not that he who refuſeth them, will ſtick much to beſtow his daughter on a Prince, who thinks himſelf happie in being but near a Throne, and to aſſiſt his King to ſuſtain the weight of his Scepter.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Philoxypes</hi> had made an end of ſpeaking, and <hi>Solon</hi> had read <hi>Policrite</hi>'s letter; my Daughter ſaid he, is yet wiſer then I thought her to have been: and ſince ſhe hath been able to reſiſt the charms of <hi>Philoxype</hi>'s greatneſs and worth J finde <hi>Epimenides</hi> had reaſon to ſpeak of her, as of a miracle.</p>
            <p>Be you then aſſured, ſaid he, Sir, That if the Gods reſtore my Daughter to me,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:151701:90"/>
I ſhall bring no other obſtacle to your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, then my humble deſire that you will ſeriouſly conſider whether ſhee be worthy or no of the honour you would do her: for if you continue in your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and that I ſhall know that ſhee doth indeed deſerve a part of the favours which you vouchſafe her, I ſhall be ready to command her to look on you, as on him whom the gods have choſen to make her happy and glorious.</p>
            <p>I do not tell you <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> that the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Exceſtides,</hi> my Father, who left me poor onely out of his own Magnificen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, was deſcended from the illuſtrious bloud of King <hi>Chodrus;</hi> for theſe are not things which I think men ought much to boaſt of: But I will aſſure you, that all thoſe of my Houſe, ſince they have left the Crown, have been as good Citizens, as their Forefathers were good Kings; and that for my particular, I had alwaies ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther oppoſe my ſelf to Tyrannie, then be a Tyrant.</p>
            <p>In fine, ſaid he, as it is not to your great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that I give <hi>Policrite, I</hi> pretend alſo, that <hi>Policrite</hi>'s virtue, ſhall ſupplie the place of a Crown.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="165" facs="tcp:151701:90"/>
But alas, ſaid <hi>Philoxypes!</hi> how will you give me this Divine <hi>Policrite,</hi> if we know not where ſhee is? She muſt be begg'd of the Gods, replied <hi>Solon,</hi> ſince tis from them alone that we are to expect all the good that can befall us.</p>
            <p>In fine; ſir, <hi>Philoxypes</hi> conceived an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſable joy, to finde <hi>Solon</hi> ſo favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably diſpoſed towards him. But alſo his grief was no leſs extream, to think that <hi>Solons</hi> good intentions would prove of no uſe, if <hi>Policrite</hi> were not found. Yet was he ſomewhat comforted with the ſight of ſo famous a man, and the converſation of one ſo perfectly wiſe, made his ſorrow appear at leaſt more moderate, though really it was alwaies very great. Nay, <hi>I</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member he told me that notwithſtanding all his ſadneſs, he forgot not you, ſir, but entertained <hi>Solon</hi> with the diſcourſe of you, as of a very extraordinarie Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage.</p>
            <p>This mean while the King, having heard of <hi>Solons</hi> arrivall, and how that <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite</hi> was his daughter, was exceeding glad, and would have him and <hi>Philoxypes</hi> to come to Court; ſo as this Prince his love was no longer ſo great a ſecret.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:151701:91"/>
Imagining that <hi>Cleanthes</hi> was not gone out of the Iſland, command was ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to all the Towns and Vilages, to give an account of what ſtrangers lived in them, but do what they could, they could learn no acceptable news.</p>
            <p>This mean while the Court grew very melancholy; for Princeſs <hi>Aretaphile,</hi> not able to put on a reſolution of pardoning the King, the King by an odd phanſie of Love, reſolved alſo to winne this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs her heart, before he would aſſure her to make her his Queen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philoxypes</hi> on his part was mad to think he could not finde out <hi>Policrite,</hi> and that he had been the cauſe why <hi>Solon</hi> had loſt her: and <hi>Solon</hi> was alſo very ſad that hee could hear no newes of his daughter; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially at a time when he vvas of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie to return to <hi>Athens,</hi> where he had learned that there was great diſorders, and that all things tended towards Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>He knevv that there vvere three ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Factions there: that one <hi>Licurgus</hi> vvas chief of thoſe that inhabited the plains; that <hi>Megacles,</hi> ſonne to <hi>Alcmeon,</hi> commanded over thoſe of the ſea coaſt,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:151701:91"/>
and that <hi>Piſiſtrates,</hi> whom certainly you knew when you went to <hi>Athens,</hi> was chief of the mountaineers. So as though all that numerous people had punctually obſerved his Laws, ſince his departure, yet the face of affairs was likely ſoon to alter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solon</hi> being then neceſſitated to be gone within a few daies, told <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> That the intereſt of a mans country, was to be preferd before all things elſe: and that he who choſe rather to conceal his daughter, then to expoſe her to the love of a Tyrant, would not abandon his Countrey, to expect in vain to hear of one whom certainly the Gods would preſerve if ſhe were worthy of their care; ſo as he had no more to do, then give him full leave to marry her if he ſhould finde her; <hi>Philoxypes</hi> being at that ſame time both much afflicted, and much joyed; thankt <hi>Solon</hi> for the honour he did him; but the winde not ſerving for his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and his ſhip not being ready, he muſt have patience for a while. During this interval of time, <hi>Solon</hi> underſtood that there was a famous Temple about ſome forty miles from <hi>Paphos,</hi> dedicated as
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:151701:92"/>
were almoſt all the reſt in the Iſland, to <hi>Venus Urania,</hi> where 'twas ſaid this God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſs delighted more to be honour'd, then in any other Temple: becauſe the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom there was, that all the Ceremonies were performed by maids of good diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, who dedicated themſelves to the ſervice of that Goddeſs, and who were to ſerve her three years in her Temple before they were to marry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solon</hi> who believed he could not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy the time better, which much againſt his will, he was to ſtay in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> then in praying to the Gods, moved <hi>Philoxypes</hi> to go thither, who eaſily gave way thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: ſo as getting on horſeback the next morning and attended but by a few ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, they came to this Temple, which is very delightfully ſeated.</p>
            <p>I know Sir, I ſhould not ſtay to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you with all the Ceremonies of the ſacrifice, which upon this occaſion was offered for <hi>Solon,</hi> and <hi>Philoxypes;</hi> yet it being famous amongſt us for what en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued thereupon, I will crave leave to do it; as alſo becauſe peradventure, you have not ſeen the like: For tis a ſacrifice which doth not coſt the victims lives, but
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:151701:92"/>
on the contrary, makes them recover their liberty.</p>
            <p>This Temple is fairly enough built: the Altar is ſtately, at the foot whereof, and juſt in the mid'ſt, is placed a great candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick of Gold with twelve branches, whereon Chriſtal Lamps hung which was all lighted inſtantly after. Fifty maids, clothed in ſilver Tiffany, mingled with blew to denote the original of that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Venus</hi> whom they ſerved, having each of them a Coronet of flowers on their head, and ſprigs of Myrrh in their hands, rank'd themſelves on the two ſides of the Temple, ſhe onely excepted who was to perform the Ceremony, who ſtaid in the middle.</p>
            <p>At the foot of this golden Candleſtick, there was a great Cheſt or Coffer of the ſame metal, wherein there was fire which they termed ſacred, becauſe it is onely lighted by the agitation of certain ſtones conſecrated to the Goddeſs: ſhe who offered the ſacrifice in the name of <hi>Solon,</hi> and <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> put Amber, Frankinſence, Benjamin, and divers other perfumes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Pile of wood: This being done, and having made a little Pile of the dry
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:151701:93"/>
boughs of Myrh upon the Altar, ſhe took a Torch made of perfumed wax, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhe ſet it on fire, and with the ſame Torch ſhe lighted fifty others which were placed in ſundry parts of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: after this, one of theſe maids brought two Turtles tied together with threads of gold and blew ſilk; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her who carried the Birds, went four other maids ſinging a Hymn after the <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> manner: after theſe came four o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, bringing with them two Swans ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together with a ſtring of blew and gold, and followed by four more who ſung as did the former.</p>
            <p>Theſe maids who carryed the Victims, kneeled down before the Altar, which being done, ſhe who did the Ceremony, (to the end that ſhe might not irritate <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Anadiomena,</hi> who had been formerly worſhipped in that Temple, by the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that was done to <hi>Venus Urania)</hi> took Roſes and Cockles, which ſhe ſtrowd upon the Altar, and taking a great ſhel of the Mother of pearl full of ſea water, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up towards the eaſt, ſhe ſprinkled the Victims therewith.</p>
            <p>The holy knife, adorned with
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:151701:93"/>
Orientall Agget, was likewiſe prepared, as it were to ſacrifice them; but the maids who ſung continually forbad them in the behalf of <hi>Venus Urania,</hi> ſo as ſhee who carried the Turtles, and the other who carried the Swans, drawing near her who performed the Ceremonie, ſhe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied them, and opening one of the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of the Temple, at the ſame time when they threw new perfumes into the pile of wood, they were loſt in that cloud of perfume which aroſe, and flying to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards heaven, ſeemed as if they went to carry up the vows of <hi>Solon</hi> and <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> to the Goddeſs to whom they were offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up.</p>
            <p>After this, all the maids which were in the Temple, began a Canticle of joy and one of them taking a little Fagot of Myrh, which was bound about with threads of Gold, ſwept together the aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the little pile, to ſee whether all were quite conſumed or no; for this is one of the tokens that the Sacrifice hath been well received.</p>
            <p>In purſuit after this, they went to viſit the ſacred garden, wherein the Turtles
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:151701:94"/>
and Swans, deſtined to the ſervice of the Goddeſs, are bred up, to ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe that were offerd up unto her, were returned thither or no: for when this falls not out, tis an infallible obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation that the ſacrifice hath not been well accepted of, and that the Goddeſs thinks not thoſe birds pure enough to be preſented unto her another time. But as for <hi>Solon</hi> his Sacrifice, it had all the marks of a happy Sacrifice; the Pile was total<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſumed, the perfumes mounted ſtreight upright toward the Temples Roof, the birds flew Eaſt-ward, and were found in the ſacred Garden. In fine, theſe maids aſſured <hi>Philoxypes</hi> and <hi>Solon,</hi> that their vows were well accepted of by the Goddeſs; and that they had not of a long time offerd any Sacrifice, which had been ſo well accepted of.</p>
            <p>Having then returned acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the Divine <hi>Urania,</hi> theſe two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>Paphos: Solon</hi> did ſo pleaſantly entertain <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> and ſaid ſuch fine things to him, as not taking heed, he miſt the way by which they came. Thoſe who followed them, thought that <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> who very well knew that way, intended
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:151701:94"/>
to go ſom whither that they knew not of, ſo as they let him go on. Continuing to ride on thus by this by-way, they ſtrayed not onely from the way they were to go, but came at laſt to a place where there was no beaten track at all: finding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at the Sea ſide, amongſt wilde, and almoſt inacceſſible Rocks, the ſight here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of recall'd into <hi>Philoxypes</hi> memory the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart wherein he had found <hi>Policrites</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode.</p>
            <p>But at the ſame time he found that he had loſt his way; and that he knew not where he was: yet it appearing delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full enough unto him, though ſandy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, he ſaid to <hi>Solon,</hi> that continuing to go along the ſea ſide, they ſhould meet with ſome path which would lead them back into the right way; wherefore they did not return back, but continued on their way; and <hi>Philoxypes</hi> rode formoſt, that he might be a guide to thoſe that he had led out of the way.</p>
            <p>Being advanced a good way, he might ſee five or ſix fiſhers Cottages, built upon the ſea ſide, and heard the voice of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain women who ſeemed to bewail ſome misfortune.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:151701:95"/>
He then mended his pace, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing why the voice of thoſe women had had ſuch an operation in him: and being come near them, he knew <hi>Megiſto,</hi> and <hi>Dorida,</hi> and found them ſorely weeping, and accompanied vvith many other vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, vvho vvept as vvell as they, and vvho not minding him, looked all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvards the ſea.</p>
            <p>He then looked the ſame vvay they did, vvhere, alas! he might ſee <hi>Policrite,</hi> all alone in a little boat floating, vvithout either Oars or Rudder; vvho not knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vvhat to do, vvas upon her knees praying to Heaven; for though the ſea vvent not very high, yet vvas it ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvhat moved; and moreover, the Rocks bearing back the Waves on that ſide, and a breath of air blovving from land, the boat vvent ſtill further off.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philoxypes</hi> ſeeing <hi>Polycrite</hi> in ſo great a danger, and not ſeeing any boat that he might make uſe of, lighted ſuddenly off Horſeback, and threvv himſelf into the Water, ſvvimming ſtreight tovvards <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licrite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So as vvhen <hi>Solon,</hi> vvho vvas a little behind, vvas come to the ſea ſhore, you
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:151701:95"/>
may eaſily imagine hovv much he vvas ſurprized to ſee <hi>Megiſto</hi> covered vvith tears, <hi>Policrite</hi> all alone in a boat, vvhich the Waves bore tovvards the full ſea, and <hi>Philoxypes</hi> ſvvimming tovvards <hi>Policrite;</hi> but he vvas ſo far from her, as it vvas to be believed that (the boat floating ſtill forward) his ſtrength might fail him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he could get up to her; and that <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> might ſee his dear daughter periſh in his ſight, as alſo a Prince whom he loved no leſs then her.</p>
            <p>To tell you alſo how ſtrangely aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd <hi>Megiſto</hi> was, to ſee <hi>Philoxypes</hi> throw himſelf into the ſea, and preſently after to ſee <hi>Solon</hi> come, is not a thing eaſily done. Nor yet to ſet forth <hi>Policrites</hi> thoughts, vvhen ſhe knevv <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> and ſavv him in ſo great danger for her ſake.</p>
            <p>This gallant perſonage told us not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvithſtanding aftervvards, that ſhe no ſooner knevv him, but the object of her vovvs altered; and that ceaſing to think on her ovvn danger, all her prayers vvere poured forth for <hi>Philoxypes.</hi> This mean vvhile <hi>Solon</hi> vvas upon the ſhore vvith <hi>Megiſto,</hi> vvhoſe minde vvas not
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:151701:96"/>
then at liberty enough to tell him how this misfortune hapned, telling him one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that <hi>Policrite</hi> was loſt.</p>
            <p>And to ſay truth, I think that upon this encounter, <hi>Solons</hi> wiſdom was put to a greater tryal, then ever it had been: and that it was much more eaſie for him to refuſe a Crown, then to ſee <hi>Policrite</hi> and <hi>Philoxypes</hi> in the danger they were in, without giving apparent tokens of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair.</p>
            <p>Yet this famous man kept himſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the lawful bounds of ſorrow; and not doing any thing unworthy of himſelf, did notwithſtanding, feel what ever pains a tender and generous ſoul could ſuffer under.</p>
            <p>This mean while though <hi>Philoxypes</hi> was but lightly clad, for the ſpring was already very hot in our Iſland, he could not ſwim with that facility as he might have done, had he been naked; ſo as <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licrites</hi> boat driving ſtill away, he could not get up unto it.</p>
            <p>One might ſee this young maid uſe ſome bootleſs endeavors to ſtay this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle boat, but twas impoſſible for her to do it: nay, ſhe did things which ſhe her
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:151701:96"/>
ſelf knew were of no avail, yet could not keep from doing them.</p>
            <p>One might likewiſe obſerve <hi>Philoxypes</hi> to ſtrive to his utmoſt, &amp; then he ſeemed to be ready to periſh through wearineſs. But at laſt being got near the boat, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times one might ſee the boat driven near unto him by one Wave, and ſometimes born from him by another; for it went too and fro with the wind.</p>
            <p>It was ſo near him as he might hear <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licrites</hi> voice, not being able to anſwer her, ſo much was he out of breath with ſwimming.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid ſhe, Let me periſh; do you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the ſhore: and ſtrive not boot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly to ſave me.</p>
            <p>You may imagine whether ſo obliging a command did not oblige <hi>Philoxypes</hi> to redouble his forces. At laſt, Sir, after that <hi>Solon</hi> had ſeen the Waves riſe up more then once, ready to over-turn the boat, and ſwallow up <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> who was now able to do no more, a great Wave having driven the boat towards him, he luckily laid hold of the rope whereby it was faſtened formerly to the Sea bank.</p>
            <p>You may imagine, Sir, what <hi>Philoxypes</hi>
               <pb n="178" facs="tcp:151701:97"/>
joy was then, as likewiſe what that of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licrite, Solon, Megiſto, Dorida,</hi> and the other women that were upon the ſhore; they all ſhouted for joy.</p>
            <p>Yet was it not yet time to rejoice; For though it be not hard to guide a floating boat, yet <hi>Philoxypes</hi> was ſo weary, as there was reaſon to diſpair of his ever accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing what he had ſo happily begun: he was ſeen to ſink twice under water, yet never quit the rope which he had in his hand. Think ſir, how great <hi>Policrites</hi> greif was then, and with how many tears ſhe repaid the pains he took to ſave her. One might obſerv this Amorus Prince do two contrary things; for he would look back upon the ſhore, that he might the ſooner bring back his Dear <hi>Policrite</hi> thither; and ſomtimes believing he ſhould periſh without ſaving her, he would at leaſt have the contentment of ſeeing her at his laſt gaſp.</p>
            <p>He looked thus, ſometimes towards the ſhore, ſometimes on <hi>Policrite:</hi> and things were in this condition; when <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi> and <hi>Solons</hi> ſervants, who tarryed a good way behinde by reaſon of ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident which had befallen one of their
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:151701:97"/>
horſes, were come up, amongſt which was one of <hi>Philoxypes</hi> his gentlemen, who being skilful in ſwimming, threw himſelf inſtantly into the Water, and helped his dear Maſter to guide <hi>Policrite</hi> back unto the ſhore, where this Prince was no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner arrived, but that his force failing him he ſwounded.</p>
            <p>Tis needleſs to tell you what <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, Megiſto,</hi> and all the reſt that were on the ſhore, did to aide him. As for <hi>Policrite,</hi> ſhee was ſo ſurprized and ſo afflicted to ſee what condition <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi> was in, as ſhe was not ſenſible of the joy of having eſcaped ſo great a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: but at laſt, after having carried <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi> into one of thoſe little Huts, and having by the means they uſed, brought him to life again, and dryed his apparrel, he asked where <hi>Policrite</hi> was? whom <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> brought to him out of a little cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber whither ſhe had retired her ſelf, though ſhe had not yet perfectly ſhook off the fear ſhe had been in of her ſelf, and of <hi>Philoxypes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But at laſt all being retired that were in that little hut, ſave <hi>Megiſto, Policrite, Dorida, Philoxypes,</hi> and <hi>Solon. Solon</hi> deſired
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:151701:98"/>
               <hi>Megiſto</hi> to tell him, why ſhe had quitted the little abode which he had cauſed be built for her? wherefore ſhe was come to this place, and where <hi>Cleanthes</hi> was? Wherefore they had left no order to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint him with their removal? and how this laſt misfortune had befallen <hi>Policrite?</hi> But, ſaid he, ſiſter, ſpeak freely without any wiſe disguiſing the truth. For Prince <hi>Philoxypes</hi> knows I am your brother, that <hi>Policrite</hi> is my daughter: and I know alſo that he does her the honour to love her; therefore conceal nothing for his reſpect, for he hath now a deeper ſhare in <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite,</hi> then I have, ſince I have given her to him; and that he may now lay a new claim unto her, by having ſaved her life.</p>
            <p>I leave you to imagine, Sir, how <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite</hi> was ſurprized to know that ſhe was <hi>Solons</hi> daughter, whom ſhe knew to be a great and excellent man, but whom ſhe knew not to be her father; and to know at the ſame time that ſhee was beſtowed on <hi>Phyloxypes;</hi> ſhe bluſh'd, but with a great deal of modeſty: and looking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Megiſto,</hi> as if ſhe would ask her whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were true or no that ſhe was <hi>Solons</hi> daughter? ſhe confirmed her in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief;
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:151701:98"/>
and afforded her leaſure ſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the joy ſhe had to ſee <hi>Philoxypes</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, with that of her knowing her ſelf to be daughter to ſo famous a man, as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing appeared in her countenance but what ſo great an honour might cauſe in her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philoxypes</hi> beginning then to ſpeak, ſaid as obliging things to <hi>Solon</hi> in <hi>Policrites</hi> behalfe, as in his own; and <hi>Megiſto</hi> was ſomewhile before ſhe could ſatisfie her Brothers curioſity. But at laſt ſhe told him, That knowing the love Prince <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi> bore to <hi>Policrite</hi> ſhe had thought it fitting to acquaint <hi>Policrite</hi> onely, that ſhe was more then what ſhe took her ſelf to be, to the end ſhe might know how to treat <hi>Philoxypes</hi> with more indifferency; and that ſhe might think her ſelf the leſs obliged to him for his affection: That <hi>Cleanthes</hi> and ſhe, having obſerved that this had produced a contrary effect in <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licrite,</hi> and Prince <hi>Philoxypes</hi> having ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed much paſſion in the laſt viſit which he made them, ſhe confeſt the ones worth, and the others youth had cauſed ſome ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion in her: that in purſuit here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, knowing that the King was at <hi>Claria,</hi>
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:151701:99"/>
and fearing leaſt <hi>Philoxypes</hi> might ſpeak to him of <hi>Policrites</hi> beauty, ſhe had advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Cleanthes</hi> to quit his abode, which in effect they had done, and were come to this little Maretine hamlet where <hi>Clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes</hi> was acquainted with an old Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who had left them his hut, being himſelfe gone to live with a ſon of his: that they had left a young Slave at their former place of abode, with direction, That if <hi>Solon</hi> ſhould come thither, he ſhould wiſh him to come the firſt day of the next enſuing moon to a Temple which they named unto him, where <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anthes</hi> would not fail to be on the ſame days to meet him when he ſhould come thither.</p>
            <p>That ſince that time, <hi>Cleanthes</hi> had learnt by the Prieſt of the little Temple which was near their former abode, that this Slave was dead; ſo as knovving that the time of <hi>Solons</hi> return drevv near, <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anthes</hi> reſolved to go live himſelf alone at <hi>Paphos,</hi> knovving that vvhen he ſhould return to <hi>Cyprus,</hi> he vvould not fail to vvait upon the King, and ſo he could not miſs of him; to vvhich purpoſe he was gone thither that very morning: that <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licrite,</hi>
               <pb n="183" facs="tcp:151701:99"/>
who had no better paſtime, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſince they had left their former abode, then to draw every day ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing or other upon her Tablebooks: ſeeing all the fiſher men were gone from their little hamlet, leaving no boat behinde them, ſave that wherein they had ſeen her, and wherein there was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Rudder nor Oare, ſate down in it, and not minding whether it were well faſtened to the ſhore or no, was deſigning forth that little rural float of boats which went ſtill further from her: that ſhe was ſo attentive to her work in hand, that as ſhe her ſelf had told them, ſhe did not perceive the boat wherein ſhe was, was looſened from the land, and went float<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as the winds blew it: ſo as ſaid <hi>Megiſto,</hi> coming forth to look after <hi>Polycrite,</hi> I ſaw her in the poſture I have told you, and skreek'd out ſo loud, as I made her perceiv the danger ſhe was in, not being able to help her, there not being one man left it the whole Ham let; and all the fiſher boa, having already doubled a Cape of land whereby we loſt ſight of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Megiſto</hi> having ended her relation, <hi>Solon</hi> gan admire the Providence of the Gods
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:151701:100"/>
in the guidance of worldly things; and conſidering that unleſs <hi>Philoxipes</hi> and he had loſt their way, <hi>Policrite</hi> in all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance had been loſt, he could not ſufficiently praiſe the Goddeſs, who had ſo well receiv'd his ſacrifice; in effect, this Temple of <hi>Venus Urania,</hi> hath got much renown by this adventure. But Sir! to abuſe your patience no longer, I will only tell you, that inſtead of going to <hi>Paphos, Philoxypes</hi> and <hi>Solon</hi> went the next day to <hi>Claria,</hi> whether they brought <hi>Megiſto, Policrite, Dorida,</hi> and all the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that attended them, after that <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loxypes</hi> had largely rewarded all the fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ermens wives for their Hoſpitality and curteſie ſhewed to <hi>Policrite.</hi> To tell you how great <hi>Philoxypes</hi> and <hi>Policrites</hi> joy was, would be no eaſie matter, and to relate unto you in what terms this happie Lover expreſt his ſatisfaction to <hi>Policrite,</hi> and with what an obliging mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty ſhe received the teſtimony of his affection, and gave him ſome marks of hers, would be to undertake to diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult a task. For to learn in one and the ſame day, that ſhe was daughter to the ſo Illuſtrious <hi>Solon,</hi> and that ſhe was to
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:151701:100"/>
be wife to <hi>Philoxypes,</hi> were two things wherewith her ſoul was divided. <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xypes</hi> failed not to ſhew <hi>Policrite</hi> her pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures in his Gallery, which though rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handſome, came much ſhort of her. The next day <hi>Solon</hi> ſent to enquire out <hi>Cleanthes</hi> at <hi>Paphos,</hi> where he was found and brought to <hi>Claria.</hi> Neceſſary order being taken for it, <hi>Cleanthes, Megiſto, Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite,</hi> and <hi>Dorida,</hi> had cloathes made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to their condition.</p>
            <p>The next morning the princeſs of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamis,</hi> and the Princeſs <hi>Agheriſta,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing advertiſed by their brother <hi>Philoxy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes</hi> of the truth of his adventure: theſe two fair Princeſſes, I ſay, who loved him dearly, who had learned <hi>Policrytes</hi> illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious birth by this advertiſement, and who did reverence <hi>Solon</hi> as a God, went to <hi>Claria,</hi> to conduct this beautiful crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to <hi>Paphos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But good Gods! how they were ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized with her extream beauty, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which with her Pictures they found her to exceed them far; but if ſhe appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed fair unto them, ſhe ſeemed yet more ſpiritual.</p>
            <p>She had ſomwhat in her of admirable
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:151701:101"/>
modeſty, which having nothing in it of Ruſtick, rendred her yet more pleaſing: ſhe had a ſoul doubtleſly, fraught with all that innocency which ſhee had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved amidſt thoſe Rocks: but withall a minde and humour wherein were all the Charms which the Court could af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Megiſto</hi> being rightly <hi>Solons</hi> ſiſter, knew as wel as any one what was requiſit in, and did neceſſarily become thoſe of her Sex, and had perfectly inſtructed <hi>Policrite</hi> therein.</p>
            <p>Young <hi>Dorida</hi> appeared alſo to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fair, and lovely at the Court, where the King received <hi>Solon, Cleanthes, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſto, Philoxypes,</hi> and <hi>Policrite,</hi> with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſable joy and honor. And this ſo much the more, as that being at laſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to content Princeſs <hi>Aretaphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> Ambition, that ſo he might ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his own Love, had made her be told the day before, that it ſhould be her fault if ſhe were not Queen.</p>
            <p>But if <hi>Aretaphile</hi> were Queen of <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus, Policrite</hi> was the Queen of Beauty; none but the Princeſs of <hi>Salamis</hi> could any ways diſpute that glorious Empire
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:151701:101"/>
with her. In fine, Sir, there was nothing heard of now, but feaſts and rejoycing. <hi>Solon</hi> being of neceſſity to be gon, they haſted the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſummation of theſe famous marriages: The King would have one Ceremony ſerve for them both; nor did <hi>Cyprus</hi> ever ſee any thing of more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, though it were done with preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitation. <hi>Solon</hi> called then to minde <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pimenides</hi> his predictions, and confeſt there was ſomewhat of Divine in that holy man. But his Countries intereſt prevailing more with him, then vvhatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever other intereſts, he departed for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens,</hi> ſo as ſome tears of ſorrovv did for a vvhile a little allay <hi>Policrite</hi>'s Joy; but to comfort her, young <hi>Dorida</hi> vvas left vvith her, vvhen <hi>Cleanthes</hi> and <hi>Megiſto</hi> imbarkt themſelves with <hi>Solon.</hi> This was the condition Sir, wherein this great man left the Court of <hi>Cyprus:</hi> to vvit, the King highly content: Queen <hi>Areta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phile</hi> as highly ſatisfied, and <hi>Philoxypes</hi> and <hi>Policrite</hi> ſo happie, as vviſhes could not add thereunto.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
